<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: risk management | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/risk-management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-10T23:30:15+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Risk management]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/risk-management/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-25T22:57:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/risk-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have never learn to how control risk in my education. Recently, several things I experienced force me to pay more attention to this issue.</p>

<p>After watched a film "Mongol", I want to use my iphone to contact my family. But I can't find it. I used to put it on my desk or pocket, but it is not there. I checked a lot of other places, the bed, drawers, kichens, even closet and clothes. It still didn't show up. I began to worry about it, I felt my heart beating quickly, I wondered if I lost it in my road back from food store. It would be a disaster if I really lost it, because many personal information was in it.</p>

<p>I sit down infront of the desk and tried to calm down. I still could not figure out where it can be left. Suddenly an idea come to my mind, how can i check out if the phone was in my hourse using wifi. Could I try to contack the person who found it? So I trun on my computer and use QQ(a kind of software like skype) to send a message to my iphone. The messeage said "Could you return my iphone?", then I clicked sent button and heared a sound in the room. It was from my phone. I tried to send again and listen where the sound come from. Finally I found my phone lay on the carpet under my bed. It must slip onto the carpet from my bed.</p>

<p>I had a great relief. Then I began to think what to do to reduce the risk of losing my iphone. How to keep my personal informaton safer. I read serveral posts on tips to keep your iphone safe. They suggested first you should set a password for unlocking. Then you can also install an app called "find my iphone" to locate your phone in case you lost it. The last suggestion is do not keep important personal information in your phone.</p>

<p>In fact, all these tips are trying to control the risk or reduce the risk. In dealiing with risk, we have serveral options, sometimes we have to accept it, there are always a risk that you can do nothing to control, e.g. traffic accident. In this case, people usually buy insurance to transfer the risk to insurer. We can also take some measures to ruduce the risk, such as put a piece of paper with your email or address at the back of your phone. If somebody find your phone, he or she may return it to you according to the information you provided. I found I need to learn more about risk management and get prepared for any risk in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
