<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: publication | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/publication/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-14T19:23:03-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing paper for publication]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-14T10:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing is an very important skill as speaking. It aims to send message, from generation to generation, from people to people, from country to country. One of the most effienct way to do this is publishing in good journals. Nowadays, publication has become a crucial part of resume or CV, and people write paper not just for sending message by also seeking for fame and honor. So good universitis ask faculties for good papers; good researchers look for good journals. Good journals want good impators or indexs. Reseachers like to cite papers from good journals. It would be good if this system can really help sending necessary message to people with various needs. But we should keep in mind that it may not necessarily be the case. It is just a number game.</p>

<p>Complain is enough. We still have to write. But I believe we are writing for our audiences not for universitis and journal companies. We write because we have the impluse to share. As a begining researcher and writer, I'd like to co-write with others at first. It helps me learn writing faster and have meaningful conversations with other people. So I would also recommand others doing it this way.</p>

<p>Athough you may not like the game, it is still good to know the rules and some tools. Here are some useful resources for writhing educational journals:</p>

<h3>Writing tools and tips:</h3>

<p>[Google Drive] can help you co-write online.<br/>
[Mendeley] can help you manage your references.<br/>
[HisCite] can make graph to let you know how paper cited each other.<br/>
[SPSS] can help you analyze the data.<br/>
<a href="http://latex-project.org/intro.html">LaTeX</a> is a good document preparation system especially useful when you have lots of equations and graphs(generated with R).<br/>
There are lots of other text editors such as Miscro-soft Word, EditPlus for consider.</p>

<h3>Useful books for formating:</h3>

<p>[Publication Menual by APA]<br/>
<a href="http://www.apastyle.org/">APA Style website</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Writing-Well-30th-Anniversary-Edition/dp/0060891548">On Writing Well</a> by Zinsser</p>

<h3>Journal impactor Search Engines:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.scimagojr.com/journalrank.php?area=0&amp;category=3304&amp;country=all&amp;year=2012&amp;order=sjr&amp;min=0&amp;min_type=cd">Journal Rankings on Education</a><br/>
<a href="http://admin-apps.webofknowledge.com/JCR/JCR?RQ=LIST_SUMMARY_JOURNAL">Web of Science JCR-WebSearch Engine</a></p>

<h3>Journals List and impactor(2012 JCR Social Science Edition):</h3>

<p>REVIEW OF EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH 4.2
Journal of the Learning Sciences 3.0
JOURNAL OF RESEARCH IN SCIENCE TEACHING 2.5
SCIENCE EDUCATION 2.4
Journal of Teacher Education 1.6
JOURNAL OF COMPUTER ASSISTED LEARNING 1.6
INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.3
British Journal of Educational Technology 1.3
TEACHING AND TEACHER EDUCATION 1.2
RESEARCH IN SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.1
TEACHERS AND TEACHING 0.5</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
