<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: inquiry | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/inquiry/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-30T17:06:57+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inquiry and demonstration]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T14:15:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Dr. Oliver gave us an amazing class about demonstration and inquiry. He first asked what question to think about or ask ourselves when using demonstration. Then we played two demonstration games with everybody totally engaged.</p>

<p>The first is radiometer (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crookes_radiometer">Crookes radiometer - Wikipedia</a>).<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/radiometer.jpg" alt="Crookes Radiometer" /></p>

<p>He just put it on a table and lighted up another bulb, it began to rotate. It was my first time to see this, I was very curious of its work principle. After close observation, I found that it rotated always the same direction with white vane in front and black vane behind.</p>

<p>Then we began to wonder what factors caused the vanes to rotate. Lights? But how? Temperature? how? What else? How can we found out? Try it. I tried using different angles of the light.</p>

<p>We also tried to use hot water and cold water to pure on it. It rotate exactly the same direction as using light when using hot water but the opposite direction when using cold water.<br/>
Nobody came up with a good explantion at the end. First I thought it was because the momentum of the absorbed Photon just like Crookes did which was wrong in this situation.</p>

<p>Then we began to do another game --Buoyancy.<br/>
First Dr. Oliver sent out a pre-test with 3 yes no questions about buoyancy followed why you believe so. Then we talked about each question a little while. Students answers and opinions are totally different.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pre-test.png" alt="Pre-test" /><br/>
Let us found out. So he did another demonstration droppiing a brass cube into water cup which had been balanced. He asked us what would happen if he immersed it into the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/drop-into-water.png" alt="Brass cube into water" /><br/>
We made our predictions and then we did the experiment. We also tried some other settings which were carefully designed but playfully demonstrated.How do you use these demonstration in large class size like 30 students?</p>

<p>At the end of the class, he use his front pocket quesitons to reflect this lesson:<br/>
Does it elict students' ideas for teaching?<br/>
Does it it help student make sense of the material activity?<br/>
Dose it press students for evidenced based reasoning and communicating?</p>

<p>Yes it does! Yeah, we succeed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Molecular Workbench——在交互模拟中学习科学]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/12/15/molecular-workbench-learn-science-in-interactive-model/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-15T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/12/15/molecular-workbench-learn-science-in-interactive-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天收到一封邮件，大意是说Concord Consortium从google.com获得了250万美元的奖励。<br /><br />Concord的分子工作台项目非常让人耳目一新，它将动画模拟、交互、游戏、评价融为一体，此外你还可以根据自己的需求定做和创造适合自己的模型。下面是他们的网站：<br /><br />Molecular Workbench - An Interface to the Molecular World<br />: http://mw.concord.org/modeler/<br /><br />你只需要下载一个Java的程序，就可以在线使用这些交互动画和学习资源。其实类似的项目，曾经也介绍过一个:<br />PhET Interactive Simulations 交互式模拟——在游戏操作中学习 - Open Learning<br />: http://open-learning.appspot.com/131.html<br /><br />不知道两者有怎样的关系？<br /><br />其实作为科学教师，虽然不一定会编程、会做动画，但是要让最新的教学资源和科研成果为己所用，也不失为优秀教师。而我们的教师教育也在这些方面也应该给予相应的关注。<br /><br /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[会心跳的空调]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/11/30/the-heart-beat-of-airconditioner/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/11/30/the-heart-beat-of-airconditioner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天天气不好，一直下着小雨，雨不是很大，但是借着较强的风势，横飞乱舞，打着伞身子也会被淋湿了一半。回到家，坐在办公桌前面打开电脑，正准备做一个flash演示文稿模板，突然听到一种很奇怪的声音，嘭~啪~嘭~啪~，周而复始，有点像流水的声音，又好像似一个人的心跳，但是家里明明只有我一个人。<br /><br />于是仗着胆子站起身来，细听声音的来处，原来就是侧对着办公桌的哪个空调发出的声音。好奇怪啊，这个空调明明没有开，怎么会有声音呢。外面的风刮的更厉害了，又传来了嘭啪嘭啪的声音，于是猜想是不是与这风有关系呢？本来想静下来做点事情的，这个空调老是给我执照噪音怎么行呢，于是就开始想解决的办法。<br /><br />我猜想可能是风速变化很大，时快时慢，使得空调的循环管受的压力不断变化，进而造成里面的液体的震荡所以产生了这种类似“心跳”的声音。加入这种猜想成立的话，如何解决呢? 首先想到的是用一个大塑料袋子把空调的风扇整个包起来来，这样这个风扇的管道就不对外开放了，但是找了一会没找到合适的袋子，而且风扇在阳台栏杆的外面，需要越过栏杆才能将其罩住，栏杆很脏，而且有一定危险性，于是放弃了这种方法。那么怎么办呢？<br /><br />仔细想了一下，由于天气有点冷，房子的门窗都关着，整个房子就好像一个秘密的容器，只有空调的循环管与外面相连，由于风速变化造成压力变化，所以会传来空调的心跳声。对了，如果我在打开一个通道不久行了嘛，于是我就把阳台的拉门打开了，果然空调的心跳停下来了，问题解决！<br /><br /><br /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
