<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: assessment | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/assessment/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-15T23:00:12+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assess for Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/14/assess-for-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-14T13:06:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/14/assess-for-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to a the seminar <a href="http://www.ctl.uga.edu/node/486">Teaching and Assessing so Your Students Learn More: Maximizing Learning-Centered Pedagogy</a> by Dr. Phyllis Blumberg.</p>

<p>We did some interactive activities,such as drawing a picture of learning-centered teaching, think and discuss, group disscussion of a special topic and report. I attended the discussion of how to use assessment to promote students' learning with 6 people.</p>

<p>Although most participants are college faculties, but when assigned to group work, some tend to speak more than the others, unaware of someone not speaking a word. I want to rearrange the process by divided into two small groups, but I feel hard to interupt and unsure which way will work better. Athough we do discussed sometimes one student dominates the group work and coversation, some people are too shy to say anything. You see, sometimes people say it but not do it and even unaware of this inconsistence.</p>

<p>There are various assessments that can be used for different purposes.<br/>
Before class you can give students questiong to guide their reading and explore their prior ideas.</p>

<pre><code>multiple choice question  
guiding questions  
open questions  
Dilemma  
Senario  
judgement  
</code></pre>

<p>In class, you can give student short quiz to know if students get the point of if they are able to apply them.</p>

<pre><code>Clicker  
Online analysis  
Open questions and discussion  
short quiz  
Drawing      
</code></pre>

<p>After class, assignments can help students review, exercise and enhance what they learned.</p>

<pre><code>Online assessment  
observation  
hand-on  
Reading  
Design  
Problem soving  
exercise  
learning activities judgement and improvement  
</code></pre>

<p>Final exam can report students' acheivement.</p>

<pre><code>interview(when there are only several students, this would be a good choice)  
project(which let student really take the ownership)  
write a paper/story  
design  
make vedio/prezi  
oral presentation/defence  
Fair or competition  
Paper exam  
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
