<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: reflection | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/reflection/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-29T21:57:07+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elegy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/08/26/elegy/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T22:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/08/26/elegy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Elegy翻译为挽歌，是一部2008年的电影。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/elegy.jpg" alt="Elegy" />
Human is a kind of social animal that can not live alone. If he does live alone, he fades. When he interacts with others, he thrives.</p>

<p>In this sense, human being is like a neuron and the society is the neutral network.</p>

<p>Once I believe that I can think, but after carefully thinking I draw a conclustion that I can hardly thinking independently. For example, if live me alone in dark room I can think less and less.</p>

<p>In fact, people do not think, they just reflect or interact with the environment. This truth is hard to believe, but it is important to know if you really want to direct your life.</p>

<p>A philosopher once said that there are two kind of people in the world, those who divide things into two kinds and those do not. I don't know what the philosopher want to say, but the philosopher must be the former. There are both advantage and disadvantage in dividing things into two kinds.</p>

<p>There is an old saying in China, when the flower bloom pick it, do not wait untill it shrivels. God is a time keeper, he just counts and when he stop your life come to the end. When the time come, you may regret the stupid time you spend but nothing you can change. It is really a tragedy. Tragedy teach you the lesson.</p>

<p>In front of the god time keeper, you have to be honest to seek what you really want because you have to face yourself and you have only one chance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[生物学实验教学反思]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/03/11/biology-experimental-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-11T21:55:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/03/11/biology-experimental-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天，第一组完成了观察类实验，第一次进行实验往往是最具有挑战的。因为他们要现去摸索实验准备的过程，教学组织的过程，以及环境的布置和利用等。考虑到这些挑战的要素，对于新手教师来讲，应该说完成的还是很不错的。</p>

<p>第一小组的优点包括：<br/>
*   提前分工做了预实验和必要的准备工作，特别是实验材料的准备和探索工作。<br/>
*   认准准备了课件和学案。<br/>
*   从头到尾顺畅的进行衔接，一直到最后完成实验室的清理工作。</p>

<p>当然也存在一些可以提高的地方：<br/>
*   时间的把控和设计可以再紧凑一些，每个人讲解的时间，实验操作的时间，分析总结的时间，以及教学反馈的时间都要考虑在内。(下次我会让同学严格计时，或者带一个闹钟，模拟真实课堂的下课铃声情境)<br/>
*   预想实验教学可能出现的各种情况，在实验材料、活动组织、课件、语言等做好充分的准备。（在这个方面，其实可以鼓励他们进行预讲，预讲要求第二周的同学参与和反馈，这样第二周的学生也可以提前做实验准别，了解情况，同时也可以吸取上一周同学准备的经验）<br/>
*   可以预先布置学习任务、分发学案，并把实验设计、反思等及时更新到wikispaces上，督促大家做好实验预习。（wikispaces上的实验手册，很不明确，可以给他们设计一个表格，如课前阅读材料、准备或实验预习报告，课上活动任务及数据记录表格，作业布置等，这样他们就会明确要做哪些，不要做哪些，实验手册需要让研究生参与完善，如果可以的话）</p>

<p>在本次实验过程中，王星同学以及李娜、郑烨两位同学准备都较为充分，语言和教态也较为自然，值得表扬。其实为什么能脱稿，为什么能够应对各种突发状况，本质上离不开充分的准备。这种准备包括对内容的熟悉，对实验操作过程要点的熟悉，对学生特点和行为的预期等等。当然也离不开好的设计，好的设计一定是将内容、教法以及技术环境以较为合适的方式进行了融合的方案。因此大家也可以从这三个方面下下功夫。（要个每个同学一个metal的同时也有一个mission）</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
