<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: standards | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/standards/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-14T09:19:51-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[District standards and position description]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/18/district-standards-and-position-description/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T13:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/18/district-standards-and-position-description</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following is from the book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a>  .</p>

<h3>District standards of competent performance</h3>

<p>A standard is composed of three parts: a statement which establishes a general behavior, a list of indicators which specify how that behavior will be identified, and a principal's judgment as to the level of competent performance. The statement and indicators are listed for each standard. The level of expected performance of these standards will be determined by the professional judgment of the pnncipal. The judgment is influenced by the teacher's assignment, class size, experience, and available resources. To determine if the requirements of the standard have been met, the statement of general teacher behavior, all of the indicators, and the performance level must be considered.</p>

<p>Section I—Instructional development<br/>
Area: Diagnosing
Standard 1 The competent teacher establishes procedures for gathering data by<br/>
a. completing the diagnosis for each student<br/>
b. using the diagnostic tools which are pertinent to the teacher's goals<br/>
c. using a variety of diagnostic instruments and techniques<br/>
d. requesting assistance from others, when needed, for more comprehensive diagnosis</p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Standard 2 The competent teacher interprets diagnostic data to identify the needs and concerns of both the individual and the group by<br/>
a. identifying the achievement level of each student<br/>
b. explaining the significance of the achievement level diagnosed</p>

<p>Area: Prescribing<br/>
Standard 3 The competent teacher utilizes diagnostic data to establish instructional objectives and relates these to individual needs by<br/>
a. writing instructional objectives<br/>
b. preparing objectives that show the data gathered in diagnosis are utilized<br/>
c. preparing objectives in terms of student performance<br/>
d. preparing objectives that are measurable<br/>
e. preparing both short- and long-term objectives for any assigned class</p>

<p>Standard 4 The competent teacher plans lessons to meet individual and group needs by<br/>
a. planning lessons that are consistent with the objectives<br/>
b. planning lessons that include appropriate activities which meet individual and group needs<br/>
c. planning to use appropriate resource materials related to instructional objectives<br/>
d. planning alternatives to meet the needs of individual students<br/>
e. accepting and using student feedback in planning instruction</p>

<p>Area: Facilitating<br/>
Standard 5 The competent teacher utilizes knowledge of subject matter by<br/>
a. using words and content appropriate to the subject area and students' abilities<br/>
b. using available media effectively and efficiently<br/>
c. requesting and using materials and facilities based on instructional objectives<br/>
d. knowing and utilizing community agencies, groups, and individuals to further the educational
program</p>

<p>Standard 6 The competent teacher uses effective classroom management techniques by<br/>
a. showing respect for students<br/>
b. providing an atmosphere in which students remain at task<br/>
c. exhibiting consistency when dealing with behavior problems<br/>
d. exhibiting positive verbal and nonverbal influence on students</p>

<p>Standard 7 The competent teacher applies learning theory by<br/>
a. utilizing and building upon students' interests and prior knowledge<br/>
b. providing feedback as students progress toward goals<br/>
c. allowing for a balance between intake of information and the expression of student ideas<br/>
d. providing the individual with activities to develop attitudes, appreciations, and values</p>

<p>Standard 8 The competent teacher uses a variety of instructional techniques appropriate to the students' needs by<br/>
a. giving directions in a clear, concise manner<br/>
b. phrasing questions so students may respond appropriately<br/>
C. using strategies which involve students in higher levels of thinking<br/>
d. pacing the activities within a lesson according to the needs of students</p>

<p>Area: Student Performance Evaluation<br/>
Standard 9 The competent teacher establishes procedures for assessing student performance by<br/>
a. selecting means of evaluation which are appropriate to the objectives<br/>
b. planning measurement procedures for specific purposes<br/>
C. utilizing procedures whereby students receive feedback on their individual performance<br/>
d. presenting information that indicates evaluation has taken place for each student</p>

<p>Standard 10 The competent teacher interprets the results of student performance assessment by<br/>
a.identifs ing the reasons why students have or have not met the performance objectives</p>

<p>Standard 11 The competent teacher utilizes the results of student performance assessment by<br/>
a. using objective data to arrive at a grade or indicator of student progress to be reported to parents and student<br/>
b. providing feedback that facilitates the student accomplishment of goals.<br/>
c. planning changes in teaching strategies based on the results of the evaluation.</p>

<p>Section II—Professional development<br/>
Area: Communication<br/>
Standard 12 The competent teacher communicates effectively with students by<br/>
a. listening to and considering student comments and suggestions<br/>
b. being open to suggestions about ways in which to present material<br/>
c. conveying an attitude that promotes participation in activities<br/>
Standard 13 The competent teacher communicates effectively with colleagues and staff by<br/>
a. participating in the group decision-making process<br/>
b. listening to and considering suggestions from the staff<br/>
c. sharing ideas and resources with others</p>

<p>Standard 14 The competent teacher communicates responsibly to the public the significance of the school program by<br/>
a. answering parents' inquiries promptly, honestly, and discretely<br/>
b. initiating when necessary communication with parents<br/>
c. having available or locating information to relate district philosophy to the community at large</p>

<p>Area: School Relationships<br/>
Standard 15 The competent teacher has a consistent and professional attitude toward accomplishment of own school goals by<br/>
a. contributing to the decision-making process and abiding by group decisions
b. accepting shared responsibilities in and out of the classroom during the school day
c. maintaining consistency in record keeping as defined by building or district administrative regulations and procedures<br/>
d. using adopted courses of study or adjusting teaching objectives to include such adoptions<br/>
e. carrying out reasonable requests given by proper authority</p>

<p>Standard 16 The competent teacher has a consistent and professional attitude toward the accom
plishment of district and state goals by<br/>
a adhering to and enforcing school law, state board regulations, school board policy, and established administrative procedures.<br/>
b. adhering to the Employee Conduct and Responsibility requirements as stated in the Board Policy Handbook.</p>

<p>Source: Adapted from Beaverton, Oregon Schools Personnel Handbook.</p>

<h3>Position description</h3>

<p>Position: Teacher
Reports to: Principal (or His/Her Designee)
Position Purpose:
Implements, supervises, and maintains a high quality learning environment Tor students within the specific curriculum and standards of the district.<br/>
Nature and Scope:
The teacher is a professional with the responsibility for implementing a curriculum. Inherent in this responsibility is the requirement of related academic knowledge, technical skills, and professional attitudes and judgments.<br/>
The teacher must have the ability to diagnose the needs of learners and to evaluate their performance. The teacher must also be able to prescribe learning activities appropriate to student needs and to constructively evaluate these activities. The teacher effects an optimum learning climate through appropriate and maximum use of all resources available, and through the use of effective instructional and classroom management techniques.<br/>
In addition to the requirement of technical competence, the teacher maintains an attitude and
conduct which is consistent with the district policy of professional conduct. The teacher follows building and district procedural guidelines and policy.<br/>
Primary Accountabilities:
1. Identifies the needs of students through diagnostic procedures and relates instructional objectives to these needs. Plans, prepares, and executes appropriate lessons, utilizing appropriate resource materials and activities.<br/>
2. Maintains student records as required by the school.<br/>
3. Communicates with parents, students, and other professional staff regarding student progress(behavioral and academic).<br/>
4. Follows a curriculum that is prescribed by state, district, or building.<br/>
5. Assures students of learning opportunities within a classroom environment that facilitates learning.<br/>
6. Meets the district's Standards of Competent Performance at all times.<br/>
7. Follows district and school policies, procedures, rules, regulations, and guidelines and the provisions of the contract.</p>

<p>Source: School District 48J, Beaverton, OR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
