<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: content knowledge | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/content-knowledge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-24T17:26:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The ways that content knowledge matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/the-ways-that-content-knowledge-matters/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T21:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/the-ways-that-content-knowledge-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Question:<br/>
What an expert teacher who has deep content knowledge can do?</p>

<p>Notes in class Supervision:<br/>
-give more proper instances, analogys to make student understand clearly<br/>
-relate the knowledge with students lives<br/>
-pick out the important big ideas that organizing the knowledge feild<br/>
-be able to emphasize crosscutting concepts
-be competent in science practices<br/>
-design more logical sequence of the content knowledge<br/>
-be able to understand students' difficulties and questions and has a clue</p>

<p>Additional ways(after class):<br/>
-ask good questions<br/>
-design sound learning activities and assignments<br/>
-have insights of students question or problems<br/>
-organize facts and concepts in a sense making way or framework<br/>
-have more backup examples,analogys, explainations, questions for use<br/>
-be confident to give students more opotions and more challeging jobs</p>

<p>In a word, content knowledge affect teachers' abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driver. The driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
