<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: TED | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/ted/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-02-13T01:23:42+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do the job or have fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/do-the-job-or-have-fun/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T19:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/do-the-job-or-have-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes when something becomes your job, even you love it, when you have to do if before a deadline, you tend to lose the fun you had before.</p>

<p>Something you don't have to do it, but you are interested and want to try. You are more likely to do better and have a lot of fun.</p>

<p>As a teacher, how do you apply this rule to your teaching?</p>

<p>Is it the reason why teacher drop out in their early career?</p>

<p>How to let teachers have fun in their teaching?</p>

<p>How to let students have fun in their learning?</p>

<p>Why people have fun in doing something? The following is a list of "something" can offer:<br/>
1. Provide new/pleasant experience<br/>
People are born with curiosity, and love to have new experience. They like to do the thing they have never done before or doing the same thing but in new ways.<br/>
2. Engage emotion<br/>
Passion, curiosity, sense of acheivement even superiority are all emotions letting people have fun. So if the design can engage these emotions, then it becomes hot.<br/>
3. Match their habits and mindset<br/>
They don't need to take much effort in order to operate or understand. It is user friendly designed.<br/>
4. Meet various needs<br/>
5. Be simple and neat</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't alienate disabled people]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/27/dont-alienate-disabled-people/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T09:46:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/27/dont-alienate-disabled-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, a TED talk at TEDxStanford moved me deeply. It was given by Rhodes Scholar Rachel Kolb -- who was born deaf. She showed what is possible through family support and self-belief, and proves that what is assumed about you and what you can actually achieve don't always match up. In the United States, two-thirds of hearing-impaired people do not complete high school.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/uKKpjvPd6Xo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<!--more-->


<p>When I attended a coteaching workshop, an American teacher asked me if there were any disabled students in Chinese schools. I said very few. In my experiences, from elementary school to high school, even in university, I had never meet a disabled students, who was deaf or blind. Where are they? They do exist, but may live alienated lives out of our eyes.</p>

<p>In UGA, I saw many students sitting on their wheelchairs in streets, classroom, libraries, even on buses. They really provide good access for disabled.</p>

<p>In China, the situation in Beijing and Shanghai may be better than other cities. But we still hardly see disabled people appear in front us, when they do appear, they usually have many accompanies who help them to overcome the unexpected obstacles posed by people unconsciously.</p>

<p>Disabled people do deserve to live a normal life. Please don't alienate them!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
