<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reflection | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/reflection/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-08-07T13:54:20+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Great Teachers' Great Power]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2019/04/25/great-teachers-great-power/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-25T11:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2019/04/25/great-teachers-great-power</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The title of this post is a little exaggerated. What I am really going talk about is teachers' power of affecting students.</p>

<p>Maybe you already know who am I, sicne leaders talk about leaderships, teachers talk about teaching, yes, I am a teacher.</p>

<p>As a teacher, I do care about what am I doing wether can help or have good impacts on my students. As a teacher, I also have studied many expert teachers, I saw what they can do and what they can achieve. But I bemome more puzzled how they did it. In fact, I have many answers, expert teachers have passion in teaching and in their jobs, expert teachers have solid content knowledge, expert teachers have good relationships with their students, expert teachers also teach hard. Is it enough, no, I don't think these answers have alread revealed the whole picture. I want to see teachers real power.</p>

<p>One thing we have forget is teacher-student interactions, influences can not exist without these interactions, so not only teachers but also students should be putted into our visions. Then we might see teachers' power.</p>

<p>POWER=Patience + Opportunity + Wisdom + Envision + Redirect</p>

<p>Here is a short explanation:</p>

<ol>
<li>Good teachers like good hunters, they have great patience with their students. They know it take time to really understand a person. They also know to wait untill the best opportunity appear.</li>
<li>Good teachers are good at taking opportunity to communicate with their students rather than preach without considering student status and feelings.</li>
<li>Good teacher have wisdom. That means they are robots following the rules, they know when to change the rules or create new rules.</li>
<li>Good teacher use their wisdom to enable student to see the whole picture. In this way, students can envision the status of themselves, and do what is necessary to make a change.</li>
<li>Easier said than done. Good teacher set a model for his students which can guide students to redirect their paths of life.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now, you know the teachers' power. Now you know the importance of teachers' job. Now you know why I am writing this post.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
