<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-09T09:34:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[我们能从巴西对德国的比赛学到什么]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/07/09/world-cup-brazil-vs-germany/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-09T09:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/07/09/world-cup-brazil-vs-germany</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>世界杯半决赛，德国7:1完胜巴西。说实话，我不是足球迷，也并不总是支持某个国家队（中国除外）。我觉得德国的胜利是足球文化的胜利，集体足球完胜个人足球。</p>

<p>一般的足球比赛运气可以决定七层的胜负，但是这场足球比赛刚好反过来。本届的巴西队拖泥带水的进入了半决赛，防守早就暴漏了诸多问题。进攻也缺乏新意，前锋一得到球就低头往前带，带到四周都是对方球员，把球丢掉或者射偏。很少有默契而精准的配合，更缺乏冷静的头脑和宽阔的视野，急切和愤怒让巴西成了一个二流球队。反观德国队，集体配合打的娴熟、精准、巧妙，球员非常的冷静，视野开阔，再加上德国哪种顽强，把巴西的后防线冲得落花流水。</p>

<p>足球，本质上是一项情绪游戏。球员经过刻苦的训练一般是具有技术的，但是情绪却直接决定其发挥的程度和发挥的方式。中国足球走不过国门，除了体制问题外，情绪控制是不可忽略的要素。当一个队太想赢，有太多的利益和压力让它赢，它反而会输掉比赛。米卢的“快乐足球”不得不说是针对中国队员情绪控制能力差的情况而设计的。一项复杂的进攻，往往需要冷静的头脑才能完成。而一心想进球的念头，想赢球的迫切，怕输球的后果，会让球队彻底沦为一个二流球队。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demonstration of barometric pressure using a bottle of water]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T19:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Oliver gave us an assignment to design a demonstration of science teaching. I already had several ideas. One was show them <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/">The surprising trees</a>. Another one was rolling a paper roll. The last one was the bottle water activity.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bottle-water-demonstration.png" alt="bottle water demonstration" /><br/>
Today, when I was on the road home after swimming. I couldn&#8217;t stop thinking a more neat idea and keep revising the activity. I was very tired because of swimming but my thinking keep running in my head, even on bed with windows closed and curtain down. I imagined what the scene would be like, what to say, what to do, in what order, what questions to ask. I even came up with a little poem and dialogue:</p>

<pre><code>Needle needle hot
Let the water jet out
Jet out, jet out
Oh my God
Nothing happen

Wait a minute, let me check out...
Hymn
Why
Maybe we need the hole more lower
Let me make another hole

Hymn
Maybe the we can lay down the bottle
Hymn
Let me think, drawing the hole of water on blackboard,talk to myself

Maybe we can make both the holes open
Maybe we can check out in the up-stand position
Why?
Why in this position it work
In this position it doesn't work
Did you see that?
So when will the water come out? 
One open hole or two? In which position? In which hole does the water come out?
How do you explain this?
Why one hole doesn't work?
Why two holes on the same height also doesn't work?
Why the two holes need to be on different height?
</code></pre>

<p>Finally, the design finished and the thinking stopped. This is the reason why I don&#8217;t write at night. Thinking will not let me sleep.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The surprising trees]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T16:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A tree can have its own home.<br/>
It can also step over the wall.<br/>
A tree can free your minds.<br/>
It can also make the spirit call.<br/>
A tree can become your home.<br/>
And you will never forget it anymore.</p>

<p>The tree that owns itself.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-owns-itself.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that steps over the wall.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/the-tree-step-over-wall.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/the-tree-step-over.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that frees your mind.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-free-your-mind.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-free-your-mind2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that touchs your soul.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-touch-you.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree can be your home and you will not forget it anymore.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/home-tree.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[美鸟掠影]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/21/birds-in-usa/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T10:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/21/birds-in-usa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在Bell食品超市里大概有20排货架，摆满了面包、罐头、调料等食杂用品，在特定的货架上还可以买到药膏、洗发水等生活用品。有两排货架很特殊，摆满了各式各样的、各种品牌的狗食。在堆放各种新鲜水果、蔬菜的地方，货架下面还放满了鸟食，只不过以前我一直不知道它是鸟食。虽然我经常光顾这个商店，但是确是在半年之后偶然发现这些鸟食，或者说是再发现。开始的时候，我只是感到奇怪，为什么美国人也喜欢把各种谷物混杂在一起卖，难道美国人也喜欢喝粥？直到我起了喝粥的念头，仔细观察这些装着五颜六色各种谷物的袋子，才发现上面都印着鸟的图案，原来是给鸟准备的营养大餐。</p>

<p>中国以前经常批判资本主义社会“重狗轻人”，现在可能还会有人再加一条“重鸟轻人”。不过如果你仔细的想一想，如果在一个国度人们爱狗、爱鸟爱到这样的地步，它又有什么理由会比“吃狗打鸟”的国家更轻视人的尊严和权利呢。当然，你不能排除这些爱狗爱鸟的国家里也有种族歧视者，也不能排除吃狗打鸟的国家里也有环境保护者。在美国歧视是非常严重的问题，任何歧视的言论或者行为都会导致公众和舆论的攻击。在《民主的细节》一书里又很多实例，比如美国的电影里黑人的角色几乎都是正义的，因为他们怕烙下种族歧视的话柄。名人，无论多有名、多有权，一旦有种族歧视的言论就离下台不远了。在UGA的校园里，我亲眼看到的，从公交车到教室再到食堂，每个细节的设计都考虑到了残疾人，而在中国，残疾儿童上学是困哪的，甚至打工子弟的就近入学也是困难的。毕业生找工作会遇到各种歧视，性别歧视、年龄歧视、健康歧视等等，而且这些歧视竟然是公开的。所以在“轻人”上面我们更多需要的是自我反思而不是责备他人。没有不喜欢自由飞翔和安全快乐的鸟，假如你是它们中的一员，你会选择定居何处？是什么影响了你的选择？可惜鸟是不会思考的，也不会选择，它们只能被动接受命运的安排。但是人不同，人可以选择，也可以改变环境。</p>

<p>在我的印象当中，美国的鸟是非常大胆的。它可以无视你的靠近，自在的在草丛中寻食。它可以落在你的舰艇上歇脚，俯视着船上的人类。它可以倒立着吃你在松塔里填埋的谷物，毫不担心陷阱。它可以把自己的巢搭在紧挨你橱窗的小树上，繁殖后代。</p>

<p>在Dr. Tippins的Ecojustice课上，一位同学（中学教师）教了我们如何给鸟制作Pinecone bird feeder,我叫它松塔糕。是在松塔上抹上粘稠的花生酱然后在各种谷物里打一个滚就成了。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pinecone-bird-feeder.png" alt="课上给鸟制作的松塔糕" /><br/>
之后，需要用一根细绳把这个松塔糕拴在树杈上，由于是靠一根细线悬垂的，所以松鼠和大鸟是很难够得着的。而小巧的雀儿却正合适，这可能是观鸟者想看到它们美丽的身影才这样设计的。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pinecone-bird-feeder-in-tree.png" alt="松塔糕拴在树上" /><br/>
我特意将这个松塔糕绑在窗前大树上，这样我从二楼的卧室里就可以看到鸟儿，一开始并没有鸟儿关顾，我还挺失望的，因为是春季，如果是在冬季食物短缺的时候会很快又鸟儿光顾的。但是我并没有白忙活，一天，一只很小的雀儿在松塔糕上忙活起来，它不断的变换着姿势。因为松塔糕是通过一根细线悬垂下来的，根本没有立足的地方，所以它不得不跟松塔糕一起荡秋千，像是马戏团耍杂技的一样不断的变换姿势和翻跟头。之后，不几天的功夫，沾满了各种谷物的松塔糕就被吃了个精光。制作松塔糕和观看鸟儿啄食的样子请移步这里<a href="http://www.mykidsadventures.com/pinecone-bird-feeder/">Pinecone Bird Feeder</a></p>

<p>我曾经到纽约观光，在自由女神观光船上无意中看到了一只白鸽落在舰艇的顶端歇息，于是我迅速拿出手机拍下照片。船上挤满了游客，这只鸟就居然这么大模大样的俯视着我们这些人类。它歇了一会，觉得无聊了，就飞走了。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dove-on-ship.png" alt="舰艇上的鸟" /></p>

<p>一天中午，在公寓厨房做饭的时候，我瞥见窗外树丛里落着一只腹白头红的鸟儿，触手可及，隔着窗纱也不害怕。其实以前也常看到这只鸟儿在这棵小树上穿梭，只是没有在意。由于我正在洗碗，熟练的很，所以不时抽眼向它望一望，我居然有一个新的发现，这个鸟儿总是从底下钻进树丛，然后向上一跳一跳的，像是上台阶，逗留一会就飞走了。不一会又飞回来了，仔细观察我才发现，它嘴巴里还叼着一个细树枝，这次我特别留心，我的目光紧随着它一次次向上攀移，最后停下来的小树叉上，居然凭空出现了一个窝，真是神奇。</p>

<p>清早起来，可能是昨晚忘了关窗户，各种鸟儿已经叽叽喳喳叫开了。我不知道还有多少人能在中国听到鸟儿清早的鸣唱？————无论你是在城市还是在农村。没了这动听的声音，孩子们的笔下是否会变得干涩？心头突然升起一个疑问：我们到底是从大自然里“获取了”还是“失去了”？</p>

<p>在这里儿，人类是鸟的朋友，但是鸟儿也有天敌。今天早上，我去准备自己的早餐，热一热昨天的剩饭。正在用微波炉的时候，我听见外面的鸟儿不停的、急切的、沙哑的叫着，透过窗子望去，一只松鼠正停在树杈上，四处张望，眼冒精光，这是我第一次近距离观察松鼠，它们一向在我走近前就会逃走、或者上树的，我平时还是比较喜欢这些可爱的松鼠的，但是今天这个面孔让我特别厌恶，我紧急的敲了几下窗沙，松鼠被我吓跑了，不一会哪只鸟又出现在窗前的小树上，头上红色的羽毛不住的颤动，还是那么一跳一跳的，上了四五个台阶，最后来到巢上巡视。我不知道我的干预是否及时，也不知道到巢中是否还有幸存的幼鸟，这只鸟俯下身去，小树和巢的双重遮掩让我什么也看不到。希望它们平安无事！</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coco Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/20/coco-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T11:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/20/coco-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today we did the coco experiment in Dr. Oliver&#8217;s Class. Here are some pictures.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/five-coco.png" alt="five-coco" /></p>

<p>The materials our group used:<br/>
  1. 5 bottles of coco (4 diet coco, 1 coco)<br/>
  1. 25 memos(5 fruit memos and 20 memos)<br/>
  1. 5 ml salt<br/>
  1. 1 measurer ruler<br/>
  1. 1 funnel</p>

<p>The 5 cocos were used as 5 experiment as control, coco, fruit memos, flat, salt. We measured the height of the coco before and after experiment, so we could count how much coco get out of the bottle. Here is what we got.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/coco-data.png" alt="data and figure" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inquiry and demonstration]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T14:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Dr. Oliver gave us an amazing class about demonstration and inquiry. He first asked what question to think about or ask ourselves when using demonstration. Then we played two demonstration games with everybody totally engaged.</p>

<p>The first is radiometer (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crookes_radiometer">Crookes radiometer - Wikipedia</a>).<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/radiometer.jpg" alt="Crookes Radiometer" /></p>

<p>He just put it on a table and lighted up another bulb, it began to rotate. It was my first time to see this, I was very curious of its work principle. After close observation, I found that it rotated always the same direction with white vane in front and black vane behind.</p>

<p>Then we began to wonder what factors caused the vanes to rotate. Lights? But how? Temperature? how? What else? How can we found out? Try it. I tried using different angles of the light.</p>

<p>We also tried to use hot water and cold water to pure on it. It rotate exactly the same direction as using light when using hot water but the opposite direction when using cold water.<br/>
Nobody came up with a good explantion at the end. First I thought it was because the momentum of the absorbed Photon just like Crookes did which was wrong in this situation.</p>

<p>Then we began to do another game &#8211;Buoyancy.<br/>
First Dr. Oliver sent out a pre-test with 3 yes no questions about buoyancy followed why you believe so. Then we talked about each question a little while. Students answers and opinions are totally different.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pre-test.png" alt="Pre-test" /><br/>
Let us found out. So he did another demonstration droppiing a brass cube into water cup which had been balanced. He asked us what would happen if he immersed it into the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/drop-into-water.png" alt="Brass cube into water" /><br/>
We made our predictions and then we did the experiment. We also tried some other settings which were carefully designed but playfully demonstrated.How do you use these demonstration in large class size like 30 students?</p>

<p>At the end of the class, he use his front pocket quesitons to reflect this lesson:<br/>
Does it elict students&#8217; ideas for teaching?<br/>
Does it it help student make sense of the material activity?<br/>
Dose it press students for evidenced based reasoning and communicating?</p>

<p>Yes it does! Yeah, we succeed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modify my previous lesson ESCI7040-A1]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an assignment of Dr. Oliver&#8217;s class ESCI7040(teaching strategies). The goal of this activity is to reflect on my own teaching and modify the plans for future teaching.</p>

<p>I taught learning theories to undergraduates in order to let them make sense of how students learn and apply these principles in their future teaching.</p>

<p>The guiding question is what is knowledge and how people learn? The big ideas include:<br/>
1. Different type of knowledge play different roles and people learn them differently.<br/>
2. Learning Science is not just learning scientific knowledge but also science practice and the nature of science.<br/>
3. Teacher need various types of knowledge to help students learn science.<br/>
4. Different learning theories understand people&#8217;s learning differently and give different suggestions for teaching and learning.<br/>
5. Preconceptions, learning styles, learning strategies play an important role in students&#8217; learning.</p>

<p>This lesson takes 90 minutes and during 60 minutes I was lecturing.</p>

<h3>Task1: Reflections of this lesson:</h3>

<ol>
<li>Wether the content of this lesson can effectively help them understand how students learn science and apply these principles in their teaching?<br/>
Some ideas are too general and loosely related. They should be deleted or modified.<br/>
You should focus more on students&#8217; learning not teachers&#8217; learning<br/>
Don&#8217;t try to cover every learning theories, teach the most important one and the crucial strategies or tools.<br/>
You may also included some brain-based learning studies such as how learning occur and what factors may affect learning.<br/>
Conceptual change should be included in this lesson.</li>
<li><p>Are these goals/objectives appropriate for your students?<br/>
These goals are not challenging enough for undergraduates. More critical thinking and challenging tasks should be used in this lesson.<br/>
You can try to related your teaching methods with learning principles and invite students to think both in the role of learners and teacher(your role).</p></li>
<li><p>How were the goals/objectives appropriate for the course in which the unit was taught?<br/>
I found that I simply followed the sequence of the textbook. I may first teach this lesson &#8216;learning theory&#8217; (Chapter 4) and then teach &#8216;teaching strategies&#8217;(Chapter 3). Students should first know how leaning happen and then learn how to teach.</p></li>
<li><p>How the instructional strategies adequate for the learning you hoped would happen?<br/>
Lecture should be more interactive(share learning experience of yours or students, thinking aloud, student teaching), include more student-centered activities (sorting learning tasks, diagnosing students&#8217; learning difficulties, think-pair-share, one minute writing, interpret teaching clips).</p></li>
<li><p>How were the assessments&#8211;either formal or informal&#8211;adequate(and valid and reliable) for the task of assessing student learning?<br/>
There are two assessments: A1 explain Osmosis to high school students; A2 design a 5E lesson plan. A1 is an informal assessment on class. A2 seems not closely related with this lesson. A better assignment would be study students&#8217; preconceptions about one topic and design an activity to elicit students prior ideas.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Task 2 redesign:</h3>

<h4>The big ideas that student should understand:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Learners build their knowledge on their prior knowledge collaboratively in special social context or situations.</li>
<li>Learning occur when connections are made in Neural Networks or social networks.</li>
<li>Well designed physical and social learning environment help students learn by improving their brains&#8217; function.</li>
<li>Prior ideas, emotion, metacogniton play crucial roles in students&#8217; science learning.</li>
<li>Different learning strategies suit for different learning tasks; Some tasks are more difficult than others; Student percept learning tasks differently.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The skills that student should develop:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Elicit and engage students&#8217; prior ideas of a core concept.</li>
<li>Diagnosis students&#8217; difficulties in learning a concept.</li>
<li>Design or redesign classroom learning environment to optimize students&#8217; learning.</li>
<li>Select proper learning strategies for special learning tasks.</li>
<li>Summary learning research results and its implications for teaching.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The interactive lecture and student activities:</h4>

<p>Tell the story of two kids arguing about sun:</p>

<pre><code>孔子到东方游历，遇见两个小孩在路上争辩，便问原因。一个小孩说：“太阳刚升起时距离人近。”另一个小孩说：“太阳中午的时候才距离人近呢。” 一个小孩又说：“不对，太阳刚升起的时候大得像个车盖，到了正午就小得像一个盘子，这不是远处的看着小而近处的看着大的道理吗？” 另一个小孩说：“太阳刚升起的时候清凉，到了中午的时候像手伸进热水里一样热，这不是近的时候感觉热而远的时候感觉凉的道理吗？”  
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/two-kids-argue-sun.png" alt="tow kids argue sun" /><br/>
Which kid do you agree with?<br/>
How about the situation of winter and summer?<br/>
If you are going to teaching these two kids the model of sun and earth, what are you going to do with these ideas? <br/>
Pretest: What do you know about learning? Yes or No question and why?<br/>
Learning occur easily and fast. Yes No<br/>
Learning is mainly remembering and recalling. Yes NO<br/>
Learning is a process that seldom change. Yes No<br/>
Learning ability can be enhanced though learning effort. Yes No<br/>
How this lesson Connect, extend or challenge what you know and how you teach?</p>

<p>Can you share a impressive learning experience that happened to you before? Or your most powerful learning strategy?</p>

<h4>Different types of learning:</h4>

<p>Learning subject: Machine learning, human learning, animal learning<br/>
Learning method: Discovery learning, guided discovery, inquiry-based learning, Problem-based learning; learning from instruction, rote learning, learning from examples, learning by analogy, explanation-based learning<br/>
Learning object: Conceptural learning(facts, concepts, model, theory), skill learning(process, strategies), emotion, attitude and value learning, metacognitive learning<br/>
Learning result: Deep learning, surface learning, meaningful learning,rote learning,effective or ineffective learning<br/>
Learning effort or emotion: hard learning, lazy learning, happy learning,painful learning<br/>
Learning sensory and style: eye, ear, feel, action, think, taste, smell</p>

<p>What can you learn from the following objective verb table?<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/objective-verb-table.png" alt="objective verbs table" /></p>

<ol>
<li><p>Think-pair-share<br/>
Read a research paper of misconception, write down all possible ways to elicit students&#8217; prior ideas, share with peers how these prior ideas are going to affect students&#8217; learning.</p></li>
<li><p>Ask a student to thinking aloud about a Buoyancy problem; Ask another student to think aloud about a phototropism problem; Ask the third student to think aloud about a NO2 chemical equilibrium problem. Interview them a little bit.</p></li>
<li><p>Share personal learning strategy (Chemical equilibrium).<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/no2.png" alt="NO2 Chemical equilibrium" /></p></li>
<li><p>One minute writing<br/>
Why students approach the same problem differently? How can you encourage deep learning?</p></li>
<li><p>Sorting learning tasks and matching with learning strategies.<br/>
List as many different types of learning tasks as you can in your group?<br/>
Group them as many ways as you can?</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Sorting learning tasks:<br/>
Write down the definition of enzyme.<br/>
Judge whether x is Enzyme or not.<br/>
Compare Plant and animal cell structures.<br/>
Draw the process of Mitosis.<br/>
Design the law of using human embryonic cells as research materials.<br/>
Count the Probability of a special Phenotype in the next generation.<br/>
Explain why egg shells are not too thin or too thick.</p>

<p>Learning strategies:<br/>
compare and group, summarize, visualize, hands-on, simplize, break down</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Student teaching one concept to other students or one screen to the class.<br/>
They need to be the volunteer and download the material and learn it before class, they have 3 minutes to help group members to understand this concept. Students will share their learning experience and give feedback to the volunteer teacher.</p></li>
<li><p>Diagnosing students&#8217; learning difficulties in a teaching clip.<br/>
Teacher will show a clip of real teaching, the students are asked to make sense what is happening and what to do with the situation.</p></li>
<li><p>Write one minute about what you learn or change today about learning, what is your most favorite analogy of learning now, share with your partner.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Task 3 reflect on why you change:</h3>

<p>My previous purpose is follow and cover the most important content both on the textbook and in my vision. I spent a lot of time on how to represent these content to students but did not pay too much attention to how these content serve the goal of this course. At that time, I did not have many activities to choose from and had to create my own one by one. I also had limited knowledge of how students learn science before, now I know more. So I want to include the more important ideas that I know and get rid of un important or unrelated ideas.</p>

<p>Although I believed that I should use more student-centered activities, but I just didn&#8217;t have them. It took time for me to gather, test, accumulate related activities or ideas. My enriched learning experiences and pedagogical thinking also help me to generate new activities that probably work for my students.</p>

<p>Recently, I read some papers and books about evidence-based teaching and brain-based learning, they also encourage me to select the core ideas and activities for my teaching plan.</p>

<p>Conclusion: If you want to improve your teaching practice, you need to know more about the content, more about your students, more about what you can possibly do and use in your class. Of course, you also have to know what student really learn and why they do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The tree that owns itself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/14/the-trees-that-owns-itself/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-14T14:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/14/the-trees-that-owns-itself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a happy time of lunch, Julie drive us to see a tree that owns itself. It took us only several minutes to get there from the Grit.</p>

<p>Here is the picture of the tree.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-owns-itself.png" alt="Tree owns itself" /></p>

<p>The owner of the nearby house loved this tree too much, he wanted to protect the tree as long as possible. So he claimed that he conveyed the right of this tree and nearby land to this tree itself.</p>

<p>The view of values of Americans are well presented in the story of this tree. They love and respect nature and the natural organism. They also respect and trust laws. There are more willing to share and respect other peoples&#8217; love and willings.</p>

<p>This cultural values may answer at least partly the questions: why the sky is still blue and the water is still clean; why birds sing in the morning and squallers run around; why people like to go nature for holiday and spend more money to buy green electricity.</p>

<p>This may be the big thing that China lacks and we want to rebuild, in both Chinese culture and education system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教育科研基金]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/grants-for-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T19:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/grants-for-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/keti-shenqing.png" alt="Grants for education" /></p>

<p>7-8月（截止8月15号） NARST年会 或者 AERA年会</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CSSCI收录的教育期刊]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/cssci-journals-of-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T18:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/cssci-journals-of-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>
教育学学科拟收录来源期刊名单（36种）

远成职继类（4种）
期刊名称    主办（管）单位   CN号
开放教育研究  上海远程教育集团、上海电视大学   CN31-1724/G4
远程教育杂志  浙江广播电视大学    CN33-1304/G4
现代远程教育研究    四川广播电视大学    CN51-1580/G4
现代远距离教育   黑龙江广播电视大学等  CN23-1066/G4

高等教育类（9种）
期刊名称    主办（管）单位   CN号
高等教育研究  华中科技大学等   CN42-1024/G4
高等工程教育研究    华中科技大学等   CN42-1026/G4
中国高教研究  中国高等教育学会    CN11-2962/G4
中国高等教育  中国教育报刊社   CN11-1200/G4
学位与研究生教育    国务院学位委员会    CN11-1736/G4
大学教育科学  湖南大学等 CN43-1398/G4
现代大学教育  湖南省高等教育学会等  CN43-1358/G4
高教探索    广东省高等教育学会 CN44-1109/G4
江苏高教    江苏教育报刊总社    CN32-1048/G4

教育技术类（3种）
期刊名称    主办（管）单位   CN号
电化教育研究  西北师范大学等   CN62-1022/G4
中国电化教育  中央电化教育馆   CN11-3792/G4
现代教育技术  清华大学    CN11-4525/N

教育综合类（16种）
期刊名称    主办（管）单位   CN号
教育研究    中央教育科学研究所 CN11-1281/G4
北京大学教育评论    北京大学    CN11-4848/G4
清华大学教育研究    清华大学    CN11-1610/G4
华东师范大学学报(教育科学版)   华东师范大学  CN31-1007/G4
教育发展研究  上海市教育科学研究院等   CN31-1772/G4
教师教育研究  教育部高校师资培训交流北京中心等    CN11-5147/G4
比较教育研究  北京师范大学  CN11-2878/G4
复旦教育论坛  复旦大学    CN31-1891/G4
教育与经济 华中师范大学、中国教育经济学研究会 CN42-1268/G4
教育学报    北京师范大学  CN11-5306/G4
教育研究与实验   华中师范大学  CN42-1041/G4
全球教育展望  华东师范大学  CN31-1842/G4
教育科学    辽宁师范大学  CN21-1066/G4
国家教育行政学院学报  国家教育行政学院    CN11-5047/D
湖南师范大学教育科学学报    湖南师范大学  CN43-1381/G4
外国教育研究  东北师范大学  CN22-1022/G4

基础教育类（4种）
期刊名称    主办（管）单位   CN号
课程.教材.教法    人民教育出版社课程教材研究所  CN11-1278/G4
中国特殊教育  中央教育科学研究所 CN11-3826/G4
中国教育学刊  中国教育学会  CN11-2606/G4
学前教育研究  中国学前教育研究会、长沙师范学校    CN43-1038/G4
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[师范生课程如何设置]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/curriculum-for-preservice-teachers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T14:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/curriculum-for-preservice-teachers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>怎样的课程设置对未来教师的专业成长更有利？<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/curriculum-preservice-teacher.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why it is so hard to bridge the theory-practice gap]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/why-it-is-so-hard-to-bridge-the-theory-practice-gap/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T10:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/why-it-is-so-hard-to-bridge-the-theory-practice-gap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Oliver let us read this following paper and write one or two paragraph of summary.<br/>
Nuthall, G. (2004). Relating Classroom Teaching to Student Learning: A Critical Analysis of Why Research Has Failed to Bridge the Theory-Practice Gap. Harvard Educational Review, 74(3), 273–307.</p>

<p>It is good paper to read, although it is a little long for non-native English speaker.</p>

<p>Here is what I got:</p>

<p>It matters how teacher look at and use educational research.<br/>
Is this why western culture emphase qualitative studies than quantitative studies?<br/>
The precondition of this approach is that teacher education help teachers do so. So it should be one topic in teacher education program.<br/>
why research necessary for teacher development<br/>
what research questions are more hard to know by only practicing<br/>
What relationship existes between teaching and learning</p>

<p>Why educational research is necessary:<br/>
1 teacher hard to see learning evidence (only some students)<br/>
2 reseach can help identify teachers&#8217; tacit beliefs and limitations<br/>
3 learning in students&#8217; mind are not easy to see by teachers where research should help.</p>

<p>learning is an inner process that can not easily seen<br/>
Research should help teacher see this process</p>

<p>Teachers need an explanatory theory of the teaching-learning relationship that meets these
requirements in order to plan, carry out, and evaluate their daily activi- ties effectively and efficiently(Floden, 2001; Levin &amp; ODonnell, 1999).</p>

<p>Teachers usually take teaching-learning consequence for granted and when it don&#8217;t it is student to blame.</p>

<p>Classroom 3 layers:<br/>
visible activities and behaviors<br/>
semi-visible stu-stu<br/>
semivisible individual stu</p>

<p>what role student-private-talk play in student learning(online learning sometimes is the case when learners do not interact with peers.)</p>

<p>understanding how teaching is related to learning requires an understanding of:<br/>
1. teacher influence<br/>
2. sociocultural influence<br/>
3. student make sense of their classroom experience</p>

<p>a theory of effective teaching is still needed in order to know when to look and what to look for when you observe the teachers classroom activities.</p>

<p>Best of these studies had two enormous advantages over previous research:<br/>
First, they were based on systematic observation or audio- and video-recording of teacher and student behavior. Second, independent measures of student learning that were directly related to the student experi- ences being observed were used in almost all of the best studies.</p>

<p>Teachers themselves are not always good at rating student achievement, as their ratings tend to be strongly affected by student behavior and motivation, crediting the most attentive and interested with higher achievement (Gold- enberg, Gallimore, Reese, &amp; Garnier, 2001)</p>

<p>The problem of process-product studies or careless quantitative studies is neglecting the context and other students out of</p>

<p>The study, however, is of little use in advancing our knowledge about the teaching-learning relationship</p>

<p>I have already made the point that teachers cannot be aware of critical elements in the
teaching-learning process in their own classrooms unless they already have a clear understanding of what to look for and have additional ways of observing or recording the experiences of individual students.</p>

<p>If you simply looked at the post-test totals, you would incorrectly assume that the more able learned more than the less able.</p>

<p>But it cannot produce generalizable knowledge (or an evi- dence based explanatory theory) of the relationships between the alternative versions of the visible structure and the basis model (to use Oser and Baeriswyls model) that can be transferred from classroom to classroom.</p>

<p>It has been claimed that how students learn and how their learning is shaped by the actions of the teacher is always unique and context dependent (Barab &amp; Kirschner, 2001; Bolster, 1983). This claim is both true and not true.</p>

<p>Part of the professional knowledge of teachers must be the distinction between what is unique to a specific context and what is generalizable across all students and/or contexts. While the latter is the proper focus of research on the teaching-learning relationship, an adequate explanatory theory should help us to distinguish between the two.</p>

<p>individual case studies of teaching, provided they include data about student experience and learning that can be directly connected to observations of specific classroom activities, can provide invaluable insights into the processes that lie behind the teaching-learning relationship.(baby project)</p>

<p>I believe that the professional knowledge base that is most needed to improve the quality of teaching and teacher education is knowledge about the ways in which classroom activities, including teaching, affect the changes taking place in the minds of students: what students know and believe and what they can do with their knowledge (what I have called above practical explanatory theory). At the heart of the problem that teachers face in the classroom is knowing what is going on in the minds of the students (Steffe, Thompson, &amp; von Glasersfeld, 2000).</p>

<p>Suggestions for future studies:<br/>
1. Independent in-depth assessment of what students learn.<br/>
2. Complete, continuous data on individual student experience.<br/>
3. Complete, continuous data on classroom activities.<br/>
4. Analysis based on the continuous connections among classroom activities, student experiences, and learning processes.<br/>
5. Avoid the aggregation of data.<br/>
6. Explanatory theory must be directly and transparently connected to relevant evidence.</p>

<p>Reference:<br/>
Nuthall, G. (2004). Relating Classroom Teaching to Student Learning: A Critical Analysis of Why Research Has Failed to Bridge the Theory-Practice Gap. Harvard Educational Review, 74(3), 273–307.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教育改革论辩]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/07/discuss-education-reform/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T16:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/07/discuss-education-reform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>教育改革是关系到千家万户的事，不仅仅涉及到教育官员、政策制定者、专家学者，还涉及到普通的教师、家长、学生和教育研究工作者，什么人都可以对教育说上一两句的。我也打算说上一两句。</p>

<p>关于素质教育和应试教育的争论由来已久，最近又有一场争论。列文如下：<br/>
正方：<a href="http://blog.sina.com.cn/s/blog_538c514e0101f3bm.html">王策三：应该尽力尽责总结经验教训——评“十年课改：超越成败与否的简单评价”</a><br/>
反方：<a href="http://blog.sina.com.cn/s/blog_492471c80102e77a.html">杨东平：新课程改革的得失和深化——兼与王策三教授交流</a></p>

<p>争论的导火索是一篇报道：<a href="http://edu.people.com.cn/GB/15911286.html">十年课改：超越成败与否的简单评价&#8211;人民网</a></p>

<p>报道的内容是“教师对新课改的评价”的网络调查结果，该调查由21世纪教育研究院等机构组织实施，近4000名中小学教师接受了抽样问卷调查。受调查教师覆盖了全国29个省、自治区、直辖市的城乡各级教师。（见正方文章）</p>

<p>强烈建议读者先把两篇文章比较着来读，可以兼顾和权衡，对于正确对待课程改革会很有帮助。</p>

<p>因为调查结果明确显示了教师对课程改革不满（表现在总体评价75%不满意；73%认为知识体系不系统；47%认为学生课业负担反而加重了），所以争论的关键并不是课程改革的成败。而是如何解释这个调查结果以及如何面对的课改问题。</p>

<p>正方的观点是：这个调查明确显示了课改的失败，而“超越成败”有逃避责任之嫌，当务之急是要总结经验教训，避免对立素质教育和应试教育，停止“覆灭”“应试教育”这个口号和目标，回到“学科课程”为主“经验课程”为辅的正常轨道上来，依照科学的工作方法逐步改善片面应试的弊端，而不是另起炉灶。</p>

<p>反方的观点是：观念的胜利本身就是一个巨大的成就，它是教育范式转变的前提。以杜郎口中学为代表的农村学校“学生主体课堂”是改革的一朵奇葩。今后，一是在打破“教师中心”之后，继续打破“教材中心”、“课堂中心”，走向以儿童为中心的生活教育。二是简政放权、改革中小学办学体制，促进教育家办学，使自下而上的“星星之火”得以燎原。</p>

<p>两方提出的措施都有可取的地方自然不必细说。但是对于课程改革的成败与否和未来走向，他们的观点是完全不同的。正方在说你看，教师最有发言权，这十年的课改是不成功的，不承认也得承认，考试和学科课程本身并没有错，是我们需要理性回归的正路，只是我们需要想办法改善其某些弊端罢了，决不能完全抛弃它们。</p>

<p>反方则认为，改革也不是一点都不成功，教学观念的转变不就成绩吗？另外杜郎口模式也很有潜力，只要有更好的政策，其“星星之后”可以燎原的。改革的根本方向并没错，当然还是要坚持走下去。</p>

<p>这里面，有几个问题值得讨论和思考：<br/>
关于观念的胜利<br/>
1. 教学观念的转变到底算不算课程改革的成绩呢？教师的教学观念真的转变了吗？<br/>
2. 改革进程中，教学观念的转变是怎样发生的？是自发的？还是被挟持的？稳定与否？<br/>
关于调查结果的解释<br/>
3. 这个调查结果究竟应该如何解释？做出怎样的结论才是恰当的？（不大不小）<br/>
4. 如果想全面评估课程改革取得的实质性进展，那么应该做这个评估？应该收集哪些数据？<br/>
关于今后的路该如何走<br/>
5. 未来的教育改革走向究竟应该如何走？这样大的决策应该依据什么做出？<br/>
6. 究竟是专家引领的自上而下的改革适合中国，还是在大的政策框架下自下而上星火燎原适合中国？各有哪些利弊？</p>

<p>课程改革反思应该遵循的原则：<br/>
1. 不要只看结果，要分析产生结果的原因。<br/>
2. 不要推卸责任，要认真负责、实事求是、认清问题。<br/>
3. 不要太主观化、运动化、意愿化、敌对化，要基于实证研究结果和国情做出决策，求准不求快。</p>

<p>其实这场论战早就开始了，细看其中的参考文献就知道了。能听的进去别人不同的意见，才了不起。毕竟是为公不为私。其实课程改革的团队恰恰需要不同的声音，决策者应该将不同声音都纳入到重大决策的制定和执行团队中，不辨不明。协商下的妥协要胜过一边倒的绝对胜利式的决策。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[柔柔的光]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/05/ai-de-rou-guang/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T10:12:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/05/ai-de-rou-guang</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>明明想让你快乐<br/>
却只留下悲伤<br/>
不知道爱情模样<br/>
还痴心一场</p>

<p>人海茫茫<br/>
不如一个人流浪<br/>
在一个陌生的城市<br/>
向着一个陌生的方向</p>

<p>每当夜幕降临的时候<br/>
你总是出现在我面前<br/>
命运扼住了喉咙<br/>
泪水已打湿了双眼</p>

<p>不知何时丢失了双桨<br/>
只剩下孤独的帆<br/>
不知多少岁月又或是多少年<br/>
你可曾记得我们初相见</p>

<p>风雨后<br/>
一个寂寞的小荷塘<br/>
微风轻抚<br/>
阵阵送清凉<br/>
水面上<br/>
荡起你柔柔的光</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Play with kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/03/play-with-kids/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-03T17:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/03/play-with-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to design and collect some good learning activities for my son. These activities only needs your time and some everyday stuff.</p>

<h3>Why should we play with our kids?</h3>

<h3>How to play with kids?</h3>

<h3>Early Learning Activities:</h3>

<p>Safty</p>

<p>Play with your hands</p>

<p>Clapping and Speaking</p>

<p>Gussing which hand</p>

<p>Play with your legs</p>

<p>Dance a little</p>

<p>Drawing &amp; Painting</p>

<p>Play with objects</p>

<p>Play with water</p>

<p>Play with air</p>

<p>Role play</p>

<p>Play with memory</p>

<p>Sing a song</p>

<p>Running</p>

<p>Writing</p>

<p>What have you done today?</p>

<p>Collecting bottles</p>

<p>Who is wrong?</p>

<p>Play with ball</p>

<p>Play on the grassland</p>

<p>Kite</p>

<p>Birds</p>

<p>Invitation</p>

<p>Share with friends</p>

<p>Honest</p>

<p>My family</p>

<p>Play Chess</p>

<p>Write a story</p>

<p>Snake Puzzle</p>

<p>Let&#8217;s play some Magics</p>

<p>Read a book</p>

<p>Save money for a project</p>

<p>Play with friends</p>

<p>Blinded Walk for Trust</p>

<p>Build the layers of the earth</p>

<p>Sensory Exchange</p>

<p>What happens if &#8230;</p>

<p>One of these things is not like the others</p>

<p>What is in the bag</p>

<p>Grow a plant</p>

<p>Bird food feeders</p>

<p>Water study</p>

<h3>What I learned and got</h3>

<p>References:<br/>
Brain-based Early Learning Activites</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yellow dragon]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/01/yellow-dragon/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T11:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/01/yellow-dragon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yellow dragon<br/>
Yellow zoo<br/>
Happy dancing<br/>
Happy pool</p>

<p>Jingle for my son<br/>
At Athens<br/>
June 1st 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pick the right test]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/30/pick-the-right-test/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-30T14:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/30/pick-the-right-test</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You have to pick a test to analysis your data. The question is which test is the right one. Well, it depends on your data and your hypothesis. Usually there are lot of choices, but only one solves your problem best.</p>

<p>Here are some suggestions for selecting test by the types of your variables.<br/>
Dependent and Independent Variables<br/>
Dependent Variable(DV) is what you are care of. Independent Variable(IV) is what you think may affect your dependent variable. Usually you can control your independent variable, but not depedent variable.</p>

<p>There are two basic types of variables:<br/>
Continuous Variables(e.g. height,temprature)<br/>
Discrete Variables(e.g. age, size, preferences)</p>

<p>if IV=[0,1],DV=[~] then T test<br/>
if IV=[0,1,2,],DV=[~] then one-way Anova or ANOCVA<br/>
if IV1=[0,1,2,], IV2=[0,1,2,], DV=[~] then General linear model<br/>
if IV1=[~], IV2[~],&#8230;, DV=[~], then Linear Regression &amp; Pearson<br/>
if IV=[0,1,&#8230;], DV=[0,1,&#8230;] then χ2<br/>
if IV=[~], DV=[0,1,&#8230;] then Logistic regression</p>

<p>For more details look at the following pictures:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/choiceoftest.png" alt="Choices of Test" /><br/>
This picture comes from : <a href="http://www.socr.ucla.edu/Applets.dir/ChoiceOfTest.html">SOCR: Statistics Online Computational Resource</a></p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a href="http://www.unesco.org/webworld/idams/advguide/Chapt1_3.htm">Types of Variables</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.socr.ucla.edu/Applets.dir/ChoiceOfTest.html">SOCR: Choice of Test</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multidimensional Scaling in R]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/29/mds-in-r/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T22:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/29/mds-in-r</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I met this problem when I was analysing teachers&#8217; PCK concept maps. I wanted to divide them into several clusters that shared the similar structures(nodes and links).</p>

<p>One approch is plotting them in a 2d picture to see if there is any patterns. But before that, you have to do the Muultidimensional Scaling to get your (x,y) from your Distance Matrix.</p>

<p>Distance Matrix<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/distance-matrix.png" alt="Distance Matrix" /><br/>
How I got this matrix. Well, I just count them using my data. Of course, if can deside how you count them, which counts how much score, or you simply give them a number.</p>

<pre><code>
# 1) MDS 'cmdscale'
dm <- read.table("distance-matrix.txt")
mds1 = cmdscale(dm, k = 2)

# plot
plot(mds1[,1], mds1[,2], type = "n", xlab = "", ylab = "", axes = FALSE, main = "cmdscale (stats)")
text(mds1[,1], mds1[,2], labels(x)[[1]], cex = 0.9, xpd = TRUE)
</code></pre>


<p>This the x y data I got:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/xy-data-mds.png" alt="Distance Matrix" /></p>

<p>I got this picture after plotting it out.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/plot-mds.png" alt="Distance Matrix" /></p>

<p>Reference:<br/>
<a href="http://gastonsanchez.com/blog/how-to/2013/01/23/MDS-in-R.html">7 Functions to do Metric Multidimensional Scaling in R | Gaston Sanchez</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Questions need to address in a research paper]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/28/questions-need-to-address-in-a-research-paper/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-28T18:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/28/questions-need-to-address-in-a-research-paper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A sample division for 40 pages paper.<br/>
2 Introduction<br/>
5-6 Literature<br/>
2 Theory/conceptual frameworks<br/>
6-10 Methods<br/>
4-12 Findings<br/>
10 Discussion conclusion Implication</p>

<p>(1)Introduction</p>

<pre><code>* what is known  
* what is unknown  
* Your burning Hypothesis, question, aim(Approach, plan of attack, proposed solution(a little bit),your experimental approach,why your study fills the gap  
</code></pre>

<p>tips for introduction</p>

<pre><code>* Keep short  
* for general audience: clear, concise, non-technical  
* take the reader step by step form what is know to what is unknown. end with your specific question  
* Emphasize how your study fills in the gaps(the unknown)  
* Summarize at a high level! Leave detailed descriptions, speculations, and criticism of studies in discussion  
</code></pre>

<p>Keep in minds:</p>

<pre><code>* it is not a literature review  
* catch attention  
* making the case  
</code></pre>

<p>(2)Literature review</p>

<pre><code>* comprehension  
* synthesis  
* critical  
* write the most important citations that stand your study out  
* anything in discussion should be here, no new paper add in discussion  
* one paragraph summary your review  
</code></pre>

<p>notes: if there is no directly related literature, you can close area to draw on, or standards, government policy</p>

<p>(3)Theoretical/ Conceptual Frameworks</p>

<pre><code>* help to analysis the data and approach the questions  
* theory -position/approach  
* conceptual model  
* theory drawing the studies
</code></pre>

<p>(4)Methods</p>

<pre><code>* Participants  
* Context  
* Data collections  
* Data analysis  
* Methodological theory  
* Reliability and validity  
* enough information for other people to repeat  
</code></pre>

<p>(5)Results<br/>
Tables and figures<br/>
Summarize not read table for reader<br/>
Highlight the result, Not only positive results but also negative<br/>
complement the information that is already in tables and figures<br/>
give precise values in the figure or the percentage change<br/>
don&#8217;t forget to talk about the negative and control results<br/>
Reserve the term &#8220;significant&#8221; for statistically significant<br/>
reserve information about what you did for the methods section<br/>
do not discuss the rationale for statistical analyses within the results section<br/>
Reserve comments on the meaning of your results for the discussion section<br/>
Just tell what the data show not what your data mean</p>

<p>Use the past tense for completed actions: we found , women were, men smoked ,was<br/>
Use the present tense for assertions that continue to be true<br/>
figure 1 show ,  finds confirm the data suggests</p>

<pre><code>* Synthesis the important not all  
* Show the results to match the questions  
* select the most powerful and significant  
* do not repeat the tables and figures  
</code></pre>

<p>(6)Discussion<br/>
Answer the question you asked<br/>
Support your conclusion(your data, others&#8217; data)<br/>
Defend your conclusion(anticipate criticisms)<br/>
Give the &#8220;big-picture&#8221; take-home message<br/>
Connect your theory framework and review<br/>
how your work add on</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[不要才能要]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/24/what-to-do/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T10:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/24/what-to-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>不要封闭要开放，不要暴力要协商；<br/>
不要愤世要救世，不要人治要法治。</p>

<p>不要封锁要透明，不要口号要践行；<br/>
不要污染要发展，不要禁言要多元。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
