<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-24T12:30:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interactive simulation based inquiry activities]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T12:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><video width='720' height='480' preload='none' controls poster=' http://s3.imathis.com/video/zero-to-fancy-buttons.png'><source src='https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/gmodel3.swf' type='video/mp4; codecs="avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2"'/></video></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/gmodel3.swf" alt="Plant grow to sunlight" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modeling activities and reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T23:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I attended Dr Luft&#8217;s class Methods of Science Teaching. I am becoming more and more interested in Modeling activities and I want to make a collection of these activities.</p>

<p>This is the list:<br/>
-   Candle in the water tube make it go out(Dr Luft&#8217;s class)<br/>
-   Black box(<a href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=11102">How students learn: science in classroom</a> see Chp 12)<br/>
-   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
-   Secret Tube (Dr C&#8217;s class)<br/>
-   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
If you have more good modeling activities, welcome recommandations.</p>

<p>These activities provide lots of practice options for science teachers. We usually only provide standards of what students should master but little practice activites for teachers. Well, the <a href="http://www.nextgenscience.org/next-generation-science-standards">Next Generation Standard</a> is going to change this.</p>

<p>Reflections on Modeling in science teaching<br/>
The charm of modeling:<br/>
-   Naturally need students to make careful observation,recording data,drawing conclusions<br/>
-   Naturally engage students&#8217; prior ideas for explaination or application<br/>
-   Naturally put students into the test, debate and revisement of their models or prior ideas<br/>
-   Naturally let students experience the full process of science inquiry and nature of science</p>

<p>What to focus in the modeling activites as a science teacher?</p>

<p>How to keep the balance between knowledge-centered and student-centered? Individual and Community? Cognition and metacognition?</p>

<p>Welcome to join the discussion of these open questions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors of good teacher and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T22:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A good teacher just like a good cook. Of course, you can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes. So students&#8217; perfect performance is a good predictor of competent teacher. But it takes a lot effort to make the dishes OR evaluate the students. In fact, we can also tell a good cook by his preparation and operation of his cooking.  Good cook can aways make many dishes in a limited time. Because he don&#8217;t stop, when heating the water, he is washing the vegatables or cutting the meat. When the water is ready he is also ready to fry them together. The teacher do the same thing in class expecially in a short class. I found this metaphor visiting Dr C&#8217;s class, she give instructions as well as preparing the tools for modeling, at the same time she was also doing demonstration of what the secret tube behaviors.</p>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers&#8217; beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The science teacher is like a swimming player in a swimming poor. The science teacher educator stand beside and tell the player how to swim, which style is good which is bad. But the most important thing for a person in the swimming poor is to keep safty and the most reliable style is his primary style. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not stand by but jump into the swimming poor and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Timms video and reflection of teaching science with modeling]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/timms-video-and-reflection-of-teaching-science-with-modeling/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/timms-video-and-reflection-of-teaching-science-with-modeling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is my first time to view a science classroom teaching in Japan. In fact, it supprise me a little. I know the science education in Japan is of high quality. They get much better score than the other counties and teacher are respectable profession. But I never thought the classroom are so interactive and effective. You can click <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">here</a> to view the video.</p>

<blockquote><p>This eighth-grade science lesson is about the formation of clouds. It is the third lesson in a sequence of 19 lessons on weather. The lesson is 53 minutes in duration. There are 25 students in the class.</p></blockquote>

<p>Here is my record of the time usage of the class:</p>

<blockquote><p>00-03 review what learnt<br/>
03-07 demistration<br/>
07-17 demistration of key skills for today&#8217;s experiment<br/>
18-36 Student activites(4 experiments and group take turn)<br/>
36-50 sumary of experiment result and draw conclusion<br/>
50-52 self-evalation</p></blockquote>

<p>I watched the video twice, first I just got a glance of it very quickly. The second time, I watch it very carefully and make notes of what teacher and students were doing.</p>

<p>First, I found a very interesting thing that the Japenese teacher used about 17 minutes to engage students and make demonstration at the begining. He also used about 17 minutes to sumary the results and conclusions at the end of the class. Acording to psychology studies, people are most likely to remember what happened at begining and at the end. People usually can only concentrate for 15 minutes. So most TED videos will not last more than 17 minutes. I don&#8217;t know if the teacher did it popurely. But he did it really well.</p>

<p>Second, the class is very interesting and vigorous. Students really had fun with the activities and record and try to explain.</p>

<p>Third, it keep a good balance of knowledge-centered and student-centered. The most important ideas and inquiry skills were embodied in student activities.</p>

<p>At last, I want to say although the teacher said nothing about modeling. But he raised a question for students to study.  Students want to explain but had little idea and experieces. So they did the activities that teacher prepared for them. Before experiments, they make their explannation and predictions, they recorded the result on the handouts, they have to revise their explanation and building a more powerful causal model to explain all the phenomenons. So we do can found the shape of modeling in this class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for convinence for people]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/16/design-for-convinence-for-people/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-16T13:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/16/design-for-convinence-for-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most deep impressions I got of US is the pursuing of simple and comfortable life.</p>

<p>First is the bus design.<br/>
There is a button out side of the bus that customers can push to kneel the bus. Another design is that there is a string along the windows. You can pull the string to let bus stop. You don&#8217;t even need to stand up.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing I discovered the yellow alert along the road. First I though it is to let people wark accross the street. But when I look into it carefully, It said &#8220;State law: stop when human on the line&#8221;, it is for the car. No wonder evertime when I was on the line, the drive will stop let me pass first. What a nice law!  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/statelaw.jpg" alt="Statelaw" /><br/>
One day, when I was on my way home from supermarket, I found there is an American Bank ATM special for car drivers near the shops. I have never saw such ATM before in China. You don&#8217;t have to get out of your car when you using the ATM In China, when you go to banks, usually you have wait for half an hour to get your turns in Shanghai. Why it is so different! This is a really good question to think about.</p>

<p>The last discovery is kitchen. They have kitchen not only in the apartment where I live but also in the office. There is a special kitchen room for professors and students to heat their lunch or make coffee. So nice!<br/>
Oh, I nearly forget. The water ﻿purifier﻿. It is so cool and useful, I love it too much.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/water.jpg" alt="water purifier" /></p>

<p>It is evident that the goal of American people is to pursue a simple and comfortable life. Maybe not very luxurious but comfortable.</p>

<p>How did they achieve that, market and competition may be the driving power. What it doesn&#8217;t happen in China? Big question!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fighting with the imaginary enemy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/10/fighting-with-the-imaginary-enemy/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-10T11:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/10/fighting-with-the-imaginary-enemy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you want to run away confronting a challenge. Usually, you have your own reasons. It is too hard. It is too boring. I am not good at this. It is so painful. You want to advoid to meet it although it is important and urgent. We all know it but feel so hard to control yourself.</p>

<p>So what to do?</p>

<p>YOU have an imaginary enemy to fight. Game start! Sometimes your enemy is strong and sometimes he is endurable. Mostly, you have exaggerated your enemy and belittled yourself. Imagine you are fighting against an enemy who also have his own weakness. The wise move would be found his weakness and take all the advantage you have to beat him. If you don&#8217;t fight, you are doomed to failure. If you fight, there still a hope to win.</p>

<p>In fact, you have no opotions but to fight. Your imaginary enemy would alert you and help you to beat the fearness and win the game!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computer tips recently discovered]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/07/computer-tips-recently-discovered/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T17:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/07/computer-tips-recently-discovered</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I found some useful tips to get things done more effectively.</p>

<p>How do you capture your screen when you are watching a vedio without stop it.<br/>
-   The answer is that you can setup some softwares to do this. One of them is <a href="http://www.aplusfreeware.com/categories/mmedia/FastStoneCapture.html">FastStone Caputure</a>. You just set the auto save folder and the hot key in the settings. Then, things get much easier, everytime you want capture your screen, just press the hot key. The picture can be saved in the folder with disturbing your watching. It is so useful.</p>

<p>After type your keyword in the address bar, how do you google it in a new tab with Chorme browser?<br/>
-   The answer is: press Alt &amp; Enter, then it will show your search results in a new tab.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observation of daily life of Americans]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/02/observation-of-daily-life-of-americans/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/02/observation-of-daily-life-of-americans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These days while I live in my apartment, I pay close attention to the daily life of people here. I have drawed a conclusion: Americans are lazy.</p>

<p>In fact, Lazy here is not used in a derogatory sense. You know, only the lazy people can invent and design a comfortable life. Americans are such kind of designers who are persueing simple but comfortable life. Let me give you some examples.</p>

<p>I live in a house department. In China, the parking area is often underground or a little far from the appartment. But in USA, the parking lot is jut in front of the hourse near the door. You can imagine when you get back from work, get out of your car, and then enter your door, it is so convinent.</p>

<p>After you get in, you can find a kitchen, a sitting room, a laundry room and a bath room. If you take a look at the kitchen, you will find a dish washer there and microwave oven. In China, most people just wash by hands, you can hardly found a dish washer, expecially in a student&#8217;s department.</p>

<p>As to food, most food can be cooked just by heatting, like milk and bread. If sauces are needed, they are already mixed up and ready for use. You can find all this kind of mixed up sauces or semi-manufactured food everywhere in a food supermaket. Cooking become easy here, athough the taste may becoming a little dull. Most Chinese will not buy the mixed sauces, they may want to make their own although they will spent a lot of time on cooking.</p>

<p>One day, a ceaseless noise of machinery wake me up. I look out through the window, I found a man is using a grass cutter in front of the door. In China, people also use this kind of grass cutter, which is belted to the waist. But lawn mower like a car is hardly found in China. I often saw an american sitting on it and drive it on the lawn, it is fun. I also found people here clean the street in a differnt way, they use a air blower to blow the leaves away and make the road clean. If you walk on street in the early morning in Beijing, you will see a cleaner clean street with broom. You will never found a man with a blowing machine walk here and there.</p>

<p>And almost everyone have a car here. Once I ask a black man for directions, after telling my the way, he said don&#8217;t you have a car, I sait not yet. He then added while it will be 20 to 30 minutes&#8217; walk. I follow his directions, after 10 minutes I got there. It is not that far, I said in my mind. May be they drive too much, and then have no idea how long it will take by walking.</p>

<p>So there are so many differences between the two countries. It also stand for different culture. The Americans are taking every advantage of modern science and technology to make their lives simple and comfortable. Labor is much more expensive in USA than in China. The Chinese culture advocate deligent, hard-working and Obedience.  The American culture advocate Science &amp; Technolgy, comfortable life and freedom. You can not say which one is better, but they can learn from each other.  Athough the American life is easy and comfortable, but it exhausted much more energy. Athough, Chinese food is delicious, but it is time cousuming, I think Chinese really should spend more time on inovation in S&amp;T and social system.</p>

<p>by chunlei 08/02/13 07:30AM</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dream back to Home]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/02/dream-back-to-home/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T05:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/02/dream-back-to-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a dream today. I took a flight back to home just in order to make sure everthing at home is Ok. I don&#8217;t konw why. There is an old saying what you dream at night is what you think at day. Maybe I am a little homesick now. When I am awake, I am laying on a big white bed still in USA. I thought I will not easily be homesick, but I am wrong. Well my advisor is right, I will confront some hard time and even shed tears. If it was the Cost, what I can do is only maximize the benifit.</p>

<p>I have learnt how to cook rice in microwave oven. I also learn how to cook dishes in a pan which the bottom is flat.  I have been accustomed to the food here, milk and egg for breakfast, noodles or rice for lunch and supper. I improve my spoken and writing English through participting some online courses. It does work.</p>

<p>I will also record what I have done, observed and thought by bloging. It will cover all the stories that I experienced during my study in USA.</p>

<p>by chunlei 08/02/13 05:41 AM</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[python brief]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/30/python-brief/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T14:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/30/python-brief</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Python重要用法示例</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>dir(list)
显示关键字相关的函数</p>

<p>help(list.reverse)
查询某个函数的功能</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>set 让一个list变成无重复元素的set
例如：</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>shapes = [&#8216;circle&#8217;,&#8217;square&#8217;,&#8217;triangle&#8217;,&#8217;circle&#8217;]
setOfShapes = set(shapes)
setOfShapes
set([&#8216;circle&#8217;,&#8217;square&#8217;,&#8217;triangle&#8217;])
setOfShapes.add(&#8216;polygon&#8217;)
&#8216;rhombus&#8217; in setOfShapes
False
setOfShapes - setOfFavoriteShapes
setOfShapes &amp; setOfFavoriteShapes
setOfShapes | setOfFavoriteShapes</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>map和lambda</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>map(lambda x: x * x, [1,2,3])
[1, 4, 9]
filter(lambda x: x > 3, [1,2,3,4,5,4,3,2,1])
[4, 5, 4]</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Object 先定义一个类，然后给类生成实例
定义如：
class FruitShop:</p>

<pre><code>def __init__(self, name, fruitPrices):
    """
        name: Name of the fruit shop

        fruitPrices: Dictionary with keys as fruit 
        strings and prices for values e.g. 
        {'apples':2.00, 'oranges': 1.50, 'pears': 1.75} 
    """
    self.fruitPrices = fruitPrices
    self.name = name
    print 'Welcome to the %s fruit shop' % (name)

def getCostPerPound(self, fruit):
    """
        fruit: Fruit string
    Returns cost of 'fruit', assuming 'fruit'
    is in our inventory or None otherwise
    """
    if fruit not in self.fruitPrices:
        print "Sorry we don't have %s" % (fruit)
        return None
    return self.fruitPrices[fruit]

def getPriceOfOrder(self, orderList):
    """
        orderList: List of (fruit, numPounds) tuples

    Returns cost of orderList. If any of the fruit are  
    """ 
    totalCost = 0.0             
    for fruit, numPounds in orderList:
        costPerPound = self.getCostPerPound(fruit)
        if costPerPound != None:
            totalCost += numPounds * costPerPound
    return totalCost

def getName(self):
    return self.name
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 rules to follow when studying at UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/30/3-rules-when-studying-at-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T14:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/30/3-rules-when-studying-at-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Durying my study in UGA, I will obey 3 rules:<br/>
*   能在中国做的不在美国做 Things that can be done in China will not be put at the frist place.<br/>
*   能自己做的不让别人做   Things that I can do myself will not be done by others.<br/>
*   能一天做的不用两天做   If it only need one day, I will not spend two days.</p>

<p>The aim of these rules is to let me to take every advantage of my study here. They will help me to save time and focus on the important work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[fighting with display problem in my coumputer]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/30/fighting-with-display-problem-with-my-computer/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T07:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/30/fighting-with-display-problem-with-my-computer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These days I am fighting with the Display Card Problem of my computer. Befor coming to Georgia, My coumputer can not start normaly, the screen is black, athough you can hear the sound of login. I try to ingnore this problem by using another OS Ubuntu in my comuputer.  BUT, unfortianaly, I can&#8217;t use the PAWS wireless network of UGA in Ubuntu. So I have to solve the Display problem in WIN7 or the wireless connection problem in Ubuntu. Guess what, neither of the problem is easy to trackle.</p>

<p>Finally, I solved the Display Problem using following steps:<br/>
+   setup the two display driver software in my drivers folder in C disk.<br/>
+   setup the downloaded display controler, uncheck the quick stream function<br/>
+   everything comes to normal although I still can&#8217;t use swticheable display mode in BIOS</p>

<p>What I learn from this:<br/>
+   never buy a computer with two display card fire together<br/>
+   if you have important thing just leave these problems there, important thing come frist<br/>
+   reflect and record your problem solving process</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to write your lesson plan]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/29/how-to-write-your-lesson-plan/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-29T00:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/29/how-to-write-your-lesson-plan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>经常有学生或教师问我该如何说课或者写教案。我听到后，第一反应是“查”。为什么不自己主动查一查，如何说课这个问题呢。肯定有很多资源的。在我看来，说合写都是表达教学设计的方式而已，关键还是教学设计。说其实是口头表达，其实如果你能写好教案，设计好教学，那么我相信你也能表达好。所以最关键的是理清自己的教学思路。自己都不清晰，怎么能指望别人听懂呢，更别指望受到赞赏和认可了。</p>

<p>我觉得说课要做到以下几点：<br/>
一、说课的内容一定要包括：教学目标、前段分析、教学思路-问题线索-学习活动、最后是学习检测。第一部分相当你是你要告诉别人，你要去哪，第二部分是“路况”如何，第三部分是你要如何走，第四部分是你如何知道你离目的地还有多远。<br/>
二、说课形式可以是多样的，可以借助ppt，也可以借助概念图，我推荐使用概念图，因为它能让你兼顾部分和整体、学习目标与学习活动之间的联系以及学习活动的过度和衔接等。这些都是新手教师容易忽略的。</p>

<p>三、说课的境界<br/>
-   最基本的是让人听懂，知道你要如何上这门课，这是第一个层次，也是最基本的层次。<br/>
-   第二层是让人不仅知道你怎么上，还知道你为什么这么上，教学是教师有意识的行动。<br/>
-   第三个层次，是让人觉得你是在创造性的解决实际问题，并且认同你的做法的合理性和可行性，教学是基于研究和经验摸索的创新尝试。</p>

<p>四、说课好坏的评判标准，
-   第一是教学目标设计和表述是否合理。<br/>
-   第二前段分析是否扎实、全面，是否包括学情分析、教材内容分析以及学习需要分析，是否能依据分析确定合理的教学目标。<br/>
-   第三教学思路是否清晰，问题线索是否自然，学习活动是否能帮助学生达成教学目标。<br/>
-   第四是否设计了新问题情境检测学生的学习成果和教学目标达成情况。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Study life begin in UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/28/study-life-begin-in-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T23:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/28/study-life-begin-in-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>我将在佐治亚访学一年，这一年的时间里我想用日志记录。记录我的所看、所感。</p>

<p>7月25号上午9点从上海飞往东京，转机飞亚特兰大。在东京停留了2个小时左右，我趁机买了一些日本的特产，包括绿茶和点心，这些小礼物是给接我的博士生R买的。一路上都很顺利，去亚特兰大的飞机上，坐在我左边的是一个中国人，右边的似乎是一个墨西哥人，很胖很壮，不过也很友善。我填写的海关表时，还向他借了笔，此外也问了他一些关于I94 departure record的问题，他回答的很耐心。</p>

<p>一路上我要莫看录像，要莫睡觉，为倒时差做准备。当然聊的比较多的还是与左边的中国留学生，他在英国留学，这次去美国看妈妈，我问他Groome shutle怎么坐，他说他也要做shutle，后来我给他看手机上的信息，结果其实他也是要做这个shutle的但是不是同一个线路而已。 于是我们商量好一起走。</p>

<p>从飞机下来要走很远，才能到海关检查的地点。然后排队等候，一个旅客无意识掏出了手机，结果给工作人员看见了，要求他拿着手机给检查官看，检查官是个黑人，盘问的半天检查了手机才让他继续排队。原因是这个地方是禁止拍照的。</p>

<p>盘查我的也是那个黑人警官，他问了2个问题，你来美国看什么，你研究什么，还让我出示了邀请信，之后才改了章放我过去。过了海关就去认领行李，一开始我以为应该有工作人员扫描条形码然后给我们行李，结果到了哪啥都没有，就是一个电子牌指示哪个航班的行李在哪个转盘上，我们等了半天，最后我的行李先出来了，由于我的班车是5点多的，我看了时间只有20分钟左右，我就自己先走了。 机场的地图虽然下载过，但是没什么用，有用的还是问路，问了一个警官，他告诉我做3路机场公车就可以，我赶紧去坐车，还好顺利赶到了。</p>

<p>我赶到的时候，只有2位乘客没有上车了，司机是个白人，长头发，很帅气，我告诉他我定了位置，他帮我放好行李，然后查看了记录手册，并让我付钱，结果我拿出一百美元，他说没有零钱。我问是否可以用信用卡，他说可以打电话，于是他帮我打通了电话，我说明了情况，报告了信用卡信息，结果就成功支付了。下车的时候，我看到有乘客给小费，但是很不巧我只有一百美元的，所以我说了谢谢，并解释了一下，他说没关系的。下车有机会再给吧。</p>

<p>我下了shutle，但是发现根本没有人等我，不过刚刚过了3分钟R先生就开车到了。我请他吃了快餐，本来还要买sim卡的，但是兜了很久也没找到，于是他送我去HSC入住。在工作人员的提示下，我填写了几张表格，就拿到了钥匙入住了。悬着的心终于放下来了，美国我来了。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Practice Creativity in design Chindogu]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/05/15/Chindogu-designed-by-me/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T19:33:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/05/15/Chindogu-designed-by-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近参加了一门网络课程，是关于创造力的，课程活动要求参与者设计一些chindogu，这个词源于日本，是指一些没有实际用途但是有趣的设计产品。于是我设计了以下作品： <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/beauty-in-your-cup.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hourglass-bath.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/couple-zipper-umbrella.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/lovers-dancing-shoe.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hand-tap-1.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/music-tap-1.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[win7 tab close error]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/04/04/win7-tab-close-error/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T17:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/04/04/win7-tab-close-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>P：关闭ie9标签页显示错误。<br/>
T：升级为ie10问题仍然存在。<br/>
T：关闭程序兼容性助手服务，问题仍为解决。<br/>
S: 关闭ie所有加载项，问题消失，然后逐个打开加载项，选择性加载。问题解决。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[get down to work]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/04/04/get-down-to-work/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T17:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/04/04/get-down-to-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>静下心来做事情是很了不起的品质。<br/>
快速的静下心来做事情是不得了的品格。</p>

<p>回顾过去总结教训是了不起的品质。<br/>
周期行的回顾并找出未来行动的参考是不得了的品格。<br/>
-   资料文本的回顾<br/>
-   文章的回顾<br/>
-   时间和行为的回顾</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[电影《教会》观感]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/04/04/The-mission-film-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T17:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/04/04/The-mission-film-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>电影描述的是发生在葡萄牙与西班牙边境的一个土著印第安部落的故事。故事大约发生在17世纪。当地政府默许抓捕印第安人，并作为奴隶贩卖，进而从中谋利。但是一个传教士经过一番周折，先到达了部落并且被土著居民所接纳。但是奴隶抓捕运动并没有结束，一个抓捕印第安人的雇佣兵因为愤怒，在决斗中杀死了自己的亲弟弟。对于此事他始终不能释怀，于是他来到教会，并想绝食致死。在神父的激将下，他背着一个沉重的包袱，爬上非常陡峭的瀑布，逆流而上来到印第安土著的居住地。印第安人认出了他，但看到他被包袱拖累的悲惨样子，原本威胁他的匕首反而帮他可断捆绑包袱的绳索。印第安人原谅了他。他也加入了教会，成为一名传教士，并和神父一起建立一个教堂。政府想使得抓捕当地印第安人合法化，但是教会则要庇护它的信徒。于是红衣主教特地赶来仲裁。迫于政府压力，红衣主教选择了牺牲当地印第安人，并让所有传教士撤离。但是神父和佣兵都留了下来，他们用不同的方式进行抵抗，但仍然难逃厄运。</p>

<p>悲剧总是让人印象格外深刻。</p>

<p>佣兵本来最后是有机会拉响炸药的，但是他看到一个小男孩中枪，他的伙伴想救他，他选择了先去救这个小男孩。于是他错过了拉响炸药的机会，并中枪倒下。</p>

<p>这是一个悲剧，佣兵选择了用武力保卫印第安部落。神父选择了用仁慈和舍生取义的精神来保护。但是都没有成功。</p>

<p>从战争的角度讲，佣兵安排的战斗策略是失误的：<br/>
1   没有利用天险瀑布悬崖<br/>
2   没有利用土著人善于水中作战的特点
3   没有利用森林进行运动战和埋伏战
4   没有转移老幼妇孺，避免不必要的损失<br/>
5   没有利用火枪对敌人头目进行狙击</p>

<p>影片呈现的是壮烈的牺牲，一个佣兵在最后关头选择的是爱，而不是杀戮，就已经将教义深深的烙印在观众的心中。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[biology experimental teaching]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/03/11/biology-experimental-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-11T21:55:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/03/11/biology-experimental-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天，第一组完成了观察类实验，第一次进行实验往往是最具有挑战的。因为他们要现去摸索实验准备的过程，教学组织的过程，以及环境的布置和利用等。考虑到这些挑战的要素，对于新手教师来讲，应该说完成的还是很不错的。</p>

<p>第一小组的优点包括：<br/>
-   提前分工做了预实验和必要的准备工作，特别是实验材料的准备和探索工作。<br/>
-   认准准备了课件和学案。<br/>
-   从头到尾顺畅的进行衔接，一直到最后完成实验室的清理工作。</p>

<p>当然也存在一些可以提高的地方：<br/>
-   时间的把控和设计可以再紧凑一些，每个人讲解的时间，实验操作的时间，分析总结的时间，以及教学反馈的时间都要考虑在内。
-   预想实验教学可能出现的各种情况，在实验材料、活动组织、课件、语言等做好充分的准备。<br/>
-   可以预先布置学习任务、分发学案，并把实验设计、反思等及时更新到wikispaces上，督促大家做好实验预习。</p>

<p>在本次实验过程中，王星同学以及李娜、郑烨两位同学准备都较为充分，语言和教态也较为自然，值得表扬。其实为什么能脱稿，为什么能够应对各种突发状况，本质上离不开充分的准备。这种准备包括对内容的熟悉，对实验操作过程要点的熟悉，对学生特点和行为的预期等等。当然也离不开好的设计，好的设计一定是将内容、教法以及技术环境以较为合适的方式进行了融合的方案。因此大家也可以从这三个方面下下功夫。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[to be a daddy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/02/17/to-be-a-daddy/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T22:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/02/17/to-be-a-daddy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>时间过的真快，一下子就已经是daddy了。小时候爸爸的种种，现在还记忆犹新。以后自己就会成为小家伙的回忆了，该怎样做一个好父亲呢？<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/daddy.jpg" alt="Daddy's little baby" /></p>

<h2>daddy需要做的功课：</h2>

<ul>
<li>如何给宝宝喂奶<br/>
  左手托头，让宝宝坐在自己的腿上，面朝自己，右手持奶瓶喂奶。喂奶的过程中要控制宝宝的吃奶速度，宝宝通常会吃一会，休息一会，如果宝宝不吃可以轻轻动一动奶瓶，如果宝宝吃的过快可以先拔出奶瓶，拍拍奶在喂。一般如果一次吃奶较多，由于宝宝的喷门尚未发育好，很容易吐奶，所以需要给宝宝拍奶。拍奶仍然是喂奶的姿势，只不过右手请拍其后背，宝宝打饱嗝或哈欠即可停止。</li>
<li>如何应对突发事件

<ul>
<li>打嗝<br/>
护士的办法是敲宝宝的脚底板，待其哭后打嗝自然消失。但是这一招有的时候也不管用，而且让宝宝用哭泣的方法停止打嗝未免有点不忍心。所以最好的还是预防。一般打嗝的原因很多，比如吃奶吃的太快，受凉，吸入了冷空气，奶水过凉。预防的方法是一般不要在宝宝极度饥饿或者哭泣的时候的时候喂奶，喂奶可以采用多次少量（当然父母要辛苦了），控制好奶水的温度，注意保暖，避免着凉。</li>
<li>溢奶<br/>
拍奶是防止的最好办法，但有时候还是避免不了，所以也可以给宝宝准备一个小围巾。</li>
<li>脱水<br/>
如果宝宝长时间上吐下泻，那么就要非常注意宝宝是否脱水。一旦发现宝宝长达5个小时没有小便、口唇干燥、哭泣没有眼泪，这时候就要当心宝宝有脱水的危险了。</li>
<li>感冒<br/>
感冒分为病毒感冒和伤风感冒。</li>
<li>便秘</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>如何照顾宝宝的饮食</li>
<li>如何进行早期亲子互动</li>
<li>如何帮宝宝养成良好的生活习惯</li>
</ul>


<p>……</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
