<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-20T21:18:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[一岁宝宝教育方案]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/20/edu-plan-for-infant/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-20T08:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/20/edu-plan-for-infant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>教育目的<br/>
很多时候家长不见得重视一岁以内的宝宝，觉得这个时候谈教育太早了，但实际上家长的一言一行已经暴漏在宝宝的视野当中，只不过这种教育是无意识的教育，也是无目的的教育。不管你是否有心，宝宝时时刻刻都在成长和学习。既然这样，那么为什么不进行有目的的幼儿教育呢？</p>

<p>这个阶段的宝宝可以接受感官、运动的训练和情商的教育。为宝宝智力、体力和情商发展打下基础。<br/>
教育活动<br/>
1. 纸箱子游戏<br/>
给宝宝一个干净结实的纸箱子，宝宝可以在纸箱子里坐下，在纸箱子里放一些玩具，让宝宝进行探索。也可以跟宝宝玩捉迷藏。目的是让宝宝认识空间的概念。</p>

<ol>
<li><p>分类游戏<br/>
可以让宝宝对各种玩具或者食物进行分类，给宝宝一堆物件，然后让宝宝挑选放到不同的盒子里。最好有不同颜色的盒子，分类的方法最好也是多种多样的。目的是让宝宝学会观察区分，同时形成类别的概念。</p></li>
<li><p>堆高楼<br/>
让宝宝把玩具堆在一起，可以是积木，也可以是其他的东西。可能开始的时候宝宝只会搞破坏，把堆好的高楼弄倒，这也是探索重力的过程，后面一点一点的他就学会做不同的动作。比如把一个高楼上东西放到另外一个高楼上。</p></li>
<li><p>找玩具<br/>
当着宝宝的面把玩具藏在被子里面，让宝宝找出来。锻炼宝宝空间记忆的能力。</p></li>
<li><p>玩水<br/>
让宝宝用小勺子把水从一个容器转移到另外一个容器里。理解“空”和“满”的概念。也可以玩“沉”和”浮”。（要特别慎重）</p></li>
</ol>


<p>【安全问题】<br/>
必须有大人看护。<br/>
防止宝宝吞咽、跌倒、异物进入鼻子，保护好眼睛。</p>

<p>游戏资源<br/>
<a href="http://cn.babycenter.com/baby/lets_play/">亲子游戏大全：0-1岁亲子游戏|宝宝中心</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[typing with sound]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/19/typing-with-sound/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T13:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/19/typing-with-sound</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nowardays people spend a lot of time in front of their computer. Most of the time they have to use their eyes whether they are typing or sufing on the internet.</p>

<p>But when you are using computer too much you will find your eyes hurt. Lots of students get short-sighted. A idea come to me, why not close my eye to type in front of a computer. Is it possible, may be ti is possible. So I try to find a sofware to help me to do this job. I find a one, and it works. Now I can sit in front of my computer and keep my eyes closed and typing wha I want to say. Isn&#8217;t it amazing. This software will also help blind peaple to type, because it can sound the key so they can hear what they are typiing.</p>

<p>For me, it just helps to rest my eyes and concentrate on what I am writing.</p>

<p>This is not a new idea, but if is an intersting idea.</p>

<p>The above paragraph is written by me blindly.</p>

<p>Another idea interesting is using your left hand to control the mouse and use your right hand to click. This will help you to coordinate your left brain and right brain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lesson plan of cell structure]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-16T11:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Topic: Cell structure/Biology<br/>
Designer: <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/about/">Chunlei Zhang</a><br/>
Student: High school students<br/>
Notes: This is just an imaginary teaching learning scenario sequences.</p>

<p>Imagine a house in your mind(or you can draw it), maybe your family house, maybe not. What does it look like from outside? What about the look of inside? What is the house composed of? What is the function of each part? Can you ask more questions about house?( who made them? which style? what is it made of? how to make a house?) cool!</p>

<p>Today we are going to study cell,similar with house, you can imagine cell as a house for a new strange life. You can ask any questions you want? (list students questions)</p>

<p>Some of your questions, scientists have answered? some question still need further inquiry.</p>

<p>Do you know why scientists study cell?(R or NR) They want to know more about life, an essential question is &#8220;What is life is made of?&#8221; They finally found the answer through a special equipment &#8211; microscope. Their finding suggest that most organism are made of cell. There is a story of discovery of cell.(telling the story)</p>

<p>Cell are usually very very small, and invisible to the naked eye. Do you have any experience of bleeding? What is the color of blood? If you take out of the blood cells, then it looks like this.[picture] What can you infer from this picture? If you look at blood through microscope, then you can see this. These are blood cells. If you look at the blood vessel, you will see this.(video) Not only blood, every parts of your body is made of cells.(student can also draw this conclusion by observing the picture of different tissue are made of different types cells)</p>

<p>Can you guess what is inside of a cell?(Predicted answers: empty, just water or solution, there must be some structures inside)</p>

<p>If we use electron microscope, then we can see the inside structure of the cell. Here is some pictures, try to build a cell structure model as a group. You can number different structures.</p>

<p>When the structures were first discovered by scientist, they also found it hard to communicate, so they name them. Sometime they name them by their characteristics, sometimes using the scientist&#8217;s name. (give the names of different structure) Can you distinguish the different structures inside a cell? Have a try in your group.</p>

<p>Group assessment, show Simulation and let students guess what is the structure and its possible function.</p>

<p>How the different structures relate with each other? We don&#8217;t know. What do you suggest, if you are going to study this research question.</p>

<p>Scientists got these pictures, when they study how proteins are made and transported outside of cells.[three pictures]</p>

<p>What can you see in these pictures? What can you infer? Can you guess or infer the functions of different structures? How do they function together in this process?</p>

<p>Home work: Make a cell structure model that can represent all your group knowledge about cell. We will share and discuss our models on next lesson.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let us do 'lecture']]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/15/let-us-do-lecture/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T12:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/15/let-us-do-lecture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I participated the method class by Dr. Luft and responsed to her question &#8220;How students learn best? by rehearing something, learning the vocabulary, or by doing science&#8221;.</p>

<p>My response was: the answer was obvious doing science will let student learn most, but if we take out of the word &#8220;best&#8221;, all approaches can help student learn in special situations.</p>

<p>I know it is a little misleading and I am afraid that some students in the classroom might misunderstood me. Well, by saying that, I don&#8217;t mean we should really repeat our explanations to students again and again or let students master only vocabularies or terms. But I do want say we should not put &#8216;lecture&#8217; on the opposite side of &#8216;inquiry&#8217;. I also want to point out that we should be very careful to use these two words to label teaching practices, especially those of student teachers.</p>

<p>Well, lecture, You can lecture; Some teacher is only able to lecture. But if you decide to use lecture, try to do it good. Because lecture can be totally different styles and outcomings.</p>

<p>It is interesting &#8211; we did not teach student teachers how to lecture, although this conception exist in their mind, and they are very likely to use this approach in the beginning of their carriers &#8211; isn&#8217;t it.</p>

<p>Ok, let&#8217;s do lecture.(really?)<br/>
There are different levels of lectures.<br/>
1.  Some teacher just stands there and say something, whether related or not. Student are very easily lost interests and get boring and then sleeping. Sometime they appear awake, but their mind are sleep.<br/>
2.  Some teacher stand there say something interesting, student are engaged and listen carefully, some can even retell the interesting stories to others. It is better, right.<br/>
3.  Some stand there say something putting students on uncomfortable positions, let students think critically about the dilemma or issues and discuss with each other, which may have a profound impact on what students believe and act in the future.</p>

<p>Some lecturer also do some performance or something tricky or funny; Some lecture even let audience participate, here is a example of <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZGY0wPAnus">TED lecture: the art of misdirection</a>. Whether lecture or inquiry, they are just labels. Label itself can not guarantee your teaching quality and students&#8217; learning outcomes. We should keep this in mind.</p>

<p>In fact, what teachers can do and only do is create learning opportunity by engaging student in learning activities. Student learn new knowledge through their learning experience. But, different learning experience have different consequences. The following is the learning pyriod.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/learningpyramid.png" alt="learning pyramid" /></p>

<p>You can see from the picture above, student can sit and listen, learn by listening and reading. This process just get information into their short term memory not long term memory. So they may just listen and forget, rarely transfer the new knowledge into new situations.</p>

<p>They can also study by doing science,trying to figure out questions such as what can I do with this stuff ? How to relate all these stuff? What data to collect? How to collect? What is happening? What is going to happen? Why it happen? Why it doesn&#8217;t happen? and so on. This approach not only work on the working memory, but also interact with the long term memory &#8211; their prior ideas and conceptual frameworks. They have to recall what they had learned and experienced in order to solve all these problems.</p>

<p>In the learning pyramid, the most effective way is learning by teaching,just as what the student teacher are doing now. Usually we suppose student teachers already have enough content knowledge for teaching the topic, but it is not true. Many studies showed that beginning teachers&#8217; content knowledge are usually Fragmented and less connected, it was also structured for doing test not teaching.<a href="#1">1</a> Maybe it is enough for exam but not enough for teaching.</p>

<p>Inquiry research showed that good inquiry are significantly better than lecture, but it has a precondition &#8211; the teacher have good knowledge ground.<a href="#2">2</a> Carlsen (1991) reported that when teaching self-identified high knowledge topics, teacher were more likely to ask more high level questions than teaching low knowledge topics.<a href="#3">3</a> But student teachers usually lack of this ground, they are struggling with integrating inquiry into their lessons. It is not an easy thing achieved overnight, but a step by step continuing process.</p>

<p>Recently, I read a book review <a href="http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108010/chapters/Learning,-or-Not-Learning,-in-School.aspx">Learning,or not Learning,in school</a>. The author of the book argued teacher can not give a model or demonstration, and then let student follow the model to do on their own(the mistake I also made in my teaching). There should be some middle stages, such as discussing or doing together or let students do it collaborative, before let them do it by their own. The big idea is Gradually ownership shifting, or gradual release of responsibility. It is not a new idea, but I like it.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/learningshift.png" alt="learning shift" /><br/>
This picture is from: <a href="http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108010/chapters/Learning,-or-Not-Learning,-in-School.aspx">Learning,or not Learning,in school</a></p>

<p>As you can see in the picture, the middles stages Guided Instruction(we do it) and Collaborative(you do it together) sometimes is missing our teaching. This may explain why students can&#8217;t do it well as teacher expected, because the learning process is too sharp.</p>

<p>Why I want to highlight the point that DO NOT put lecture in the opposite position of Inquiry, I have other concerns. Try to think:<br/>
What happen if student teacher believe in inquiry but can not do it well?<br/>
==>They drop out. Because they tend to believe themselves not suitable for teaching.</p>

<p>Another extreme concern is:<br/>
What happen if teacher only believe lecture and only one direction approach?<br/>
==>They refuse to change and can&#8217;t do a good job,finally they may drop out.</p>

<p>Usually, student teacher know they should do inquiry or make their class more interactive, but they are just not able to do it or feel too hard to do it. Why this happen? What to do with this? If this doesn&#8217;t change, they will form a belief that inquiry doesn&#8217;t suit them or their teaching. It is a hot potato. Well one possible approach to this problem is &#8220;we do it together&#8221;.</p>

<p>We were taught to not label students, right? We also should avoid to label teachers. Abused labels can cause problems even disasters, for example, students who labeled themselves as visual learner would say, I can&#8217;t learn very well because the teacher used very little pictures, simulations. Really? In fact, the label just limit students&#8217; learning approaches instead of expand their ways of learning. Good learner should use every possible way to learn and develop skills respectively.</p>

<p>Who should take the responsibility for learning? Teacher? Students? Or both? Or the responsibility gradually shift from teacher to students?</p>

<p>What strategies or methods are suitable for this shifting?</p>

<p>These are the questions that are worth to think over.</p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a id="1">[1]</a> Hauslein, P. L., Good, R. G., &amp; Cummins, C. L. (1992). Biology content cognitive structure: From science student to science teacher. Journal of Research in Science Teaching, 29(9), 939-964.<br/>
<a id="2">[2]</a> Blanchard, M. R., Southerland, S. A., Osborne, J. W., Sampson, V. D., Annetta, L. A., &amp; Granger, E. M. (2010). Is inquiry possible in light of accountability?: A quantitative comparison of the relative effectiveness of guided inquiry and verification laboratory instruction. Science Education, 94(4), 577-616.<br/>
<a id="3">[3]</a> Carlsen, W. S. (1991). Effects of new biology teachers&#8217; subject‐matter knowledge on curricular planning. Science Education, 75(6), 631-647.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assess for Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/14/assess-for-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-14T13:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/14/assess-for-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to a the seminar <a href="http://www.ctl.uga.edu/node/486">Teaching and Assessing so Your Students Learn More: Maximizing Learning-Centered Pedagogy</a> by Dr. Phyllis Blumberg.</p>

<p>We did some interactive activities,such as drawing a picture of learning-centered teaching, think and discuss, group disscussion of a special topic and report. I attended the discussion of how to use assessment to promote students&#8217; learning with 6 people.</p>

<p>Although most participants are college faculties, but when assigned to group work, some tend to speak more than the others, unaware of someone not speaking a word. I want to rearrange the process by divided into two small groups, but I feel hard to interupt and unsure which way will work better. Athough we do discussed sometimes one student dominates the group work and coversation, some people are too shy to say anything. You see, sometimes people say it but not do it and even unaware of this inconsistence.</p>

<p>There are various assessments that can be used for different purposes.<br/>
Before class you can give students questiong to guide their reading and explore their prior ideas.</p>

<pre><code>multiple choice question  
guiding questions  
open questions  
Dilemma  
Senario  
judgement  
</code></pre>

<p>In class, you can give student short quiz to know if students get the point of if they are able to apply them.</p>

<pre><code>Clicker  
Online analysis  
Open questions and discussion  
short quiz  
Drawing      
</code></pre>

<p>After class, assignments can help students review, exercise and enhance what they learned.</p>

<pre><code>Online assessment  
observation  
hand-on  
Reading  
Design  
Problem soving  
exercise  
learning activities judgement and improvement  
</code></pre>

<p>Final exam can report students&#8217; acheivement.</p>

<pre><code>interview(when there are only several students, this would be a good choice)  
project(which let student really take the ownership)  
write a paper/story  
design  
make vedio/prezi  
oral presentation/defence  
Fair or competition  
Paper exam  
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The passion of his life]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/the-passion-of-his-life/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T19:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/the-passion-of-his-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>He was a UGA professor. He died today, of a Severe disease. His wife is also a UGA professor in Pysics Department. She said his husband only left two sentences to his friends and students in UGA.</p>

<p>First, he just say GOODBYE.</p>

<p>Second, he said must guarantee every student have access to his collection, because it is really his passion&#8211;lifelong passion.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[learning or not learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/learning-or-not-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T12:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/learning-or-not-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Learning is dangerous; Not learning is lethal.</p>

<p>Why learning is dangerous? Because when are learning you have to change&#8211;habits, beliefs,knowledge,actions and so on, every change may let you sit in an uncomfortable place unsure of the following consequence.</p>

<p>But not learning is lethal. Because the world change in every minutes, even every seconds, if you act the same way as before, you will be very likely lost your job, get a stroke and worry about your food and Pension.</p>

<p>What to do then?</p>

<p>Learn with a teacher, learn with your friends and learn in your own feasible and effective ways. Of course you have to study how learning happen to you at first.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HungerU]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T14:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to MLC to attend a lecture by Dr Michelle Smith. In front of MLC, I saw a strange thing. You can see the picture below.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hungeru.png" alt="hungeru" /></p>

<p>The fact and statistics is printed on it. Food still occupy a large percentage(39.8%) in their total household spend. In Congo, 70% goes to food, it means people there are more likely in hunger.</p>

<p>I asked where is the data from? They told me they gathered these data last Saturday, and the survey is still going on.</p>

<p>How can I participate? I asked. Just let people know this fact and then we can change this fact and statistic. Isn&#8217;t it a good idea? College students may not give money directly, but they can collect data and spread the fact all over the world.</p>

<p>Although the program is funded by Farm Journal Foundation, I guess volunteer college students played a role in the Survey and HungerU Tour in different countries. This is the responsibility that our college students are able to and should shoulder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubuntu crash on graphic driver]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/ubuntu-crash-on-graphic-driver/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-08T22:14:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/ubuntu-crash-on-graphic-driver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I updated ubuntu, and then I can&#8217;t start it any more. It show tyy1 login. In fact I met this problem several times before, I know it is caused by the graphic driver update. I have to reinstall the right driver. But I forget where is the driver file and how to setup it.</p>

<p>I tried many times and finially I got it back to normal. The solving process:</p>

<pre><code>#login with your username and password
cd Downloads # where my dirver is
sudo sh amd-driver-64.run
setup it (always select the first selection and ok)
#restart
</code></pre>

<p>I have copied the driver in the folder dirver. so next time I can found it more easily.</p>

<p>The problem I have to solve:<br/>
1.  How to stop the update for the graphic driver?<br/>
2.  How to recover my ubuntu quickly?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TMUX and VIM in ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/tmux-and-vim-in-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-08T13:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/tmux-and-vim-in-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Learning to use a new language is not easy. Learning to use all the shortcut keys of TMUX and VI also takes time.</p>

<p>Today, I want to record what I had learnt about TMUX and Vi.</p>

<p>While, I should divided this post into two posts, but TMUX only takes a little ink, so I just put it here.</p>

<p>TMUX is a tool to help you divide your screen of your terminals into several screens. Whenever you want to use hotkeys, you have to press Ctrl + B first, then you can press the hot key. You can change the pre hot key, but I just leave it unchanged. The most used keys are the following:<br/>
REMEMBER to press Ctrl+B first!!</p>

<pre><code>%  #divide screen left and right  
"  #divede screen up and down  
Ctrl + Down #make the down screen smaller  
exit #cancel present screen  
n  #new dash window  
</code></pre>

<p>That is it.</p>

<p>Then let me record the tips of VI. Well it is much complex than the former. Generally, it has three mode, i mode(insert and edit), v mode(copy and paste), and : mode(file operation). Ok let me write down the most used keys:</p>

<pre><code>Ctrl +: #this will let you enter the file operation mode  
i       #this will let you enter the edit mode, Press Esc to enter : mode  
v       #this will let you enter copy and paste mode, Press Esc to enter : mode  
</code></pre>

<p>When you press &#8216;v&#8217; in the : mode, you can press Arrow Button to select the text you want to copy or delete, and then press:</p>

<pre><code>y       #copy  
d       #delete
p       #paste  
Ctrl+:  #show clipped board  
:%s/ski/sky/g  #replace ski with sky in all place  
</code></pre>

<p>Isn&#8217;t easy. But it takes time to get used to them and operate unconsioucely.</p>

<p>I also want to keep down some hot keys of Ubuntu, let me google first. Ok here are they:</p>

<pre><code>Ctrl + Alt + L     lock the desktop  
Win                applications desktop  
Ctrl + Alt + Left  shift to left desktop  
Alt + Tab          shitt applications  
Alt + F4           shut down present application  
Ctrl+Win+Up        Maxilize present window  
Ctrl+Win+Down      Minilize presnet window  
Ctrl+Alt+T         Open terminal
$ command1 &amp;&amp; command2 # execute command1 first and succeed then execute command2  
Ctrl+Shift+Arrow   Shift Workplace  
Ctrl+Shift+Alt+Arrow   move present window to Workplace  
</code></pre>

<p>Want to know more, click <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/KeyboardShortcuts">here</a><br/>
Now almost done, and wait to be expanded.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do the job or have fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/do-the-job-or-have-fun/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T19:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/do-the-job-or-have-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes when something becomes your job, even you love it, when you have to do if before a deadline, you tend to lose the fun you had before.</p>

<p>Something you don&#8217;t have to do it, but you are interested and want to try. You are more likely to do better and have a lot of fun.</p>

<p>As a teacher, how do you apply this rule to your teaching?</p>

<p>Is it the reason why teacher drop out in their early career?</p>

<p>How to let teachers have fun in their teaching?</p>

<p>How to let students have fun in their learning?</p>

<p>Why people have fun in doing something? The following is a list of &#8220;something&#8221; can offer:<br/>
1. Provide new/pleasant experience<br/>
People are born with curiosity, and love to have new experience. They like to do the thing they have never done before or doing the same thing but in new ways.<br/>
2. Engage emotion<br/>
Passion, curiosity, sense of acheivement even superiority are all emotions letting people have fun. So if the design can engage these emotions, then it becomes hot.<br/>
3. Match their habits and mindset<br/>
They don&#8217;t need to take much effort in order to operate or understand. It is user friendly designed.<br/>
4. Meet various needs<br/>
5. Be simple and neat</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Machine learning and Octave]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/machine-learning-and-octave/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T12:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/machine-learning-and-octave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I joined NG&#8217; class of <a href="https://class.coursera.org/ml-004/class/index">Machine Learning</a></p>

<p>I start to learn programing with <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/octave/about.html">Octave</a></p>

<p>Here is the Basic Commands from Ng&#8217;s class notes</p>

<pre><code>
PS1('>> '); % make pre short  
1==2 %false  
1~=2  
1 && 2 % AND  
1 || 0 % OR  
xor(1,0) % OR
a=3; % semicolon supressing output  
b='hi';  
disp(sprintf('2 decimals: %0.2f',a))  
a=pi;  
format long  
format short  
A=[1 2; 3 4; 5 6]  
ones(3,1)  
zeros(1,3)  
rand(1,3)  
hist(-6+sqrt(10)*(randn(1,10000)))  
size(A,1)  
save hello.txt v -ascii % save as text  
eye(6)  
length(A)  
load featuresX.dat  
load priceY.dat  
load('featuresX.dat')  
who  
clear priceY  
clear  
v=priceY(1:10)  
A(3,1)  
A(2,:) % ":" means every element along that row/column  
A([1 3],:) % get 1,3 row  
A(:,2)=[10;11;12]  
A=[A,[100;101;102]]  
A(:) % put all elements into a single vector  
C=[A B]  
C=[A; B]  
sum(A)  
prod(A)  
floor(A)  
ceil(A)  
max(A,[],1)  
max(A,[],2)  
max(A)  
flipud(eye(9))  
t=[0:0.01:0.98]  
y1=sin(2*pi*4*t);
y2=cos(2*pi*4*t);  
plot(t,y1);  
plot(t,y2,'r')  
xlabel('time')  
ylabel('value')  
legent('sin','cos')  
title('my plot')  
print -dpng 'myPlot.png'  
close  
figure(1);plot(t,y1);  
figure(2);plot(t,y2);  
subplot(1,2,1); % divides plot a 1x2 grid, acce  
axis([0.5 1 -1 1]) & x [0.5 1] y[-1 1]  
clf;
imagesc(A)  
imagesc(A), colorbar, colormap gray;  

indices=1:10;  
for i=indices,
   disp(i);
end;  

i=1;  
while i <=5;  
  v(i)=100;  
  i=i+1;  
end;  

i=1;  
while true,  
  v(i)=999;  
  i=i+1;  
  if i==6,  
    break;  
  end;  
end;  

v(1)=2;  
if v(1)==1,  
  disp('equal one')  
elseif v(1)==2,  
  disp('equal two')  
else  
  disp('not one or two')  
end;  

pwd  
ls  

addpath('C:users\ang\Desktop') % octave search path  
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conflicts between commercialization of science and education equity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/30/conflicts-between-commercialisation-of-science-and-education-equity/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T23:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/30/conflicts-between-commercialisation-of-science-and-education-equity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I attended Dr Jackson&#8217; class <a href="http://djackson.myweb.uga.edu/8990/Daily/Day12.html">ESCI 8990 Daily Page</a>.</p>

<p>We discussed questions:<br/>
1.  whether scientific knowledge is a private product?<br/>
2.  whether is it right to use grants to apply patent or develop products for profits?<br/>
3.  conflicts between patent protection and equal access to scientific knowledge.</p>

<p>I didn&#8217;t say a word because I was the only Chinese around the table and intellectual property protection in China has a bad reputation although the situation is improving. I don&#8217;t want to defend too much, but I guess everyone may only have one story about the IPP in China. But just as Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie said: <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/chimamanda_adichie_the_danger_of_a_single_story.html">There is a danger of a single story</a>. So it will always be good to know more than one story.</p>

<p>The idea of patent protection became popular in industry culture. In order to encourage people and companies to develop more new type of products for society goodness, we give them such protects and advantages in using the patent that they invented first.</p>

<p>But, in agricultural civilization, such as accent China, there is no such idea. Some people may keep their special way of making food or drinks as their secrets, but once the secrets were known by others, they can also make the same food and drinks, and it is legal. The government may also help to publish and transmit some technologies, such as paper making and the printing. If they apply for the patent of making paper and printing, how much money they can earn? But this may also slow down the development of human society. So every patent has limited period for protection. The patent finally becomes common property of human society.</p>

<p>In agricultural civilization, labor is the main value source of a product. Yes, patent tell how to make a product, but it is the labor make it realized. This is not true in industrial civilization, the people or company who possess the patent earn the most of the profit. You will never know how cheap labor become in China nowadays. Is it equal? Is it a new kind of colonization? Many developed country put their factories into developing countries, they use their labor, resources and make wastes and pollution. Is it fair? Is it sustainable? Will it leads to wars? You can read more about <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/drloveccsu/ecojustice-pedagogy">Ecojustice</a>.</p>

<p>Well, industrialization and consumerism are both come from western culture. Human rights is also declared in the western. But there is conflicts between commercialization of science and education equity. The following paragraph is from:<a href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/">The Universal Declaration of Human Rights</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Article 26.
   (1) Everyone has the right to education. Education shall be free, at least in the elementary and fundamental stages. Elementary education shall be compulsory. Technical and professional education shall be made generally available and higher education shall be equally accessible to all on the basis of merit.</p></blockquote>

<p>Poor people receive poor education and they remain poor, becomes a circle. This will only lead to hate and war. Patent protection can help develop new products and technologies and promote the progress of society. It can also benefit some people and groups and hurt the others. Especially, when the researchers use grants(money from citizens) to do research and apply for patents only benefit for a special organization or people. Then it is unfair.</p>

<p>It is also disputable whether something should be a patent. For example, the people invent the product later by his own, will lost all the value of his effort because it would be illegal to for him to use the same way to make product.</p>

<p>The company own the patent seems own a new kind of capital &#8211; Intellectual Capitalism. Government tend to protect their patent rights in order to encourage more company to do research and development. But sometimes it will lead to monopolization and the price of their products becomes unreasonable(several times higher than its actual cost). Will government still protect?</p>

<p>With the global industrial production, with consumerism and commercialization, will this new kind of capitalism &#8211; Intellectual Capitalism create a new colonial history. Do we want this happen? Or it already happened.</p>

<p>There should be a balance between patent protection and common benefit, between efficiency and fairness, between developed and developing countries, between industrial civilization and agricultural civilization, between human and nature, otherwise we are making troubles and potential dangers for ourselves!</p>

<pre><code>On the other hand, science education sits in an uncomfortable place in this landscape given particular aspects of patenting and property rights imply limited access and thus inequity in knowledge acquisition.
</code></pre>

<p>iphone</p>

<p>克隆文化
有性繁殖与无性繁殖</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laptop stand designed by myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-29T22:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is uncomfortable to work on my laptop on a table. Becuase the screen is too low and you have to bend your head which cause pain in the neck.<br/>
So I made a laptop stand using a useless shoes box. Here is the picture.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/laptopstand.png" alt="laptop stand" /></p>

<p>You can alway make a change if you want to. And small change can make a big difference sometimes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't alienate disabled people]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/27/dont-alienate-disabled-people/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T09:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/27/dont-alienate-disabled-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, a TED talk at TEDxStanford moved me deeply. It was given by Rhodes Scholar Rachel Kolb &#8211; who was born deaf. She showed what is possible through family support and self-belief, and proves that what is assumed about you and what you can actually achieve don&#8217;t always match up. In the United States, two-thirds of hearing-impaired people do not complete high school.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/uKKpjvPd6Xo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<!--more-->


<p>When I attended a coteaching workshop, an American teacher asked me if there were any disabled students in Chinese schools. I said very few. In my experiences, from elementary school to high school, even in university, I had never meet a disabled students, who was deaf or blind. Where are they? They do exist, but may live alienated lives out of our eyes.</p>

<p>In UGA, I saw many students sitting on their wheelchairs in streets, classroom, libraries, even on buses. They really provide good access for disabled.</p>

<p>In China, the situation in Beijing and Shanghai may be better than other cities. But we still hardly see disabled people appear in front us, when they do appear, they usually have many accompanies who help them to overcome the unexpected obstacles posed by people unconsciously.</p>

<p>Disabled people do deserve to live a normal life. Please don&#8217;t alienate them!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The metaphor of rock climbing]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/the-metaphor-of-rock-climbing/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T20:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/the-metaphor-of-rock-climbing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so hard to descibe how teacher develop related knowledge to teach a special topic.</p>

<p>I have come up with many analogies to assit my thinking and modeling of teacher knowledge development.</p>

<p>Here is another wonderful analogy Rock Climbing. The following is a picture:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/rock-climbing.png" alt="rock climbing" /><br/>
More about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_climbing#Crack_climbing">Rock climbing</a><br/>
The teacher developed lots of intermediate representations (just like the cracks, faces, slabs in rock climbing) to help students learning the scientific concept.</p>

<p>Good teacher can &#8220;see&#8221; the postions of students and can &#8220;arise&#8221; the right representation to help. The subject matter knowledge is the moutain. The &#8220;safety rope&#8221; is the good teacher-student relationship which keep the safe environment for learning. The routes can be fun and the goal can be challenging. They all motivates student to climb and learn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From falling objects experiment to a simulated experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/from-falling-objects-experiment-to-a-simulated-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T13:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/from-falling-objects-experiment-to-a-simulated-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I attened the Science Method class. An interesting question discussed was the experiment of falling objects-the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galileo%27s_Leaning_Tower_of_Pisa_experiment">Galileo&#8217;s Leaning Tower of Pisa experiment</a>.  Dr. Luft provided us some students&#8217; responses and let us to figure out the students&#8217; thinking and how to response to students properly.</p>

<p>But the question caught my curiosity in the class was two ice cube droping from the same inclination.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bigsmallball.png" alt="two ball fall at the same height" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I asked my classmates what happens in the following situations.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/3inclinations.png" alt="picture" /></p>

<p>I acturally did the experiment using <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/en/simulation/energy-skate-park">simulation environment</a>.</p>

<p>The result is interesting. Ball B frist arrived at the bottom with lest time.(The first two curves are situation A; Next two curves are situation B)
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/skater.png" alt="Result" /></p>

<p>Ball A is the second arrived. Ball C is the last one. <br/>
From Leaning Tower of Pisa Experiment to simulated experiment, what a big change information technology has made to our science teaching and learning!</p>

<p>In fact, David Scott-Astronaut of  Apollo 15-recreated Galileo&#8217;s famous experiment on the Moon by Hammer and Feather Drop.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/4mTsrRZEMwA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>You see the space technology also expanded our learning experience and provided us an amazing teaching resource-a dicrepant event.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The beautiful leaves on the tree]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/19/the-beautiful-leaves-on-the-tree/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-19T16:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/19/the-beautiful-leaves-on-the-tree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/autumn-tree.jpg" alt="autumn-tree.jpg" /></p>

<p>On a grassy lawn near the road, standed a little girl about five years old. She was looking up at the colorful tree leaves and jumping to reach them. She jumped up using all her energy but found herself still get nothing.</p>

<p>I walked close to the girl-she was really a beautiful angel.</p>

<p>&#8220;Do you need help?&#8221; I asked.<br/>
She stared at me with her shinning black eyes without saying a word.<br/>
&#8220;Do you want some leaves? I can help!&#8221; I repeated. <br/>
&#8220;No&#8221; she answered. <br/>
&#8220;I can use the ball.&#8221; She fetched a ball from the ground just several steps away.<br/>
&#8220;then the leaves will fall.&#8221;<br/>
&#8220;You are very clever!&#8221; I said.<br/>
After I left, she began throw the ball up to the leaves again and again - very exitedly.</p>

<p>Well, she may never heared of the term &#8220;gravity&#8221;, but she do have been aware of it and even make use of it to get the beautiful leaves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[美国科学教师职业状况观察]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/08/science-teachers-life-in-unite-states/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T21:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/08/science-teachers-life-in-unite-states</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在佐治亚科学教师年收入大约为30000美元（最低2万，最高4万左右）。
根据美国教育部1996年的数据，不同州略有差异，一般最低也有2万美元，最高可达5-6万美元。</p>

<p>一个科学教师参加时长一整年的专业发展项目，可以获得1500美元的补助。<br/>
参加专业发展项目的老师可以获得额外的空余时间用于学习和研讨。<br/>
一个科学教师一周要上30节课左右。<br/>
每个班级有学生30人。</p>

<p>完善中。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Model-based Learning Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/03/model-based-learning-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-03T10:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/03/model-based-learning-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>What is Model-based Learning(MBL)?</h3>

<p>How students learn: science in classroom</p>

<h3>Why to promote MBL now?</h3>

<h3>How MBL affects science learning?</h3>

<h3>How to use MBL in science classroom?</h3>

<h4>How to process MBL?</h4>

<h4>How to assess students&#8217; work?</h4>

<h4>How to adapt the activities for various needs?</h4>

<h4>Simulation approach</h4>

<h4>Collaboration approach</h4>

<h4>Resources</h4>

<h3>What are the Opportunities and Challenges for science teachers?</h3>

<h4>Misunderstandings</h4>

<h4>Lack of knowledges and skills</h4>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
