<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-23T19:13:34-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教育游戏推荐]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/23/educational-games/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-23T17:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/23/educational-games</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>教育游戏活动</p>

<h3>STEM教育类：</h3>

<p>设计挑战<br/>
1、用A4纸设计并制作一架飞行器，要求能在同等高度在空中飞行最久。<br/>
2、设计机场电梯防护栏，要求能够避免行人携带行李车乘坐传送带式电梯。</p>

<h3>教育技术类：</h3>

<p>1、即时反馈技术<a href="Kahoot!%0Ahttps://kahoot.it/">Kahoot</a><br/>
2、仿真模拟游戏<a href="https://phet.colorado.edu/">Phet</a><br/>
3、严肃科学游戏<a href="http://www.carolina.com/teacher-resources/Interactive/online-game-cell-structure-cellcraft-biology/tr11062.tr">Cell Craft</a><br/>
4、科学能力测评<a href="https://www.nationsreportcard.gov/science_2009/ict_tasks.asp">NAEP Interactive Computer Tasks</a></p>

<h3>博弈游戏：</h3>

<p>1、作业时间博弈<br/>
4名学生一起玩游戏。分别扮演数学老师、语文老师、英语老师、科学老师。学生做多能完成的作业量为4个小时，每位老师都可以布置一个作业时间（0-4小时），如果4位老师布置的总时间超出了4小时，那么布置最多的老师作业取消资格。如果还超出4个小时，第二多的老师作业无效，直到作业总时间少于4小时。累计4轮，布置有效作业时间最多的老师获胜。</p>

<p>2、<a href="http://wenku.baidu.com/link?url=4uBsGnuqAfvV7OUYpkTN6Gr4FR-LTd5w5VdpJ_xXRNZ656LCgBjOA5xPaHls5WexPOhDm88aGcaIQkEjxACkWlv8mQnYUuaidY9I_p5zwR3">红黑博弈游戏</a></p>

<p>3、<a href="http://wenku.baidu.com/link?url=ag8JzKqecYLW0PwDhF5VQ1ZUdx96xZu61mDpdP3tAbv5f_OrVIKl4xFw30mK80bzhucrlDMdYorkiImUp5DCsfOD8Aohv_akVf-azLRKSbW">趣味博弈游戏-讨教还价、百元大钞</a></p>

<h3>团队合作游戏：</h3>

<p>1、<a href="http://open.163.com/movie/2014/4/B/M/M9NB0CLKV_M9NBBIPBM.html">拇指摔跤-游戏的力量</a></p>

<object width="640" height="360"><param name="movie" value="http://swf.ws.126.net/openplayer/v02/-0-2_M9NB0CLKV_M9NBBIPBM-vimg1_ws_126_net//image/snapshot_movie/2014/3/I/9/M9NBBIJI9-1423031805465.swf?isTEDPlay=1"></param><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"></param><param name="wmode" value="transparent"></param><embed src="http://swf.ws.126.net/openplayer/v02/-0-2_M9NB0CLKV_M9NBBIPBM-vimg1_ws_126_net//image/snapshot_movie/2014/3/I/9/M9NBBIJI9-1423031805465.swf?isTEDPlay=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="640" height="360" allowFullScreen="true" wmode="transparent" allowScriptAccess="always"></embed></object>


<p>2、背靠背站起</p>

<object width=640 height=360><param name="movie" value="//share.vrs.sohu.com/my/v.swf&topBar=1&id=14201808&autoplay=false&from=page"></param><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"></param><param name="wmode" value="Transparent"></param><embed width=640 height=360 wmode="Transparent" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" quality="high" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//share.vrs.sohu.com/my/v.swf&topBar=1&id=14201808&autoplay=false&from=page" type="application/x-shockwave-flash"/></embed></object>


<p>3、教师双簧<br/>
两人一组，一名同学表达教师的口头语言，一名同学表演教师的肢体语言，开展教学。观众或评委根据两人的配合默契度打分或点赞!。<br/>
可以分解教师口头语言和肢体语言，也可以分解教师的板书和讲解，还可以分解教师的语言和表情。</p>

<h3>板书游戏：</h3>

<p>1、我画你猜（将抽象概念可视化）<br/>
组织者准备20张抽象概念的卡片，比赛选手两人一组，一个能看到卡片的概念，但是不能说话也能写字，只能画图。另一人猜测卡片背后的概念。看不同小组谁能够猜的对更多的卡片。</p>

<h3>现场教学比赛（语言和板书）</h3>

<p>组织者准备若干（如20个）教学主题，这些主题可以事先让参赛者知道。比赛时，让参赛者随机抽签，抽到之后马上开始3分钟教学讲解。两两PK最终，有观众投票决定胜负。赢得最多场数的队伍获胜。</p>

<h3>情境短剧：</h3>

<p>1、未来学校：设想你时空穿越来到一所未来学校，新奇的故事接二连三的发生……<br/>
2、信息土著的教育：工作后你会面临信息土著的学生，作为老师你该何去何从……<br/>
3、新型教师：你将成为怎样的新型教师以适应这个时代的变化发展<br/>
4、学校教育印象：描述你印象深刻的、对你有很重要影响的事件。<br/>
5、交互式短剧：短剧中的角色的命运会受到观众的影响，剧情也会根据观众的投票或反应而发生变化。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[爱是我们最宝贵的财富]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/14/love-is-our-best-legacy/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-14T10:55:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/14/love-is-our-best-legacy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>爱是什么？</p>

<p>它是人与人的一种积极互赖人际关系。如果进一步拓展，它也可以是人与一切事物的积极互赖关系。比如你可以爱父母、爱配偶、爱子女，也可以爱家庭、爱家乡、爱祖国，还可以爱空气、爱原野、爱大海、爱大自然。</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/lovesea.jpg" alt="love" /></p>

<p>爱不仅是言语，更是行动。<br/>
爱有时需要勇气。<br/>
爱是有条件的，但却并不刻求回报。<br/>
爱像火，它发光发热。它可以照亮他人，也可以温暖他人，还可以召唤起别人爱之火。爱可以产生更多的爱。<br/>
理智相似一个壁炉，如果完全密闭空气，爱就会熄灭，如果完全破除，爱就容易泛滥成灾。<br/>
爱不一定导致好的结果，但是缺乏爱的世界注定不精彩。</p>

<p>人本生来就有爱，爱是人的一种固有品性和能力。同情心和换位思考就是爱的基础。但是，它也会被阴影淹没，被冰冷的枷锁束缚，进而让人失去爱的能力而变得麻木。比如嫉妒、仇恨、冷漠会让人弃爱不顾。刻板的职业角色和观念会让人麻木不仁，失去感受爱的能力。沉迷和上瘾会让人无暇为爱行动。</p>

<p>爱是如此珍贵和重要，所以人一定不要失去爱的能力。爱的能力包括感知、消化、行动三种能力，下面分别介绍。</p>

<p>首先是感知爱的能力。这在很大程度上，取决于你设置的临界点。有的人把这个临界点设置的很低，所以他容易感动，也容易做出爱的行动，从而也更大的机会获得爱。有的人把这个临界点设置的很高，所以他难于感受到别人的爱，也不愿意给予爱，这样一来也就更难获得别人的爱。就像笑点很低的人最开心一样，爱点低的人更幸福。当一个人对别人期望越大，实际上其设置的爱点也越大，其结果往往是失望越大。</p>

<p>其次是消化爱的能力。有人获得了别人的爱，受宠若惊，不知所措。有的人则骄傲自大，认为理所应当。还有的人会心生歉疚，认为自己不配拥有。从感知爱到产生爱的行动，这就是爱的消化过程。它直接决定着爱是否能传递下去。如果认为别人的爱是天经地义、理所应当，就不会升起一颗感恩之心，爱的感知也就不会转化为爱的行动。人人爱我，就不会产生我爱人人。而起决定作用的就是那颗感恩之心。</p>

<p>最后是爱的行动能力，也就是给予爱的能力。爱有大小长短之分。如果某人爱你，你也爱某人，这是小爱。如果某人爱你，而你爱人人，这是大爱。&#8221;投我以桃，报之以李&#8221;是短爱，&#8221;两情若是久长时，又岂在朝朝暮暮&#8221;是长爱。做出爱的行动是需要智慧和勇气的，同时也需要毅力和才能。所谓“穷则独善其身，达者兼济天下”，这穷和达固然可以理解为财富或权利，也可以理解为做出爱的行动能力。</p>

<p>爱虽有大小长短之分，但却并无高低贵贱之别。或大或小，或长或短，所有真心的爱都值得珍惜拥有，都能让这个世界更美好。</p>

<p>一个人一定要有爱的能力，感知爱、消受爱、给予爱。因为它是我们给予这个世界的最好礼物，也或许是人类最宝贵的财富。</p>

<p>这些文字就算是情人节礼物吧！</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[加拿大卓越教师项目总结]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/13/ubc-program-summary/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-13T12:48:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/13/ubc-program-summary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>21天的紧张学习，一次特别意义的春节，3次新奇而愉快校园之旅，在我们全员参与的一场快闪热舞之后落下帷幕。有<a href="https://v.qq.com/x/page/a0371cjogl2.html">视频</a>为证。</p>

<p><embed src="https://imgcache.qq.com/tencentvideo_v1/playerv3/TPout.swf?max_age=86400&v=20161117&vid=a0371cjogl2&auto=0" allowFullScreen="true" quality="high" width="480" height="400" align="middle" allowScriptAccess="always" type="application/x-shockwave-flash"></embed></p>

<p>这次培训项目是Tony老师为我们师范生精心准备和量身打造的、高质量的课程。当中 有很多教育理念、教学技巧、策略以及教学活动都值得未来教师教育项目参考和借鉴。</p>

<p>其中给我形象最为深刻的活动如下：<br/>
1、教育印象（image of schooling: An image about teaching or learning that has some meaning to you）<br/>
2、劈叉苦茶 Pechakucha Pairs(15seconds X20 pages) 开学第一天就明确最后作业<br/>
Planning Sheet for Pechakucha- peer review<br/>
3、在地性学习（place-based learning &#8211; interviewing the campus）<br/>
4、读书进程 （Reading Schedule）<br/>
5、TPI survey<br/>
6、Multiple Intelligence survey<br/>
7、学习经历短剧（Skit that illustrates your experience as a student）<br/>
8、学校观察（New understanding and questions about teachers, students, subject matter, Milieux）<br/>
9、个体帮助（Meet with professor Marina Milner-Bolotin）<br/>
10、社会和情感学习能力（Self-awareness, Social awareness, Responsible decision-making, self-management, relationship skills）</p>

<h3>教育策略及其背后理念:</h3>

<p>可视化（教育是认知加工辅助）如画示意图<br/>
游戏化（教育是刺激反应连接）如开展比赛，教师团队和学生团队pk，4人讲同一主题，两两一组，同课异构，相互PK，一方做教师另外一方就做学生，另外4人担任裁判，做教学记录，并最终在支持的一方处签名。<br/>
民主化（教育是社会文化转型）如让学生决定准备时间，分权而不是控制<br/>
意义化（教育是意义主动构建）如参观学校主动构建对学校教育的理解</p>

<h3>具体的做法和技巧：</h3>

<p>Philosophy of teaching statement<br/>
short test<br/>
Fill the form sheet to draw your conclusion</p>

<h3>Group work</h3>

<p>1、Think-pair-share<br/>
2、Jigsaw<br/>
3、Three step interview(interview alternate and then share in group)<br/>
4、Group Investigation(找到共同兴趣点、计划研究内容、研究任务分工、分析、总结、报告)</p>

<p>divide into different groups by taking off a shoe</p>

<h3>Inquiry based activities</h3>

<p>1、Use factoid to provoke student questions(e.g.: Tornadoes are nearly invisible whirling winds until dust and debris are picked up or a cloud forms inside the funnel.)<br/>
2、Push student thinking by asking questions(What do you wonder about now? Does this suggest any new approaches, ideas to you worth investigating? what kinds of connections can you make? where do we go from here?)<br/>
3、Slow down<br/>
4、Be on the look out for student&#8217;s questions and persistent interests<br/>
5、Use previous activities to move forward<br/>
6、Help students make sense of non-fiction text（by different symbols）</p>

<p>促进学生思考的策略：<br/>
分享教学目标、关键问题或面临的挑战<br/>
随机提问<br/>
Wait Time<br/>
澄清或转述学生的回答<br/>
追问（为什么？你同意吗？你能举个例子吗？）<br/>
让学生总结（你可以总结一下小丽的观点吗？）<br/>
克制价值判断性言论<br/>
让学生外化思维过程（你是怎么得出这个答案的？）<br/>
信息可视化（如图片组织者）</p>

<p>简单学习策略<br/>
时间伙伴（clock buddies）<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/clock_buddies.png" alt="clock buddiest" />
Think, Pair, Share(2分钟独立思考，2分钟同伴交流，最后班级分享)<br/>
图形组织者<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/graphic_organizer.png" alt="graphic organizert" /><br/>
PMI chart<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/PMI.png" alt="PMI chart" /></p>

<p>更复杂的学习策略<br/>
3 step interview（访谈者，被访谈者，报告员，3个主题的访谈，每一轮角色轮换一次）<br/>
角色扮演\skit（情景短剧）<br/>
拼图Jigsaw（每组派一名学生去专家组学习，然后返回学习小组进行分享）<br/>
Place Mat<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/PlaceMat.png" alt="Place Mat" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[后真相时代：真相依然重要]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/12/fact-is-still-important-in-the-post-truth-era/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-12T16:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/12/fact-is-still-important-in-the-post-truth-era</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在大众媒体和互联网信息满天飞的时代，同样一件事，会有不同的观点和立场，持有不同立场的人都只会选择性的使用所谓“事实”来佐证自己的观点。而大多网民，往往也只是选择一个立场站队而已。似乎真相已经无关紧要，这样的事发生在郭德纲和他徒弟之间纠纷中，发生在傻根和他老婆的离婚事件中，发生在冯小刚和万达对撕之间，发生在特朗普与希拉里的竞选辩论中。</p>

<p>站在一个普通网民的立场，对于一个事件可能压根就没有搞清楚事实的欲望，或者也缺乏辨别信息真伪的能力，更不愿以花费时间，最后结果就是找一个自己愿意相信的故事了事。至于真相，事不关己，也就没那么重要了。即便是某人被黑了，或者受到了舆论不公正的待遇，或者有人造谣生事。在这个时候，真相已经不重要，态度和立场已经压倒了事实。</p>

<p>如果仔细思考，这是一件非常可怕的事。我们可以称之为舆论暴力，舆论不分青红皂白就给当事人洪水猛兽般的压力和冲击，不管当事人做过还是没做过，更可拍的是打压完之后，即便错误了也没有人对所造成的后果负责。</p>

<p>这让我想起一个电影，网民通过一个非法平台来影响玩家现实行为，从接吻到冒险，甚至杀人，因为背后的网民都是匿名的，他们不负担任何责任，最后玩家一个接着一个在完成任务的过程中意外死去，直到主人公联合好友和黑客破坏了游戏平台，曝光了每个匿名网民的真实身份。</p>

<p>我们的网络舆论就像这个游戏，戏内戏外不断切换。也许上一秒你是个网民，你根据自己的喜好对冯小刚万达事件发表评论，只顾个人偏好不管事实真伪。下一秒你就变成了当事者，受到不管事实真相、不负责任的外界舆论的人肉搜索和打压。</p>

<p>我们真的希望看到一个这样的世界吗？我们真的想成为一个匿名、不负责任甚至心理变态的舆论暴力的一份子吗？公民理性何在？独立思考能力何在？如果这样的话，人人都不在乎真相，那么我们也就变成了一群网络暴民，冲动、偏激、愚蠢、不负责任、被人利用。</p>

<p>后真相时代是人们面对信息过载的一种无奈现状，千万不要把它当成终点或既成事实而不加改变。在这样的时代，真相本身以及追求真相的意识和能力实际上比任何时代都更宝贵。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LeSoleil Fine Art Gallery]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/09/lesoleil-fine-art-gallery/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-09T12:20:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/09/lesoleil-fine-art-gallery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was wandering around in Vancouver BC last month, I found a art gallery along the Howe Street by chance. It is called LeSoleil Fine Art Gallery.</p>

<p>It was raining and I had some time, so I decided to have a look inside of the gallery. One artist&#8217;s painting named &#8220;That Night the Magic Mirror&#8221; attracted my attention. The artist&#8217;s name is Cecilia Aisin-Gioro (爱新觉罗.恒钦). She is the grandniece of the last Chinese Emperor Pu Yi Aisin-Gioro.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/that-night-the-magic-mirror.jpg" alt="That Night the Magic Mirror original" /></p>

<p>You can find more paintings of her <a href="http://lesoleilfineart.com/cecilia-aisin-gioro">here</a>.</p>

<p>At my first look of the picture, the woman is very beautiful and youthful, but herself in the mirror seems less energetic. When you look the picture carefully, you will found a mistake(or unnatural phenomenon) in the picture. Take your time to have a look.</p>

<p>The woman have two left arms, one you can see directly, one in the mirror, without right arm. What does Cecilia want to say? or it is just a mistake?</p>

<p>The other thing I don&#8217;t like is the face in the mirror. It is flat and dull comparing with her real face.</p>

<p>So I changed it like this.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/that-night-the-magic-mirror11.jpg" alt="That Night the Magic Mirror changed" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UBC week 3: Diversity & Complexity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/01/ubc-week-3/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-01T20:22:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/01/ubc-week-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Monday</h3>

<p>On Monday, we went to Victoria and visited the BC Museum. It took us about 2 hours to look around the natural history and human history exhibition. The most interesting things were Mammoth and indigenous people of Canada. Our students also had a great time on the ferry, because it was the first time for most of them to travel by ferry. I took us nearly one and a half hour to across the Channel. So most of our time was spent on road or boat.</p>

<h3>Tuesday</h3>

<p>On Tuesday, during the time of check in, one student asked about the religion system in Canada. Andrea hesitated whether should talk about this. Tony encouraged her to have a try and she gave use a useful introduction of the family trees and history of different religions in BC. Tony highlighted the idea of religious tolerance, which means people can respect and be tolerant to others&#8217; religions.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, a terrible terrorist attack happened in Quebec, in which one man killed six people and injured another five in a Quebec mosque on Sunday. Click <a href="http://www.torontosun.com/2017/01/29/4-reported-dead-in-shooting-at-quebec-city-mosque">here</a> to know more.</p>

<p><a href="http://pm.gc.ca/eng/news/2017/01/29/statement-prime-minister-canada-fatal-shooting-city-quebec">Here</a> is the statement by the Prime Minister of Canada on Sunday.</p>

<pre><code>Diversity is our strength, and religious tolerance is a value that we, as Canadians, hold dear.
</code></pre>

<p>After Tuesday&#8217;s class, I found UBC faculties and students got together on the square and express their feelings and ideas about the event. Slogans such as &#8220;Hate is not the answer!&#8221; &#8220;LOVE&#8221; &#8220;Connection&#8221; were written on the posters. Several speakers were invited to give a public speech. More than one hundred audience circled around.</p>

<p>Well, these things were accidentally connected in my mind, which push me to think the goal of our education, the role of college in society, the beliefs behind our teaching practices.</p>

<h3>Wednesday</h3>

<p>On Wednesday, we visited the Richmond High School. Their students of grade 12 showed us around and introduced their school. Our college students also visited several classes and had a nice talk with their students.</p>

<h3>Thursday</h3>

<p>Teachers&#8217; professional development needs to be autonomous.<br/>
Teachers should make their classroom a more public place rather than a private place. Although new teacher may take their time to do so.</p>

<p>school system vs education agenda(教育系统与教育使命)</p>

<p>A history of my approach to teaching(Tony)</p>

<pre><code>As a beginning teacher. I believed in technical rationality.  
Graduate school. I encountered constructivism.  
More recently, I learned about complexity science  
</code></pre>

<p>Classroom as Complex systems: its not an entirely new idea!</p>

<p>Four theoretical principles of complex phenomena or system:<br/>
1 an emphasis on a non-linear frameworks(Davis, 2004)<br/>
2 cogintion is not simply representative of what we know but a continual bringing forth of what we know through the process of engagement(Capra,2002)<br/>
3 open system maintain themselves by being is a state of disquilibrium yet they remain stable nonetheless(Prigogne,1984)<br/>
4 spontaneous emergence of order from apparent random or unrelated events(2001)</p>

<p>What does your classroom look like？<br/>
* networks(peer, buddy, teacher, parents)<br/>
* self-regulation(negotiated curriculum)<br/>
* feedback loops(pairs, groups, whole class)<br/>
* disequilibrium(edge of chaos? generative)<br/>
* nested(student, class, program)</p>

<p>If a classroom or teaching and learning represent complex systems and if we fail to acknowledge them as such&#8230;.
&#8230;then we are probably failing to allow for, recognize, or take advantage of the emergence of complexity as it arise in our practice.</p>

<p>Five features of complexity that enhance the possibility of emergence<br/>
Internal redundancy - commonality &#8230;shared understantding<br/>
Internal diversity -variety &#8230; a rich pool of ideas<br/>
Neighborhood interactions  -engagement &#8230;ideas bumping up against one another<br/>
Decentralized control  -democratization &#8230; collective authoring<br/>
Enabling constraints  playing field &#8230;a generative space</p>

<p>Four implications for classroom:<br/>
1 surrendering certainty(open eye)<br/>
2 An emphasis on inquiry(the effort to articulate what we don&#8217;t know)<br/>
3 Acknowledge Complicity(迭代交互影响)<br/>
4 Allow for improvisation</p>

<p>Graduate life in UBC and how to apply for UBC</p>

<h3>Friday</h3>

<p>Presentation Report<br/>
Flash mob<br/>
Certificate ceremony<br/>
Feedback Survey<br/>
Pictures together and say Goodbye.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UBC Week 2: Gamification & SEL]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/01/ubc-week-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-01T19:44:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/01/ubc-week-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Monday:</h3>

<p>learning theory and the colorful pictures.<br/>
Gamification in education by Ms. Hu and Dr Boskic.</p>

<h3>Tuesday:</h3>

<p>Visit Cook Elementary School<br/>
This school is well organized to meet every students&#8217; learning need although it is not as rich as Norma Rose Point School.</p>

<h3>Wednesday:</h3>

<p>Meet Professor of UBC<br/>
UBC class visits</p>

<h3>Thursday:</h3>

<p>Tony wrote:</p>

<pre><code>I am not teaching you how to be a teacher  
but I am asking you think about being an educator in the world.(conception of teaching and learning; language to talk teaching &amp; learning; make sense of your practice as a teacher)  
</code></pre>

<p>Different perspectives：<br/>
1 Behaviorism(Behavior, Stimulus/Response)<br/>
2 Cognitivism(Symbols,making connections, schema)  <br/>
3 Constructivism(Elicit existing conceptions, personal construction)<br/>
4 Social Constructivism(Social interaction, mediation of knowledge)
5 Enactivisim(Embodied action, context is critical)<br/>
6 Complexity(dynamically adaptive phenomena, emergence)</p>

<p>Can you think of examples in your subject area</p>

<p>a test</p>

<p>Visit BC transition program class</p>

<h3>Friday:</h3>

<p>Social and Emotional learning<br/>
Tony let us watch the 2007 Spring Festival Live</p>

<p>The new BC curriculum<br/>
Understanding (big ideas)&#8211;Do (curricular competency learning standards) &#8211;Know (content learning standards)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What make a good teacher?]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/24/what-make-a-good-teacher/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-24T21:50:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/24/what-make-a-good-teacher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post will not be another list of good teacher characters. There are already many lists. Some come from serious studies. Some come from just personal experiences or judge(like <a href="http://cgi.stanford.edu/~dept-ctl/tomprof/posting.php?ID=665">this one highly</a> recommended). Some come from student or teacher self-reports(read <a href="https://www.unicef.org/teachers/teacher/teacher.htm">this student self-report</a>). Well these lists of qualities of good teachers help little in explaining how teachers become good teachers. What I want to do here is think about the most critical character that make a teacher becoming a good teacher.</p>

<p>The best answer (I can give for now) is being serious of their teaching job is the most important character in becoming a good teacher. Being serious means the teacher really care about students&#8217; learning in class and take enough efforts to make it better. The efforts include making the place, understanding students, building connections, organizing cognitive burdens, trying different ways or strategies, critical thinking and examine their own practices, keeping learning themselves, making meanings and so on. Well, maybe it is cheating answer because it nearly included all the characters in the lists. But how can teachers become better if they don&#8217;t care teaching at all.</p>

<p>The truth is that I care then I want to improve.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tony's tricks are not just tricks——week one summary]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/21/tonys-teaching-tricks/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-21T18:15:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/21/tonys-teaching-tricks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this lovely week, our students enjoyed Tony&#8217;s classes. WHY? Because Tony made it a lovely place to learn. HOW? In order to answer this question, I have to go back and inquiry Tony&#8217;s classes and teaching practices. I hope I can recognize not only Tony&#8217;s magic tricks but also his intentions behind. If I don&#8217;t write it down, the ideas may disappear and never come up to my mind again. So the FRIST goal of this post is a reflection and a record for myself.</p>

<p>It is a challenging job to decode a teacher&#8217;s class, especially Tony&#8217;s complicated, multicultural and bilingual class in with many educational goals, skills and strategies were embedded. Fortunately, Tony provided some clues. The clues were written on the whiteboard or explicitly said by Tony.</p>

<h3>Monday 16th Nov, Hot Water Welcome</h3>

<p>After we got in the door of Scarf building, we saw a welcome poster for our ECNU students in the corridor. It is not big, but well printed and mounted with a frame. The next day, It was put on the wall of our classroom. There were two hot water containers prepared for us. So nice! [MAKING THE PLACE]</p>

<p>The thing we did in the morning was self-introduction. Tony provided some useful scaffoldings, a map of China, pins with student names and numbers, umbrellas and format of introduction. When TAs and faculties came, they introduced themselves too.[CONNECTING THE PEOPLE]</p>

<p>In the afternoon, students went to corridor to look around their own pictures printed by Tony. The pictures were chosen by students. They stand for students&#8217; image of teaching or learning and also have special meaning for themselves. After they got back, they share a picture and the reasons why they choose it to share. Tony would welcome other students to make comments too. Then the picture owner reveal its meaning or story. [ENGAGING THE STUDENTS]</p>

<h3>Tuesday 17th Nov, Placed Based Learning</h3>

<p>Natalie introduced the place at different levels, Vancouver, BC, Canada, Turtle island, the Indigenous. Place based learning aim to make this change from I AM NO WHERE to I AM NOW HERE. Place represents layers of stories and it can included ecological education, bioregional education, critical pedagogy, experiential education, indigenous ways of knowing and being. Place based learning connects people and their places. It disrupts the idea of a one size fits all curriculum. Place is not about where we lived, buy rather about how we live where we live. Wisdom also sits in places. So our learning should not take place without a place.[PRESENT THE CONCEPTION]</p>

<p>Place based learning should answer three questions:</p>

<pre><code>WHAT IS WHERE  
WHY IS IT THERE  
WHY SHOULD I CARE  
</code></pre>

<p>Students explored the place around Scarf building in UBC. They must interview someone about the place and sit down some where in the building silently for 5 minutes to feel the place. Every group of 4 people needed to take 3 pictures and answer the three questions.[EXPLORE AND SHARE]</p>

<p>They explored many places excitedly and discovered many culture differences. The pictures were printed out and put on the wall to share. In this activity, pictures provided many learning opportunities:</p>

<pre><code>the pictures show interesting information and details  
the pictures generate questions  
the pictures have stories  
</code></pre>

<p>Natalie remind the students:</p>

<pre><code>Place making=build and construct while,  
place maker=every body make a part.   
Teachers are place maker.  
Forget place we forget how to make place.  
</code></pre>

<p>I think this [place based learning] was carefully selected for our students, because it help them to explore UBC, practice oral English and think about connections between people and places.</p>

<h3>Wednesday 19th Nov, School Visit</h3>

<p>let the children to be children</p>

<p>I wrote a post about <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school/">Norma Rose Point School</a>.</p>

<p>How Learning theories are different and alike?[fill tables]</p>

<h3>Thursday 19th Nov, Skits</h3>

<p>Task: In your group, you are to perform a short skit that illustrates an &#8220;image of schooling&#8221; drawn from your experience as either a primary, secondary, or post-secondary school student. The performance lasts 2 or 3 minutes.[ROLE PLAY]</p>

<p>How we can divide the groups?[TEACHER QUESTION]<br/>
Students&#8217; answers: by group numbers,by tables, by a game, pick card, color of clothes, by students&#8217; abilities and so on.</p>

<p>How much time do we need to prepare this skit?<br/>
Students&#8217; answers: 20 minutes; 30 minutes; 25 minutes.<br/>
Teacher: OK we choose the middle.<br/>
[Democratic the Classroom]</p>

<p>Teacher decides the activity but let students decide the time to prepare. To do so, students can have some ownership.</p>

<p>Go to the corridor and divide groups by taking off a shoe.[MAKE IT ANOTHER WAY]</p>

<pre><code>The only limit is your imagination.  
</code></pre>

<h3>Friday 20th NOV, TPI</h3>

<p>[check in]<br/>
Use check in to borrow students&#8217; ideas and questions as learning needs and learning opportunities.</p>

<p>[music as alarm]<br/>
When it is time for rest, turn on the music. When class begin, turn it off and student aware of that without a pain.</p>

<p>Group dividing strategies:<br/>
[Number the table and symbol the students]<br/>
Let students pull out the table number[Democratic the Classroom] and teacher draw the symbol like a game. This strategy can engage more students. Don&#8217;t&#8217; put back the table number if you don&#8217;t want one table answer twice.</p>

<p>[verbal curing]<br/>
LET students know the signal 30 seconds ahead before you give the signal.</p>

<p>Other cures:</p>

<pre><code>verbal cure  
eye contact  
visual sight  
audio sound  
</code></pre>

<p><a href="http://www.teachingperspectives.com/tpi/">Teaching Perspectives Inventory</a><br/>
Students already took the survey and sent them to Tony. Tony print them out and sent it back to students. Then Tony began to count the heads who were dominant in one perspective and write the results on board. Then he let one student read the text about one perspective and then everyone try to summary the paragraph by keywords or phrase.<br/>
Here is the result:</p>

<pre><code>TRANSMISSION 1  
    accuracy Anthony content knowledge
APPRENTICESHIP 7  
    skill norm practice
DEVELOPMENTAL 4  
    learner reasoning and thinking,make sense of something
NURTURING 23  
    safety heart support 
SOCIAL REFORM 3  
    change collective, deconstruction, who why interests
</code></pre>

<p>Tony let student write on a note what impress them most these days. Then let them post it up on the wall near their pictures.[MAKE A PLACE FOR STUDENTS to share]</p>

<p>Let us get back to the question that I asked. My best answer for now is that Tony made good social and emotional connections with our students by making a place where they feel good by his hands, heart and minds. It was not tricks at all!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticism is not critical thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-19T19:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Tony asked our students to make up a skit to show their image of schooling. This activity provide opportunities for students to speak English and express their ideas or images of schooling which may be the first step to realize and change their own teaching perspective.</p>

<p>During the activities, an interesting phenomenon showed up. Most of them criticized the education they had in China. While,it was true that the Chinese education had many problems. But, the thinking and reasoning of the problematic educational phenomenon is shallow, or not deep enough, in other word, critical thinking is missing.</p>

<p>In order to get more from this activity, students should not jump up to conclusion too quickly. They should not ignore the context that these things took place, the social context, the historical context, the economic context, the physical context, and so on. They should also rethink the theories and rationals behind their judgement and carefully examine the proof and logic. In short, critical thinking should take the place of criticism.</p>

<p>Why harsh criticism of people&#8217;s own education is not good even harmful? First, it easily leads to extreme and skin deep thinking which block more intellectual endeavor. Second, it hurt their self-image and self-confidence. Third, it can easily separate their connection with the previous themselves and places. Extreme criticisms call abandon or escape but not improvement and responsibility. Try to think of place-based learning, it heals the disconnection between people and places while harsh criticism do the opposite.</p>

<p>According to Daniel T. Willingham, critical thinking have three key features: effectiveness, novelty, and self-direction. Critical thinking is effective in that it avoids common pitfalls, such as seeing only one side of an issue, discounting new evidence that disconfirms your ideas, reasoning from passion rather than logic, failing to support statemnts with evidence, and so on.</p>

<p>Critical thinking is novel in that you don&#8217;t simply remember a solution or a situation that is similar enough to guide you. Using a complex algorithm to solve a math problem is not critical thinking. But devising a new algorithm is. Critical thinking is self-directed in that the thinker must be calling the shot(making desicions themselves): awards or punishment will disrupt instead of promote critical thinking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Norma Rose Point School]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T22:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have been in BC for 3days. Everything is new for our ECNU students, the beautiful campus of UBC, the long NO 44 bus, the comfortable Landmark hotel, the nice professors and staffs, the exciting learning activities.</p>

<p>Today is even special. We went to visit a middle school called <a href="http://go.vsb.bc.ca/schools/normarosepoint/Pages/default.aspx">Norma Rose Point School</a>. The school is not far from UBC, in fact it is the neighborhood of UBC. It took us about 20 or 30 minutes to walk there from Scarfe building where our classroom located. There are about six hundreds of students in the school, from kindergarten to grade 8, including both elementary and secondary education. This school is very unique because of its educational rationals and teaching building design.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/ROSE_Point_school.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>They believe learning should be integrated and take place in communities instead of separated and in classrooms of each discipline. They want to give student a whole picture of the world and want them to experience this by themselves in their learning communities. In this way, students get better understanding of who they are, where they come form, how they will change the world around them. They will also take more responsibility of their learning and be proactive to inquiry the world around them rather listen to the teacher and memorize for tests.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/global_issues.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Community_learning_outcome.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The learning schedule and activities are designed and carried out by a faculty team but not a single teacher as traditionally school usually do. The teacher love this kind of collaborative teaching, it also give teacher many opportunities to learn from each others. It is much easier for new teacher to join the team to teach together. As you can see, they value collaboration very much. Student collaborate with student, teachers and even parents. Teacher collaborate with colleges, parents, and university professors. Student who are good at something can teach others. Teacher can do the same thing. They are all super heroes at that time. Super hero is a learning activity designed by the 4th grade teacher team which engage students and let them rethink what a hero means.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/grade4_learning_schedual.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Many features of the school building reflect educational wisdom. They make a window to let student who play basketball to look downstairs and notice what is happening in the football playground. All the classrooms are open without a door but only three or two walls. It means guests are always welcome to join or observe the class. There are also lots of art crafts made by student to show their understanding of their school spirits.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/art_crafts.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/open_classroom.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>It is hard to believe such an ideal school can exist and survive. ARE there any disadvantages and challenges for this kind of school? Of course there are, but who can deny their bold spirit and unique learning place design. It is beautiful! That is enough for now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[迷失在城市生活里]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/03/lost-in-the-city/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-03T22:48:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/03/lost-in-the-city</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>现代人生活节奏越来越快，每个人都步履匆匆，打电话总说自己很忙，忙不过来，忙个没完没了。</p>

<p>这让我想起一个故事：</p>

<p>有一队人正在沙漠中举步维艰的前行，突然前面的队伍停了下来，首领很生气问为什么要停下来，来人回答说：我们走的太快了，要停下了等等被落在后面的灵魂。</p>

<p>这是一个物欲横流而缺乏反思的时代，而如果任凭自己卷入洪流就会面临迷失自我的风险。别人进城，我也进城，别人买房，我也买房，别人生娃，我也生娃，别人孩子上补习班，我也让孩子上补习班，总之千万别落后。</p>

<p>我是谁，我为什么要跟随，我来自哪，我要去哪里，这些人生大问题早已被紧张的城市生活所淹没。我不在是自己的我，我成了城市街道里的一个影子，不知道从哪里来，也不知道要到哪里去，忐忑而焦急，疲于奔命的紧跟着城市的节奏。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unpublished post]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/28/unpublished-post/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-28T11:10:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/28/unpublished-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>遗传与环境对学习的影响<br/>
科学教育的简化模型<br/>
neural network application OCR<br/>
我们缺少优秀的设计师<br/>
迷思概念再认识</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[超级个体]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/26/superman-in-the-life/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-26T10:20:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/26/superman-in-the-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>偶然的机会发现了罗辑思维这个脱口秀节目，觉得很值得有空车上听一听。比如古典的“超级个体”概念就很启发性，下面是摘录的笔记：</p>

<p>一、现在是个体崛起的时代</p>

<p>1、知识瘫痪的人<br/>
知识碎片不能转换成个体能力，眼高手低的人。</p>

<p>2、白日梦想家<br/>
只是画饼，但是不思考和行动的人。</p>

<p>3、安全自封的人<br/>
怕承担任何分享而固步自封的人</p>

<p>4、错误心智模式的人<br/>
从同行是冤家到同行是伙伴<br/>
从铁饭碗到超级个体<br/>
从巨婴到巨人<br/>
从三思而后行到边想边做<br/>
从知识瘫痪到独立思考和行动<br/>
从本职工作到业余工作</p>

<p>现代社会：不是智者生存，也不是强者生存，而是适者生存。</p>

<p>现代社会的变化：<br/>
1、用很少的生活资料，就能养活自己<br/>
2、组织的寿命变短，个人的寿命变长<br/>
3、职业在跨界，公司也在跨界，跨界成了新常态</p>

<p>未来是个体崛起的时代，每个人生产力更强，都有机会成为想成为的自己。永远不会失业的工作没有了，只要超级个体不会失业，但是要不断换工作。</p>

<p>二、你需要的3种超能力</p>

<p>1、自我迭代：一边奔跑一般思考</p>

<p>2、元能力：生产、连接、传播。</p>

<p>3、超级复原力：经得起失败，并从失败中积累经验。</p>

<p>三、成为超级个体的2种心法</p>

<p>1、乐高式的能力组合<br/>
郝景芳的《北京折叠》获得雨果奖。单一能力结构风险很大。X型、π型人才生态位更大。</p>

<p>2、给自己超链接的机会<br/>
给自己跨界的机会</p>

<p>四、你的世界观<br/>
你相信这个世界是善意的还是恶意的？<br/>
它决定了你的认知模式和行为模式。</p>

<p>五、现代人的关键竞争力<br/>
学习力（阅读、倾听、联系）<br/>
生产力（生产产品）<br/>
传播力（传播观念）<br/>
领导力（合作和引领他人）<br/>
行动力（切割、计划、行动、坚持）</p>

<p>而这5种力，都要在独立思考和实践中发展的。</p>

<p>听这个节目的话：点击这里。<br/>
古典：超级个体[罗辑思维]No·200【MP3<em>声音</em>录音】免费在线收听|下载-喜马拉雅fm<br/>
<a href="http://www.ximalaya.com/1412917/sound/27048773">http://www.ximalaya.com/1412917/sound/27048773</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[雾霾]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/22/smog/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-22T15:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/22/smog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>这不是一个新话题，但是却一直像幽灵一样挥之不去，影响人们的生活、健康，特别是心情。我担心它还会影响校园里孩子的身体健康，这是不可接受的，是红线。所以，现实强迫我们必须要认识雾霾、应对雾霾、治理雾霾。</p>

<p>一、认识雾霾<br/>
1、雾霾是什么？<br/>
雾霾，是雾和霾的组合词。雾霾常见于城市。中国不少地区将雾并入霾一起作为灾害性天气现象进行预警预报，统称为“雾霾天气”。<br/>
雾霾是特定气候条件与人类活动相互作用的结果。高密度人口的经济及社会活动排放大量细颗粒物（PM 2.5），一旦排放超过大气循环能力和承载度，细颗粒物浓度将持续积聚，此时如果受静稳天气等影响，极易出现大范围的雾霾。</p>

<p>气象学解释：<br/>
雾，是接近地面的空气因气温下降水蒸气凝结而成的悬浮的微小水滴；<br/>
霾，是大量极细微的干尘颗粒等均匀地浮游在空中，使水平能见度小于10千米的空气普遍浑浊现象，也称灰霾。<br/>
在气象学上，雾和霾的判识标准为：相对湿度小于80%时为霾；相对湿度大于90%时为雾；相对湿度在80%—90%之间时为雾和霾的混合物，其中雾和霾的程度要按照大气细颗粒物PM2.5和PM1.0（指空气动力学直径分别小于2.5和1.0微米的细颗粒）的浓度来判识。</p>

<p>值得指出的是，雾本来是一种自然现象，但是在污染导致大气细颗粒物增多的情况下，即使气象上判识为“雾”，也不再是完全的自然现象，而是有细颗粒物附着的微小水滴。</p>

<p>雾霾毒性大小，关键看携带的颗粒。颗粒如果是重金属就可能会导致重金属中毒，如果是致癌物质就会提升患癌症的概率。</p>

<p>摘自：http://tech.sina.com.cn/d/v/2015-12-10/doc-ifxmpnqf9456114.shtml</p>

<p>2、雾霾是如何形成的？<br/>
从PM2.5来源看，雾霾主要是人类活动造成的。不是天灾，是人祸。<br/>
PM2.5的来源可分为一次源（直接排放）和二次源（二次生成）。</p>

<p>一次源又可分为自然排放源和人为排放源。其中，自然排放源包括风扬尘土、火山灰、森林火灾、海浪飞沫、生物来源等。人为排放源包括工业粉尘、机动车尾气颗粒物、道路扬尘、建筑施工扬尘、厨房烟气等。</p>

<p>二次生成是指排放到大气中的气态污染物通过多种化学物理过程产生的二次细颗粒物。人类活动排放的大量气态污染物如二氧化硫SO2、氮氧化物NOx、氨气NH3、挥发性有机污染物（VOCs）等，都能在大气中被氧化产生硫酸盐、硝酸盐、铵盐和二次有机气溶胶（SOA）。这些新生成的细颗粒物是大气中PM2.5的重要来源。全球范围内，二次颗粒物贡献率在20%—80%之间，在我国中东部地区常常高达60%，在成霾时往往二次颗粒物所占比例更高。</p>

<p>也就是说，人类活动产生的二次颗粒物占比更高！从这个意义上说，雾霾主要是人类活动造成的。</p>

<p>3、雾霾的危害有哪些？<br/>
危害人体健康，特别是呼吸器官。</p>

<p>妨碍交通出行，提升安全隐患。</p>

<p>4、关于雾霾的谣言？<br/>
谣言一：只要戴口罩就能防雾霾？<br/>
谣言二： 空气净化器可以有效净化雾霾，家中必备？<br/>
谣言三：防雾霾中医药方、多吃蔬菜能防雾霾？<br/>
谣言四：雾霾是“核雾染”？<br/>
答案： 点击<a href="http://tech.sina.com.cn/d/v/2015-12-10/doc-ifxmpnqf9456114.shtml">这里</a>。</p>

<p>二、防护雾霾<br/>
1、户外活动如何防护？</p>

<p>2、室内活动如何防护？</p>

<p>3、如何调节个人活动达到防护的目的？</p>

<p>三、治理雾霾：从个体到社会，从科学到艺术，从产品到市场。<br/>
1、个人选择：从环保意识到生活习惯。<br/>
2、商业经济：如何让雾霾有利可图？<br/>
3、公共政策：让谁来买单？<br/>
4、产品研发：从口罩到空气净化机的设计。<br/>
5、科研工程：谁来把雾霾吹走？<br/>
6、文化艺术：神曲，还是神曲，没有话剧？</p>

<p><a href="http://www.iqiyi.com/w_19rrclfe59.html">雾霾版《卷珠帘》</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.iqiyi.com/w_19rrclbxvt.html">大雾版：北京北京</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ahtv.cn/swf/?video=293668">小品《雾霾！走开！》</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tinbergens_four_questions]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/11/18/tinbergens-four-questions/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-18T23:01:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/11/18/tinbergens-four-questions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>鸟为什么下蛋？<br/>
Why bird lay egg?<br/>
机制问题：蛋壳如何起到保护作用？<br/>
Mechanistic explanations for how an organism&#8217;s structures work.<br/>
发育问题：蛋壳是如何形成的？<br/>
Developmental explanations for changes in individuals, from DNA to their current form.<br/>
功能问题：蛋壳薄厚合适对鸟类有怎样的意义？<br/>
A species trait that solves a reproductive or survival problem in the current environment.<br/>
进化问题：蛋壳的厚度恰好合适是如何进化来的？<br/>
The history of the evolution of sequential changes in a species over many generations.</p>

<p>HOW?<br/>
以静态的观点问HOW，是机制问题<br/>
以动态的观点问HOW，是发育问题</p>

<p>WHY?<br/>
以静态的观点问WHY，是功能问题<br/>
以动态的观点为WHY，是进化问题</p>

<p>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinbergen%27s_four_questions</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Word必须要打开两次才能打开]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/11/17/word-have-to-open-twice/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-17T19:21:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/11/17/word-have-to-open-twice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>我的系统是win7，有一个问题一直困扰着我，就是每次打开word文档的时候总是第一次失败，第二次正常。</p>

<p>今天网上找到一个方法，就是把默认输入法从搜狗输入法改成中文简体美式键盘。</p>

<p>在用不用打开两次那么麻烦了。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[魔镜魔镜告诉我：什么知识最重要？]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/07/20/mirror-mirror-on-the-wall/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-20T22:11:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/07/20/mirror-mirror-on-the-wall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>魔镜魔镜告诉我，什么知识最重要？</p>

<p>拉丁文吗？科学吗？经典著作吗？文化要素吗？关于如何学习的知识吗？问题解决能力吗？核心素养吗？创造力吗？STEM吗？……</p>

<p>这个世界变化太快，生活变化太快，我们真的能教给学生足以应对未来挑战的东西吗？假如这个东西是存在的？那么它是什么？它是不变的还是变化的？如果它是不变的，那么它如何帮助学生应对从未有过的新挑战？如果它是变化的，那么寻求不变的传承或者最核心的知识、技能是否就要落空？对于这个不断变化的东西，我们怎么掌握它变化的规律，怎么去描述它，怎么在教学实践中实现它，让学生经过有限时间的培养长出它的果。</p>

<p>当下，核心素养成为一个红得发烫的标签，就好像以前提的素质教育，还有人人都说的“以学生为中心”的口号，以最快的速度在媒体、报纸、学术杂志泛滥开来。其实之所以有这样的提法，跟我们的时代背景密切相关。现在时信息时代，信息爆炸，知识也跟着泛滥，我们突然意识到，不可能把所有有用的知识、技能都传承下去，那么至少传承最重要的，最有用的，最核心的，核心素养就在这样的背景中粉墨登场的。其实这不是一个新问题，但是人么确实是史无前例的感觉到了这个问题的迫切性，进而试图用核心素养来解决这个难题。</p>

<p>当然，一个标签是解决不了任何问题的，所以我们要弄清楚核心素养的内涵。21世纪核心技能包括：学习与创新技能、生活与职业技能、信息媒体与技术技能。OECD则要测查世界不同地区15岁青少年是否为未来生活做好了准备，并将科学素养定位为反思性公民参与公共科学相关议题讨论和实际问题解决的能力。在其测评中，以科学地诠释现象、设计和评价科学探究、科学地阐释资料和证据三个维度测评青少年的科学素养。再有就是流行的4Cs，交流-合作-批判性思考-创造(Communication, Collaboration, Critical thinking and Creativity)。就这些组织和机构提供的答案来看，核心素养并不是一个有明确内涵的统一概念，它实际上是培养目标的一种抽象而笼统的表达。这样一来，这个标签的内涵自然是变化的，而且不同国家、不同时期其相应的内涵也会有差异。所以提核心素养，就是再提培养目标，当然它与全面发展有些小矛盾，因为全面发展更理想化，而在有限时间和资源条件下，提核心素养可能更实际，但是同时我们也要注意不要把不该削减的削减了，那就真的把核给扔了，变成无心素养了。</p>

<p>我们找不到问题的答案，有时是因为思维方法不对，有时却因为问题本身就有问题。</p>

<h3>教学是不是一种知识传承？教学是不是只是一种知识传承？</h3>

<p>教学过程中必然有知识传承，但是期望这种传承直接帮助学生应对外来挑战，那是太乐观了。</p>

<p>教学肯定不仅仅是一种知识传承，实际上它是一种师生合作再造、再发现，学生的学习成果一方面是已有的知识和技能，另一方面是学生和教师合作过程中生成性成长。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Atlas and NGSS]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/07/09/atlas-and-ngss/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-09T23:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/07/09/atlas-and-ngss</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>概念进程图：<br/>
比如关于科学性质的认知进程图：<br/>
Science Literacy Maps: The Nature of Science
http://strandmaps.dls.ucar.edu/?chapter=SMS-CHP-0857</p>

<p>美国下一代科学课程标准：<br/>
NGSS Search the Standards | Next Generation Science Standards
http://nextgenscience.org/search-standards</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教学主线小组讨论]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/05/18/coherent-content-storyline-discussion/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-18T17:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/05/18/coherent-content-storyline-discussion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天和上外附中小组就小学内容分析进行了小组讨论，感觉还挺有效果的。讨论的形式是，先分小组自选主题进行教学内容要点梳理，然后每个小组派一位代表把要点写在黑板上。之后，每位同学就如何落实这些要点，如何把这些要点串联起来，如何进行恰当的收和放进行讨论。</p>

<p>讨论过程也会涉及到选择怎样的教学素材，怎样处理和使用才能把素材用足用好展开。</p>

<p>每个案例面临的问题都不一样，有的内容多，老师面临的是在有限的时间内如果只选取重难点加以落实。</p>

<p>有的案例内容少，老师面临的是如何将学习深化，如何引导学生进行深入的思考。</p>

<p>还涉及到如何选取素材，哪些素材适合从头到尾使用，哪些素材适合用在某个环节上。</p>

<p>如何将内容串起来，如何把问题线索理清楚，如何从头到尾一线而贯之。</p>

<p>同学们问哪里能找到高中前科学概念的梳理，我希望以后我们自己总结和梳理一个。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
