<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-01T11:03:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yellow dragon]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/01/yellow-dragon/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T11:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/01/yellow-dragon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yellow dragon<br/>
Yellow zoo<br/>
Happy dancing<br/>
Happy pool</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pick the right test]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/30/pick-the-right-test/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-30T14:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/30/pick-the-right-test</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You have to pick a test to analysis your data. The question is which test is the right one. Well, it depends on your data and your hypothesis. Usually there are lot of choices, but only one solves your problem best.</p>

<p>Here are some suggestions for selecting test by the types of your variables.<br/>
Dependent and Independent Variables<br/>
Dependent Variable(DV) is what you are care of. Independent Variable(IV) is what you think may affect your dependent variable. Usually you can control your independent variable, but not depedent variable.</p>

<p>There are two basic types of variables:<br/>
Continuous Variables(e.g. height,temprature)<br/>
Discrete Variables(e.g. age, size, preferences)</p>

<p>if IV=[0,1],DV=[~] then T test<br/>
if IV=[0,1,2,],DV=[~] then one-way Anova or ANOCVA<br/>
if IV1=[0,1,2,], IV2=[0,1,2,], DV=[~] then General linear model<br/>
if IV1=[~], IV2[~],&#8230;, DV=[~], then Linear Regression &amp; Pearson<br/>
if IV=[0,1,&#8230;], DV=[0,1,&#8230;] then χ2<br/>
if IV=[~], DV=[0,1,&#8230;] then Logistic regression</p>

<p>For more details look at the following pictures:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/choiceoftest.png" alt="Choices of Test" /><br/>
This picture comes from : <a href="http://www.socr.ucla.edu/Applets.dir/ChoiceOfTest.html">SOCR: Statistics Online Computational Resource</a></p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a href="http://www.unesco.org/webworld/idams/advguide/Chapt1_3.htm">Types of Variables</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.socr.ucla.edu/Applets.dir/ChoiceOfTest.html">SOCR: Choice of Test</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multidimensional Scaling in R]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/29/mds-in-r/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T22:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/29/mds-in-r</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I met this problem when I was analysing teachers&#8217; PCK concept maps. I wanted to divide them into several clusters that shared the similar structures(nodes and links).</p>

<p>One approch is plotting them in a 2d picture to see if there is any patterns. But before that, you have to do the Muultidimensional Scaling to get your (x,y) from your Distance Matrix.</p>

<p>Distance Matrix<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/distance-matrix.png" alt="Distance Matrix" /></p>

<pre><code>
# 1) MDS 'cmdscale'
dm <- read.table("distance-matrix.txt")
mds1 = cmdscale(dm, k = 2)

# plot
plot(mds1[,1], mds1[,2], type = "n", xlab = "", ylab = "", axes = FALSE, main = "cmdscale (stats)")
text(mds1[,1], mds1[,2], labels(x)[[1]], cex = 0.9, xpd = TRUE)
</code></pre>


<p>This the x y data I got:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/xy-data-mds.png" alt="Distance Matrix" /></p>

<p>You got this picture after plotting it out.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/plot-mds.png" alt="Distance Matrix" /></p>

<p>Reference:<br/>
<a href="http://gastonsanchez.com/blog/how-to/2013/01/23/MDS-in-R.html">7 Functions to do Metric Multidimensional Scaling in R | Gaston Sanchez</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Questions need to address in a research paper]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/28/questions-need-to-address-in-a-research-paper/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-28T18:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/28/questions-need-to-address-in-a-research-paper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A sample division for 40 pages paper.<br/>
2 Introduction<br/>
5-6 Literature<br/>
2 Theory/conceptual frameworks<br/>
6-10 Methods<br/>
4-12 Findings<br/>
10 Discussion conclusion Implication</p>

<p>(1)Introduction</p>

<pre><code>* what is known  
* what is unknown  
* Your burning Hypothesis, question, aim(Approach, plan of attack, proposed solution(a little bit),your experimental approach,why your study fills the gap  
</code></pre>

<p>tips for introduction</p>

<pre><code>* Keep short  
* for general audience: clear, concise, non-technical  
* take the reader step by step form what is know to what is unknown. end with your specific question  
* Emphasize how your study fills in the gaps(the unknown)  
* Summarize at a high level! Leave detailed descriptions, speculations, and criticism of studies in discussion  
</code></pre>

<p>Keep in minds:</p>

<pre><code>* it is not a literature review  
* catch attention  
* making the case  
</code></pre>

<p>(2)Literature review</p>

<pre><code>* comprehension  
* synthesis  
* critical  
* write the most important citations that stand your study out  
* anything in discussion should be here, no new paper add in discussion  
* one paragraph summary your review  
</code></pre>

<p>notes: if there is no directly related literature, you can close area to draw on, or standards, government policy</p>

<p>(3)Theoretical/ Conceptual Frameworks</p>

<pre><code>* help to analysis the data and approach the questions  
* theory -position/approach  
* conceptual model  
* theory drawing the studies
</code></pre>

<p>(4)Methods</p>

<pre><code>* Participants  
* Context  
* Data collections  
* Data analysis  
* Methodological theory  
* Reliability and validity  
* enough information for other people to repeat  
</code></pre>

<p>(5)Results<br/>
Tables and figures<br/>
Summarize not read table for reader<br/>
Highlight the result, Not only positive results but also negative<br/>
complement the information that is already in tables and figures<br/>
give precise values in the figure or the percentage change<br/>
don&#8217;t forget to talk about the negative and control results<br/>
Reserve the term &#8220;significant&#8221; for statistically significant<br/>
reserve information about what you did for the methods section<br/>
do not discuss the rationale for statistical analyses within the results section<br/>
Reserve comments on the meaning of your results for the discussion section<br/>
Just tell what the data show not what your data mean</p>

<p>Use the past tense for completed actions: we found , women were, men smoked ,was<br/>
Use the present tense for assertions that continue to be true<br/>
figure 1 show ,  finds confirm the data suggests</p>

<pre><code>* Synthesis the important not all  
* Show the results to match the questions  
* select the most powerful and significant  
* do not repeat the tables and figures  
</code></pre>

<p>(6)Discussion<br/>
Answer the question you asked<br/>
Support your conclusion(your data, others&#8217; data)<br/>
Defend your conclusion(anticipate criticisms)<br/>
Give the &#8220;big-picture&#8221; take-home message<br/>
Connect your theory framework and review<br/>
how your work add on</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[不要才能要]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/24/what-to-do/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T10:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/24/what-to-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>不要封闭要开放，不要暴力要协商；<br/>
不要愤世要救世，不要人治要法治。</p>

<p>不要封锁要透明，不要口号要践行；<br/>
不要污染要发展，不要禁言要多元。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go the big pool forget the small one]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/21/go-the-big-pool-forget-the-small-one/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-21T12:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/21/go-the-big-pool-forget-the-small-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so amazing to swim in the big pool; You are just like a fish swimming in the ocean. The water is clear; you can see everything in the water. It also takes less effor swimming in a big pool; you swim faster and faster with passion. Forget the small pool, come to this one.</p>

<p>It usually opens from 11 AM to 1 PM during weekdays. Enjoy it and have fun!</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/uga-swimming-pool.png" alt="UGA Swimming Pool" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[我只想找一口水喝]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/20/poem-i-want-water/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-20T11:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/20/poem-i-want-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>
我只想找一口水喝
我一路疾驰
只想找一口水喝
扑灭腹中的烟火

我来到从前的小河
她已经干涸
连榕树爷爷也失去了踪影
只留下七零八落的脚踝
散落在角落里
哭干了所有的眼泪

河床里是一具尸首
早已经腐烂
散发着恶的臭
还有苍蝇的轰鸣

我又焦急的奔向湖岸
一心想喝那甘甜的湖水
湖面寂静
泛着死一样的绿
还有一片一片的鱼肚白在飘荡
没了往日的喧嚣
也没了往日伙伴们排队时的争吵

我喝了个痛快
这油亮的湖水
带着异样的满足
不为别的
我只想找一口水喝
找一口水喝
扑灭我腹中的烟火

可，可…
可这烟火却越烧越旺
连我的视线也开始燃烧起来
越痛苦、越挣扎
越挣扎、越痛苦
也不知到过了多少时间
我终于挣脱了
天空是那么的蓝
眼前是一团洁白
在风的轻抚下安睡

榕树爷爷拉着我的手
还有那村边的小河
咕咕的欢迎着我的归来
这是我的家
我再也不愿意离开
再也不愿意离开
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing paper for publication]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-14T10:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing is an very important skill as speaking. It aims to send message, from people to people, from generation to generation, from country to country. One of the most efficient way to do this is publishing in good journals. Nowadays, publication has become a crucial part of resume or CV, and people write papers not just for sending messages but also seeking for promotions. So good universities ask faculties for good papers; good researchers look for good journals to publish. Good journals want good impactors or indexes. Good researchers tend to cite more good papers from good journals. But can this system help sending necessary message to those in-need audiences? It may not necessarily be the case. It is just a game of numbers dominated by the for-profit companies and ambitious universities who care little what the content really mean.</p>

<p>Complain is enough. We still have to write anyway. But I believe we are writing for our audiences not for universities or journal companies. We write because we have the impulse to share. As a beginning researcher, I&#8217;d like to co-write with partners at first. I can learn easier and faster by observing the writing process and talking to them about it. So I would also recommend you co-write with somebody at first.</p>

<p>Although you may not like the game, it is still good to know the rules and the tools. Here are some useful resources for writhing educational journals:</p>

<p>I found writhing is both hard and complicated. It is like a hedgehog rolls itself as a ball; you can hardly approach anyhow. First it is hard because it is hard. Especially if you don&#8217;t write often, it takes time to develop your own writing skills. Second, it is complex and complicated. Writhing a paper may include many small jobs: reading, citing, linking, analyzing, reasoning, revising, formatting, managing. It will remain hard unless you cut the job into small pieces that you can play with; Cutting tasks is a crucial managing skill.</p>

<h3>Writing tips:</h3>

<pre><code>* Write down your thoughts while you read.  
* Write it down when it come up to you.  
* Write timely before the deadline.  
* Write summary periodically.  
* Write, and then shut down disturbs.  
* Write with your ear, your mouth, and anything that helps.  
* Write briefly and clear; Every word tell.  
* Write as yourself and to be yourself.  
* Write as you are talking to a friend about your new discovery(emotion)  
</code></pre>

<h3>Writing steps:</h3>

<pre><code>1  abstract, title, journal  
2  results, logic, 5pages  
3  enrich each paragraph and link together  
4  revise and formatting  
</code></pre>

<h3>What make a paragraph good</h3>

<p>Focus on one idea<br/>
Format paragraph<br/>
  -Topic sentence<br/>
  -explanation evidence logic<br/>
-not too long: 3 sentences<br/>
-Concluding/Beginning sentence<br/>
-Paragraph work together<br/>
-unity(pronoun, sense, tongue)</p>

<h3>What make good sentence</h3>

<p>-no cluster, brief, clear, concise every word tell<br/>
-use strong verb<br/>
-make it colorful</p>

<h3>The hard thing:</h3>

<p>When you are wrting,it is hard to make the right decisions:<br/>
when to quit (something you don&#8217;t want to do now);<br/>
when to search for help (something necessary but you can&#8217;t do yourself);<br/>
when to just do the job no matter you like it or not.</p>

<h3>Writing tools:</h3>

<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/">Google Drive</a> can help you co-write online.<br/>
<a href="http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</a> can help you manage your references.<br/>
<a href="http://interest.science.thomsonreuters.com/forms/HistCite/">HisCite</a> can make graph to let you know how paper cited each other.<br/>
<a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/analytics/spss/">SPSS</a> can help you analyze the data.<br/>
<a href="http://latex-project.org/intro.html">LaTeX</a> is a good document preparation system especially useful when you have lots of equations and graphs(generated with R).<br/>
There are lots of other text editors such as Miscro-soft Word, EditPlus for consider.</p>

<h3>Useful books:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Publication-Manual-American-Psychological-Association-ebook/dp/B00CPUBEBM">Publication Manual by APA</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.apastyle.org/">APA Style website</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Writing-Well-30th-Anniversary-Edition/dp/0060891548">On Writing Well</a> by Zinsser</p>

<h3>Journal Rankings Search:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.scimagojr.com/journalrank.php?area=0&amp;category=3304&amp;country=all&amp;year=2012&amp;order=sjr&amp;min=0&amp;min_type=cd">Journal Rankings on Education</a><br/>
<a href="http://admin-apps.webofknowledge.com/JCR/JCR?RQ=HOME">Web of Science JCR-WebSearch Engine</a></p>

<h3>Journals and their impactors(2012 JCR Social Science Edition):</h3>

<p>REVIEW OF EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH 4.2<br/>
LEARNING AND INSTRUCTION 3.3<br/>
Journal of the Learning Sciences 3.0<br/>
COMPUTERS &amp; EDUCATION 2.7</p>

<p>JOURNAL OF RESEARCH IN SCIENCE TEACHING 2.5<br/>
<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1002/%28ISSN%291098-237X">SCIENCE EDUCATION 2.4</a> <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1002/%28ISSN%291098-237X/homepage/ForAuthors.html">for-authors</a><br/>
<a href="http://jte.sagepub.com/">Journal of Teacher Education 1.6</a> <a href="http://www.sagepub.com/journals/Journal200961/manuscriptSubmission">for-authors</a><br/>
JOURNAL OF COMPUTER ASSISTED LEARNING 1.6<br/>
<a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?show=aimsScope&amp;journalCode=tsed20#.U3QKWCggtes">INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.3</a> <a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/action/authorSubmission?journalCode=tsed20&amp;page=instructions#.U3QLWiggtes">for-authors</a></p>

<p>British Journal of Educational Technology 1.3<br/>
TEACHING AND TEACHER EDUCATION 1.2<br/>
RESEARCH IN SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.1</p>

<h3>NARST Proposal Review Rubric</h3>

<p>(from <a href="http://www.narst.org/">NARST website</a>)</p>

<pre><code>
For each category, three criteria are required. Given the constraints of the 5-page limit  
for proposals, please assign a numerical rating using the following descriptors as a guide:
5 Highly evident: Proposal provides clear, substantive, and coherent evidence of all criteria
4 Evident: Proposal adequately describes all criteria in the category.
3 Mostly evident: Proposal adequately describes 2 out of 3 criteria in the category
2 Somewhat evident: Proposal adequately describes 1 out of 3 criteria in the category
1 Not evident Proposal does not adequately describe any of the criteria in the category
Subject/Problem
1. Is there a clear focus for the study?
2. Does the proposal include a clear rationale for the study?
3. Does the proposal describe the model, theoretical framework, or philosophy of the study?
Design or Procedure
Empirical Studies
1. Does the proposal clearly describe the methodology (theory of method)?
2. Does the proposal clearly describe the research methods, design, and study context?
3. Are the methodology, procedure, and design appropriate for the study?
Non-Empirical Studies (e.g., conceptual or position papers, reviews of literature)
1. Does the proposal clearly describe the approach used to develop the argument or conduct the review?
2. Are the ideological/philosophical positions of the author and sources made clear?
3. Does the proposal include an appropriate range of literature?
Analyses and Findings
Empirical Studies
1. Do the data analyses appear to be appropriate, coherent, and complete?
2. Are the arguments or interpretations supported by the data?
3. Does the proposal discuss alternative interpretations, bias, reliability, or validity as appropriate?
Non-Empirical Studies (e.g., conceptual or position papers, reviews of literature)
1. Do the syntheses of ideas appear to be appropriate, coherent, and complete?
2. Are the arguments or interpretations supported by evidence?
3. Does the proposal discuss alternative interpretations, counter-arguments, or bias, as appropriate?
Contribution
1. Do the conclusions add to, refine, or refute the oretical constructs?
2. Do conclusions contribute valuable insights into teaching/learning/researching science education?
3. Does the proposal clearly describe implications for teaching/learning/researching science education?
Cohesiveness*(Related Paper-Sets ONLY)
1. Are all of the papers in the set focused on a similar concept/theme?
2. Do all papers contribute new information to the set, making a meaningful strongly-related whole?
3. Are all papers of high enough quality to be accepted individually?
General Interest
1. Does the content of the presentation promise to be of general interest to NARST members?
2. Is the content presented in a way that will be meaningful to NARST members?
3. Does the paper promise to be of interest to the education community at large?
Overall Rating
(1-not recommended; 5 highly recommended)  
</code></pre>


<h3>Basic Paper Structure(ITDFD)</h3>

<pre><code>
Title
Author
Abstract
Keywords

Introduction
  Background
  Literature
Theoretical Framework 
  Theoretical foundation
  Research questions
Design/Procedure
  Participants
  Instrument & Procedure
  Reliability & Validity
Findings
  Tables & Figures
Discussion
  Findings review
  Conclusions
  Implications

Acknowledgements
References
</pre>


<p></code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[夏日中的两个女孩]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/09/two-girls-as-passers-by/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T17:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/09/two-girls-as-passers-by</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>星期三，5月7号，下午三点钟，我从AD楼出来，去赶公交车。这是学期的最后一天，HSC校车明天就要停开了。未来的相当一段时间里，我只有做City巴士度日了。一出门，下了台阶，太阳就火辣辣照了上来，转眼望去，一个女孩拖着一个大箱子向AD楼走来。我估量箱子很沉，她拖箱子时很费力气。望了一眼这两段陡峭的台阶，估计她要进楼很难拖得上去。她身材高挑，黑头发，黄皮肤，戴着墨镜，俨然是个亚洲人，于是我主动用英文问她是否需要帮助。她说ok，然后就把大箱子一把丢给了我，自己空着手，看着我。这也有点出乎我的意料，我本想是两个人一起把箱子抬上去，结果她要我一个人来做这个事了。唉，谁让我答应帮忙，好吧，于是我就开始费力地把这个大箱子往上面拖。拖到了中间，她问我是不是中国人，我说是？她回了一句，台湾人。第一次我没有听清楚，她又重复道，我是台湾人。我哦了一下，终于把箱子拖上去了。我看了她一眼，她没什么表示，没有用英语也没有用中文，说一声谢谢，我只好走了，她就一个人拖着箱子往门里面拽，弹簧门却故意捣乱似的卡住大箱子好几次，我本想再去帮她，但还是收住了脚步。</p>

<p>我很是好奇，她为什么不说她自己的名字，而是说台湾人。她先问我是不是中国人，我说我是中国人，但她却直接回了一句“我是台湾人”。于是，关于她我唯一了解的信息就是“她是台湾人”，一个有点骄傲的台湾人。</p>

<p>其实我的室友也是台湾人，是个男的，但是也并不像这个女孩那样。</p>

<p>我终于等到了巴士，上了车，坐到佐治亚中心换乘HSC校车。太阳还是那么毒辣，让人有个地缝都想钻进去。不巧的是等公交车的地方一棵树也没有，不过马路对面有几棵高一点的树，于是有一小块阴凉投影到我们这一边，我不自觉地钻进这小块阴凉里，为了不晒到头只好蹲下。有一个美国女孩儿，肤色略黑，也觉得太阳太难抵挡，也凑了过来。于是我们闲聊起来。我问她在等哪辆公交汽车，原来，我们等的是同一辆公交车。过去了一辆FH之后，我们的HSC就来了。上了车，我们又继续聊了一会儿，原来她是来自于美国北部的一个州，哪里的气候非常干燥，她说她花了一段时间才能适应这里湿热的气候。我说从干燥的地方到湿润的地方还是比较好适应，如果反过去就难了！我跟她讲我原来住在干燥的中国北方，但是现在工作在湿热的南方，有跟她同样的亲身体验。之后她向我介绍了她的姓名，在快要到HSC的时候她下了车，原来她不住在HSC，而是住在附近的小区里。她礼貌的跟我打了一个招呼，说很高兴见到我，我说我也是。之后她就下车了。</p>

<p>这两个女孩给我的印象极深，虽然她们的名字我已经忘了（在车上交谈时，我就说过我总忘却名字）。第一个女孩显得更时髦一些，第二个女孩儿则显得更朴实。但是，我觉得最大的不同在于她们对别人的看法以及与人交流的方式。</p>

<p>我并不是说所有的台湾人都这样，我只是一个观察点而已。但是我也至少知道了，有些台湾人多少可能会对大陆的中国人有别样的看法，甚至对帮助过她们的大陆人，也同样保留着成见。</p>

<p>有成见并不可怕，可怕的是不知道自己有成见，可怕的是不能放下成见进行平等的对话。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[中国环境危机地图]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/06/china-environmental-risk-maps/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T15:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/06/china-environmental-risk-maps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>中国癌症村地图 <a href="https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?msa=0&amp;msid=104340755978441088496.000469611a28a0d8a22dd&amp;dg=feature">China Cancer Villages Map - Google Maps</a></p>

<p>中国血铅污染地图 <a href="https://maps.google.com.hk/maps/ms?ie=UTF8&amp;brcurrent=3,0x3403e2eda332980f:0xf08ab3badbeac97c,0&amp;oe=UTF8&amp;msa=0&amp;msid=104340755978441088496.000489e60c3649d260e18&amp;dg=feature">China Blood Lead Poisoning Map</a></p>

<p>中国污染地图 <a href="https://ditu.google.com/maps/ms?msa=0&amp;msid=118244671891871382452.0004763f27eca98ca1be8&amp;dg=feature">China Pollution Map - Google Maps</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ipe.org.cn/pollution/index.aspx">公众环境研究中心-中国水污染地图</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Chinese say maybe and but]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/04/why-chinese-say-maybe-and-but/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-04T10:52:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/04/why-chinese-say-maybe-and-but</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I watched a TED recently that Sarah Jones(a actress) played the role of 11 people from different cultures to response to random questions asked by TED audiences.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/YlmZkY1uqXM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>I was impressed by the Chinese American woman she played who always repeat &#8220;BUT&#8221; and &#8220;Maybe&#8221;. It heard like a typical Chinese speaker. I began to think why Chinese people tend to say these two words again and again. One reason is that they are not good at express themselves. The second reason might be they are not confident; they feel insecurity. She said that at least the food should not be poison. As you know, food, sex and sacurity are the basic needs of human according to Maslow&#8217;s hierarchy of needs.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Maslow-needs.png" alt="Maslow's hierarchy of needs" /> <br/>
Why Chinese people are lack of sacurity. Well, it is a long story. To make it brief&#8212;it is becuase poisonous food, polluted air and water, dominated culture and so on. A survey report that many rich people in China want to imgrant to other country such as US, Canada. Some Corrupt officials want to have orther country&#8217;s identity because they want to escape from the punishment. There also a lot of people want to go US, becuase they worry about the nature and social environment, they worry about the education and healthy of their children.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lost in local extrema]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T11:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love this place, the library at the second floor in Aderhold Building. I love this table, which is not too big but just enough. This love can guide me back home.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/simple-desk.png" alt="simple desk" /></p>

<p>I lost myself sometimes in some very narrow area. People may ignore the whole when they are attracted and trapped by them. It can be power, It can be sex, It can also be anger and violence.</p>

<p>A picture comes to my mind when I am thinking of these dangerous Local Extrema&#8212;the local extrema. I frist notice this phenomenion in NG&#8217;s machine learning class. This is the picture that he used to show local extrema. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/local-extrema.png" alt="local extrema" /></p>

<p>When the computer only have one seed, it is very likely trapped in a local extrema and return a wrong answer. It is just like a person who lost himself when he try to reach the extrema unrealized that it is only the local extrema.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[how to use R]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/21/how-to-use-r/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T23:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/21/how-to-use-r</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>
##week2
a <- 1:10
b <- c(1,3,4,5,8,9,11,14,15,18)
cbind(a,b) #
rbind(a,b) #
length(a) #
class(a)
as.character()
as.logical()
as.numeric()
m <- matrix(a,nrow=2,ncol=5)
dim(m) #[1] 2 5
attributes(m) $dim [1] 2 5
m <- 1:10
dim(m) < c(2,5) #
f <- factor("yes","no","yes","yes")
table(f) # yes 3 no 1
x <- c()
x <- c(x,1)
mean() #求平均值
cor(a,b) #求相关系数
is.na()
is.nan()
read.table() #读取txt表格
read.csv() #读取csv文件

names()
x[!is.na(x)] # 去除缺失的数据
data <- data.frame(id=1:10,height=170:180)
data["id"] #返回局部data.frame
data["id"][!is.na(data["height"])] #返回height无缺失的id
data[[id]] #返回vector
paste("00","1",".csv",sep="") # 001.csv
paste(a,collapse="")
for (i in 1:length(id)){
    s <- as.character(id[i])
    spre <- paste(rep("0",3-nchar(s)),collapse="") # use collapse join vector
    fn <- paste(directory,"/",spre,s,".csv",sep="") # use sep to join string
    data <- read.csv(fn)
}

if(length(x)>0){print(x)}else{}

##Week3
x <- list(a=1:5,b=rnorm(10))
lapply(x,mean)#$a[1] 3  $b[1] 0.03937816
如果x不是一个list,那么它将被自动转换成list,相当于使用as.list()函数
x <- list(a=matrix(1:4,2,2),b=matrix(1:6,3,2))
lapply(x,function(elt)elt[,1]) #$a[1] 1 2  $b[1] 1 2 3
sapply(x,mean) #会自动简化结果，返回一个vector或者matrix，不能简化返回list
x <- matrix(rnorm(200),20,10)
apply(x,2,mean) #返回10列的均值
apply(x,1,sum) #返回每行的总和共20个
a <- array(rnorm(2*2*10),c(2,2,10)) #三维数组
apply(a,c(1,2),mean)
          [,1]      [,2]
[1,] 0.1888774 0.5517366
[2,] 0.2667046 0.2412767

str() #Compactly Display the Structure of an Arbitrary R Object
str(tapply)
> x <- c(rnorm(10),runif(10),rnorm(10,1))
> f <-gl(3,10) #生成标签 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3
> tapply(x,f,mean) #具有相同标签的数值的平均值
with(mtcars, tapply(mpg, cyl, mean))# mtcars is a data.frame with cyl and mpg

> split(x,f) #利用标签将list进行拆分
> s <- split(airdata, airdata$Month)
> lapply(s,function(x) colMeans(x[,c("Ozone","Solar.R","Wind")]))
split(x,list(f1,f2),drop=TRUE) # empty levels can be dropped

> mapply(rep,1:4,4:1)
[[1]]
[1] 1 1 1 1

[[2]]
[1] 2 2 2

[[3]]
[1] 3 3

[[4]]
[1] 4

traceback() # print out where error occurs,else do nothing
debug() # step through one line at a time
browser() #suspend the execution wherever called and put it in debug mode
trace() # insert debug code in specific place

#Play with the iris data
library(datasets)
data(iris)

#Play with $
> x <- makeCacheMatrix()
> x
$set
function (y) 
{
    x <<- y
    inv <<- NULL
}

$get
function () 
x

$setinverse
function (inverse) 
inv <<- inverse

$getinverse
function () 
inv

> x$set(matrix(rnorm(9),3,3))
> x$get()

> x$set(a)
> x$get()
            [,1]      [,2]       [,3]
[1,] -0.50184759 -0.751659 -2.1276852
[2,]  0.37466264 -1.448643  1.1807655
[3,] -0.06093845  0.740338 -0.8508723
> cacheSolve(x)
           [,1]       [,2]       [,3]
[1,] -0.4668678  2.8847043  5.1705844
[2,] -0.3214999 -0.3872940  0.2664879
[3,] -0.2462983 -0.5435808 -1.3137063

#week4
str(str)# see the structure of a object
m <- matrix(rnorm(100),10,10)
str(m)
str(lm)
str(ls)
x <- rnorm(100,2,4)
summary(x)
str(x)

#作图
hist(rnorm(1000,2,4))
hist(BMI, breaks=20, main="Breaks=20")
hist(BMI, breaks=seq(17,32,by=3), main="Breaks is vector of breakpoints")
seq(0, 1, length.out = 10) #在一定范围产生制定数目的序列
plot(x,y)

#拟合
> set.seed(20)  #进而可以再次产生同样的随机数 方便别人重复模拟
> x <- rnorm(100)
> e <-rnorm(100,0,2)
> y <- 0.5+2*x+e
> sumary(y)

#评估运算时间 user time（cpu 时间消耗）elipsed time(流逝壁钟时间)
> system.time(readLines("http://www.jhsph.edu"))

#就
make.Negloglik <- function(data, fixed=c(FALSE,FALSE)){
    params<- fixed
    function(p){
        params[!fixed] <- p
        mu <- params[1]
        sigma <- params[2]
        a <- -0.5*length(data)*log(2*pi*sigma^2)
        b <- -0.5*sum((data-mu)^2)/(sigma^2)
        -(a+b)
    }
}
set.seed(1)
normals <- rnorm(100,1,2)
nLL <- make.Negloglik(normals)
optim(c(mu=0,sigma=1),nLL)$par

> # Fixing sigma=2
> nLL <- make.Negloglik(normals,c(FALSE,2))
> optimize(nLL,c(-1,3))$minimum
[1] 1.217775
> optimize(nLL,c(-1,2))$minimum
[1] 1.217775
> #Fixing u=1
> nLL <- make.Negloglik(normals,c(1,FALSE))
> optimize(nLL,c(1e-6,10))$minimum
[1] 1.800596
> nLL <- make.Negloglik(normals,c(1,FALSE))
> x <- seq(1.7,1.9,len=100)
> y <- sapply(x,nLL)
> plot (x,exp(-(y-min(y))),type="l")
> nLL <- make.Negloglik(normals,c(FALSE,2))
> x <- seq(0.5,1.5,len=100)
> y <-sapply(x,nLL)
> plot(x,exp(-(y-min(y))),type="l")


Assignment 3
#在R中有的时候表达方式是不一样的，比如
引用某个变量的子变量用
time$year #而不是time.year

表示数组相乘用 
%*%

判断是否包含 
"a" %in% c("a","b","c")

使用R的时候我自己经常犯的错误
该使用[]的时候错误的使用了（），特别是在操作data.frame的时候
该使用[[]]错误的使用了[]，前者可以变为向量，后者还是data.frame
忘记了使用%%进行

如何使用Order
> (ii <- order(x <- c(1,1,3:1,1:4,3), y <- c(9,9:1), z <- c(2,1:9)))
 [1]  6  5  2  1  7  4 10  8  3  9
 > rbind(x, y, z)[,ii] # shows the reordering (ties via 2nd & 3rd arg)
  [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4] [,5] [,6] [,7] [,8] [,9] [,10]
x    1    1    1    1    2    2    3    3    3     4
y    5    6    9    9    4    7    1    3    8     2
z    5    4    1    2    6    3    9    7    2     8


</code></pre>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[不同发电机的原理]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/19/how-to-generate-electricity/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T17:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/19/how-to-generate-electricity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>原电池发电（化学能转化为电能）<br/>
以铜锌原电池为例，其中锌电极发生的电极反应式是：<br/>
锌片 Zn－2e-=Zn2+ （氧化反应）
锌离子进入溶液，使得溶液里的正电荷过多；同时锌失去的电子沿导线经电流计流入铜片，使溶液里原有的氢离子在铜电极上被还原成氢原子，这样溶液中多余的正电荷就被中和；氢原子又结合成氢分子并放出。铜电极发生的电极反应式是：<br/>
铜片 2H++2e-=H2↑ （还原反应）
由于在锌、铜两个电极上不断发生的氧化还原反应，使化学能转变为电能。锌片是给出电子的一极，是电池的负极，铜片是电子流入的一极，是电池的正极。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/primary-cell.png" alt="Primary Cell" /></p>

<p>动力发电（水力、火力、风力、核能、太阳能蒸汽发电）<br/>
其原理是利用动力推动线圈切割磁感应线发电。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/firepower.gif" alt="Fire Power" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/waterpower.gif" alt="Water Power" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/nuclearpower.gif" alt="Nuclear Power" /></p>

<p>热电机<br/>
其原理是热电效应，即不同的金属导体（或半导体）具有不同的自由电子密度，当两种不同的金属导体相互接触时，在接触面上的电子就会扩散以消除电子密度的差异。而电子的扩散速率与接触区的温度成正比，所以只要维持两金属间的温差，就能使电子持续扩散，在两块金属的另两个端点形成稳定的电压。由此产生的电压通常每开尔文温差只有几微伏。如能适当设计和组合就可以产生工作电压。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/seebeck_effect.png" alt="Seebeck Effect" /></p>

<p>太阳能发电<br/>
其原理主要依赖于光电效应。<br/>
太阳光照在半导体p-n结上，形成新的空穴-电子对，在p-n结电场的作用下，光生空穴流向p区，光生电子流向n区，接通电路后就形成电流。这就是光电效应太阳能电池的工作原理。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/solar_cell.png" alt="Solar Cell " /></p>

<p>原电池反应_百度百科: http://baike.baidu.com/view/159629.htm<br/>
各种发电方式：http://vm.nthu.edu.tw/science/shows/nue/various.html<br/>
热电效应 - 维基百科：http://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E7%86%B1%E9%9B%BB%E6%95%88%E6%87%89<br/>
Solar cell - Wikipedia：http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_cell</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chinese Puzzle Pot design]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/19/chinese-puzzle-pot-design/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T14:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/19/chinese-puzzle-pot-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is an interesting class called Intro to the design of everything <a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/viewer#!/c-design101/l-300162902/e-441839145/m-438038764">link here</a></p>

<p>They showed a pot that can put in water by a hole at the bottom, and no water come out. It works well.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/chinese-puzzle-pot-photo.png" alt="Chinese puzzle pot photo" /></p>

<p>The following is one possible inner structure design in my mind.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/chinese-puzzle-pot-design.png" alt="Chinese puzzle pot design" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Repeated Measures Correlation Mixed Model]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/17/repeated-measures-correlation-mixed-model/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-17T09:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/17/repeated-measures-correlation-mixed-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How to do it?<br/>
Analysis==>Mixed Model, then you got diaogue 1 as follows. ID shuold be put be included as subjects. Year should be included as repeated, cause I measured multiple times by different year.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/mixed-model-d1.png" alt="Mixed Model Dialouge 1" /><br/>
The most hard decision to make is which Repeated Covaricance Type to select, there are a lot of choices, the most used ones are:<br/>
1. Unstructured: you have no idea of the correlation of repeated measures, SPSS we estimate all the correlation independantly (r12,r13,r23,r14,r24,r34).<br/>
2. Scaled Identity: no correlations at all, r=0.<br/>
3. Compound Symmetry: all correlations equals r.<br/>
4. AR1: (r, r<sup>2,</sup> R<sup>3)<br/></sup>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/mixed-model-AR1.png" alt="Auto Regression 1" /><br/>
5. Toeplitz:(a,a,a,b,b,c)<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/mixed-model-toepliztz.png" alt="Toeplitz" /><br/>
6. Another choice is &#8220;diagonal&#8221; which assumes no correlation between the random effects.</p>

<p>Then you determing the fixed effect variable:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/mixed-model-d2.png" alt="Mixed Model Dialouge 2" /></p>

<p>And the random effect variable:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/mixed-model-d3.png" alt="Mixed Model Dialouge 3" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ecojustice work]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/15/ecojustice-work/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-15T20:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/15/ecojustice-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>share a film clip that portrays an environemntal meassage<br/>
美丽的大脚</p>

<p>photo essay</p>

<p>sustainability share-a-thon</p>

<p>book study</p>

<p>nature principle presentation</p>

<p>memory banking<br/>
pick a community practice and interview some people who participate in this practice to grow your knowledge about this practice. I selected foot ball as both comercial and community practice. I wrote a post about foot ball.</p>

<p>Citizen Science<br/>
Citizen science (also known as crowd science, crowd-sourced science, civic science, or networked science) is scientific research conducted, in whole or in part, by amateur or nonprofessional scientists, often by crowdsourcing and crowdfunding. Formally, citizen science has been defined as &#8220;the systematic collection and analysis of data; development of technology; testing of natural phenomena; and the dissemination of these activities by researchers on a primarily avocational basis&#8221;.[1] Citizen science is sometimes called &#8220;public participation in scientific research.&#8221;[2]<br/>
[1] &#8220;Finalizing a Definition of &#8220;Citizen Science&#8221; and &#8220;Citizen Scientists&#8221;&#8220;. OpenScientist. 2011-09-03. Retrieved 2012-10-11.<br/>
[2] Hand, E. (2010). &#8220;Citizen science: People power&#8221;. Nature 466 (7307): 685–687. doi:10.1038/466685a. PMID 20686547<br/>
from: wikipedia</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[多次重测数据的方差分析]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/14/repeated-measures-anova/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T13:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/14/repeated-measures-anova</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>统计学比较抽象，需要通过例子加以学习。</p>

<p>比如第一型错误（Type I error）和第二型错误（Type II error）。比如验证一个人的智商是否超常（极高或者极低），我们知道95%人群的智商在70-130之间，一般成正态分布。我们会做出一个零假设H0，假定某人的智商是正常的。然后用某种评估方法测量一个人的智商结果是145，超出正常范围，这样我们就否定零假设，认为该人智商是超常的。</p>

<p>但是我们的评估方法不一定准确，所以不可避免的会犯错误。第一型错误是，该人智商属于正常范围（接受H0），但是的统计评测显示的却是超常（拒绝H0）。第二型错误是，该人智商明明超常（拒绝H0），结果我们统计评测显示该人智商正常（接受H0）。简单说也就是假阳性和假阴性，或者假检出和假包含。</p>

<p>分析数据就像是在森林里寻宝，每次进入森林都很不容易，需要花很多时间，非常容易迷失方向，面对无数的表格和无数的可能分析方法不知所措。而且好不容要到的路径，下次再想用却忘记了，需要花费很多实践才能再次找到。于是很多人做了很多无用的功，就是在原地打转。为了避免这样的情形发生，分析数据时一定要写分析记录和报告，否则即便是文件夹里有无数的报表，也忘记当初这个报表是干什么的了。</p>

<p>如何使用SPSS绘制重复测量的误差条图？答案是可以使用SPSS的graph builder，不过我在用的过程中发现一个很低级的错误。我搜索到了一个视频教程<a href="http://vimeo.com/49231146">Create a clustered bar or line chart of means for repeated measures data (with optional error bars) on Vimeo</a>。其实原理很简单，就是把多个变量同时拉到纵轴。但是我拉的时候，系统却不容许，也不报错。晕。后来发现，原来这些变量必须是scale类型，而不能是normal。全部粘贴覆盖为scale之后，问题解决。不提示为什么不能拖拽，这是SPSS设计上的缺陷。其实类似的问题还有，当你使用Multiple Imputation(MI)处理缺失数据的时候，如果变量类型不是scale，SPSS也会拒绝执行MI，这也是在网上查了才解决的。因此，在使用SPSS的时候一定要小心的变量类型，尽量最开始就设好。</p>

<p>下面进入正题，如何进行重复测量的方差检验。其实如何做并不难，难的是如何解释Spss产生的一大推报表，并选择有用的信息进行报告。首先这样的检测一般可以分为两类：One Way Anova以及Two-way Anova。前者是单因素实验设计，后者是双因素实验设计（如V1（2）× V2（3）交叉设计，共有6组）。两者的区别以后再解释。</p>

<p>此外还有组间变量（比如不同的处理、教学方法、培训类型）和协变量（性别、教育程度）等。</p>

<p>这种统计方法往往可以让你检测是否存在交叉效应。</p>

<p>在报告的时候，SPSS同时给你multivariate test和Univariate test的结果。到底报告那个呢？取决于Mauchly&#8217;s Test of Sphericity，如果sig&lt;0.05那么，说明球度（sphericity）假设不成立，那么就要看修正后的Univerite test的结果。Spss提供多个修正结果，根据Epsilon-Greenhouse-Geisser的值是否大于0.75进行不同的选择，如果大于则选择Huynh-Feldt修正的结果，否则则选Greenhouse结果。<br/>
另外就是如何报告F检验的结果。通常报告的格式如下F(自由度，误差自由度)=F值，p=sig，n=total。这些值在哪里呢？看下图。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/f-test-report.png" alt="F test report" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NARST 2014 Pittsburgh]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/07/narst-2014-pit/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-07T17:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/07/narst-2014-pit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST) is a worldwide organization of professionals committed to the improvement of science teaching and learning through research. More about NARST click <a href="https://www.narst.org/about/mission.cfm">here</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/narst.png" alt="NARST" /></p>

<p>The 2014 Annual meeting is hold in Pittsburgh from March 30 to April 2. The theme of this meeting is &#8220;AWAKENING DIALOGUES — Advancing Science Education Research Practices and Policies&#8221;. I attended this conference and presented a paper with my advisor. There were more than one thousand of participants from more than 25 countries. And many many presentations and posters were going on at the same time. Fortunately I bought the conference program book which contain maps and all related information. Although I did take my laptop with me, but actually I found that the book helped me a lot especially on finding a place and planing for where to go in order to listen to special presentations.</p>

<p>There were 13 sessions in total. I attended 10 sessions and plus 1 session in which I presented our study on teacher perception. I arrived at Sunday afternoon and missed 2 sessions. But after that, I managed to took all the left sessions. So you can imagine how busy I was at that time when going from one room to another room. I thought we could not attend the committee meeting but in fact Dr Jackson told me we were allowed to do that as long as we were interested. Next time I would like to have a try. It was really a pity that I forgot to take a picture with my advisor. In fact I just took a lot of pictures of other researchers&#8217; slides but did not take any picture of myself. Instead, my advisor took some pictures for me when I was introducing our study. During the last session, a presenter asked the audiences(only 3 people including me because most had left) to took a picture with her. This was the only picture that I took with others in my first NARST conferences. Next time I don&#8217;t want such a harry anymore. I will try to take my time to enjoy the next conference rather than keep running all the time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[由读书的姿势想到的]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/03/22/the-gesture-of-reading/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-22T22:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/03/22/the-gesture-of-reading</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>古代的读书很有趣，一个人或坐或立，一边读书，一边摇头晃脑。电视剧里是这样演的，估计过去的读书人还真是这样的。（有待考证）</p>

<p>我在想，为什么他们倾向于这样读书呢？有的人说他们陶醉了，但是小孩子也是这样的，也许他们只是模仿吧了。我觉得没有这么简单。</p>

<p>我查了一下，在百度知道里找到这样的答案：
古人为什么要摇头读书：
反映了古人很早就有了保健意识呀。
第一，读书的确很辛苦，摇头可以解除疲劳
第二，摇头可以促进血液循环，增长记忆力呢。
第三, 古人的读的书就是我们现在所谓的文言文，古文是讲究韵律和节奏的。所以读书时摇头晃脑可以增强节奏感，使自己更加全身心的投入其中。 这里的“读”其实是指“吟”，更接近于“唱”，是有音节、音韵的，摇头是为了配合音调、节奏的
此外，古人读书也是表演，摇头晃脑可以丰富自己的动作和表情，以致于增加美感
来自：http://zhidao.baidu.com/question/69442869.html?qbl=relate_question_0</p>

<p>我觉得其中的为了增加节奏感进而便于吟诵是一个很好理由。比如在《诗·大序》这样写道：“诗者，志之所之也。在心为志，发言为诗，情动于中而形于言。言之不足，故嗟叹之。嗟叹之不足，故咏歌之。咏歌之不足，不知手之舞之足之蹈之也。”</p>

<p>果然想必是因为再读韵文而歌咏之了。</p>

<p>但是我觉得这样的读法没准还真有助于健康。比如摇晃颈椎，可以增加大脑供血，增强记忆力，避免长期伏案而得颈椎病，另外也可以避免长期静坐而对胸椎和腰椎的伤害。再有，据说从圣先贤、帝王将相、大师名家到普通的读书人，几乎都没有近视眼的。（待考）看一眼，然后读一句，然后摇晃一番四处瞅瞅，也学还真能预防近视。</p>

<p>那么既然这样的读书方式这样有趣，是否可以演变为现代的读书和使用电脑的方式呢。。我觉可以尝试，但是不一定全部照搬。比如现代的电脑病越发广泛，我就深受其害。近视是初中的时候造成的。现在刚刚三十出头，胸椎由于长期使用电脑姿势不当而经常疼痛。也许设计电脑输入的时候应该把这些问题考虑进去，比如有人研究发现，钢琴键盘熟练之后输入的输入速度会比现在的键盘更快，也许也会更舒服。有的时候我们经常会陷入一些思维定势，比如读书一定是要静坐而读。用电脑也一定是静坐而用电脑，为什么不能动呢，其实没什么科学依据说不能动。其实反而是动一动有好处，但是如何动确实需要进一步的研究。</p>

<p>我举得在这样的键盘设计、以及读书姿势的设计上大有可为。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
