<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: activity | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/activity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-08-28T08:22:45+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demonstration of barometric pressure using a bottle of water]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T19:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Oliver gave us an assignment to design a demonstration of science teaching. I already had several ideas. One was show them <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/">The surprising trees</a>. Another one was rolling a paper roll. The last one was the bottle water activity.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bottle-water-demonstration.png" alt="bottle water demonstration" /><br/>
Today, when I was on the road home after swimming. I couldn't stop thinking a more neat idea and keep revising the activity. I was very tired because of swimming but my thinking keep running in my head, even on bed with windows closed and curtain down. I imagined what the scene would be like, what to say, what to do, in what order, what questions to ask. I even came up with a little poem and dialogue:</p>

<pre><code>Needle needle hot
Let the water jet out
Jet out, jet out
Oh my God
Nothing happen

Wait a minute, let me check out...
Hymn
Why
Maybe we need the hole more lower
Let me make another hole

Hymn
Maybe the we can lay down the bottle
Hymn
Let me think, drawing the hole of water on blackboard,talk to myself

Maybe we can make both the holes open
Maybe we can check out in the up-stand position
Why?
Why in this position it work
In this position it doesn't work
Did you see that?
So when will the water come out? 
One open hole or two? In which position? In which hole does the water come out?
How do you explain this?
Why one hole doesn't work?
Why two holes on the same height also doesn't work?
Why the two holes need to be on different height?
</code></pre>

<p>Finally, the design finished and the thinking stopped. This is the reason why I don't write at night. Thinking will not let me sleep.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
