<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: comments | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/comments/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-29T06:59:22+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elegy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/08/26/elegy/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T22:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/08/26/elegy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Elegy翻译为挽歌，是一部2008年的电影。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/elegy.jpg" alt="Elegy" />
Human is a kind of social animal that can not live alone. If he does live alone, he will die. When he interact with others, he thrive.</p>

<p>In this sense, human being is like a neuron and the society is the neutral network.</p>

<p>Once I believe that I can think, but when I think carefully I can not thinking independently. For example, if live me alone in dark room I can think little.</p>

<p>As matter of fact, people do not think, they just reflect or interact with the environment. This truth is hard to believe, but it is important to know if you really want to beat it.</p>

<p>A philosopher said that there are two kind of people in the world, those who divide things into two kinds and those do not. I don't totally know what the philosopher want to say, but the philosopher must be the former.</p>

<p>There is old saying in China, when the flower bloom pick it, do not wait it shrivel. There is a god time keeper, he just counts and when he stop you die.</p>

<p>When the time come, you will regret the stupid time you spend but nothing can change. It is really a tragedy. Tragedy teach you the lesson.</p>

<p>In front of the god time keeper, you have to be honest to seek what you want because you have the only one chance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
