<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: 翻译 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/翻译/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-30T12:04:51+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Myths about learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/30/myths-about-learning/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-30T11:45:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/30/myths-about-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Myths About Learning<br/>
关于学习的认识误区</p>

<p>Will Rogers once said, “It isn’t what people don’t know that hurts them. It’s what they do know that just ain’t so.” All of us – teachers, parents, and students – retain outdated ideas about learning that are based largely on our previous experiences in school. Modern brain science has helped steer us in the right direction.<br/>
Will Rogers曾经说过：造成伤害的不是哪些人们不了解的东西，而恰恰是他们自认为知道但却错误的东西。我们所有人，教师、家长还有学生，还留着基于学校经验的过时了的学习观。现代脑科学已经帮助我们转向正确的方向。</p>

<p>Here are a few of the biggest myths:<br/>
下面是一些最大的认识误区：</p>

<p>Basic Facts Come Before Deep Learning<br/>
This one translates roughly as, “Students must do the boring stuff before they can do the interesting stuff.” Or, “Students must memorize before they can be allowed to think.” In truth, students are most likely to achieve long-term mastery of basic facts in the context of engaging, student-directed learning.<br/>
基本的概念一定要先于深度学习<br/>
这句话，翻译过来就是“学生必须做无聊的事情，然后才能做有趣的事情。” 或者“学生必须记忆，然后才能思考。”实际上，在吸引人的、自我主导的学习情境中，学生才最容易达成对基本事实的真正掌握。</p>

<p>Rigorous Education Means a Teacher Talking<br/>
Teachers have knowledge to impart, but durable learning is more likely when students talk, create, and integrate knowledge into meaningful projects. The art of a teacher is to construct ways for students to discover.<br/>
严格的教育意味着教师讲授<br/>
教师有知识需要传授，当是实际上，只有当学生交谈、创造和在项目中应用知识的时候，持久的学习才更可能发生。</p>

<p>Covering It Means Teaching It<br/>
Teachers are often seduced by the idea that if they talk about a concept in class, they have taught it. At best, students get tentative ideas that will be quickly forgotten if not reinforced by a student-centered activity.<br/>
讲了就等于教了<br/>
教师经常会被这样的想法误导，如果他们在课上讲了一个概念，他们就已经教过了。而实际上，学生最多只是获得一些初步的想法，而且它们很快会被忘掉如果不通过学生为中心的活动加以巩固。</p>

<p>Teaching to Student Interests Means Dumbing It Down<br/>
If we could somehow see inside a student’s brain, its circuitry would correspond to its knowledge. Since new learning always builds on what is already in the brain, teachers must relate classroom teaching to what students already know. Teachers who fail to do so, whether due to ignorance or in pursuit of a false idea of rigor, are running afoul of a biological reality.<br/>
依据学生的兴趣教学以为着降低要求<br/>
假如一个人能看到一个学生的大脑内部的话，它的环路会对知识做出反应。因为新的学习永远需要建立在电脑已有的基础之上，教师必须将课堂教学与学生已知相关联。如果教师不能做到这点，无论是源于无知又或者对所谓严谨的错误认识，都只是在刁难一个生命存在。</p>

<p>Acceleration Means Rigor<br/>
Some schools accelerate strong students so that they can cover more material. ICG schools are more likely to ask such students to delve deeper into important topics. Deep knowledge lays a stronger foundation for later learning.<br/>
加速就意味着严格<br/>
有些学校加快好生的学习进度，这样他们可以学习更多的内容。独立课程团队学校会更多的让学生在重要主题上深入钻研。深层知识回味他们已有的学习奠定坚实的基础。</p>

<p>A Quiet Classroom Means Good Learning<br/>
Students sitting quietly may simply be zoned out, if not immediately, then within 15 minutes. A loud classroom, if properly controlled, included the voices of many students who are actively engaged.<br/>
安静的课堂意味着良好的学习<br/>
学生静静的坐着可能只是在走神，及时不是马上，15分钟后也会。一个嘈杂的课堂，如果在适当的控制下，实际上是包含了更多积极参与的学生声音。</p>

<p>Traditional Schooling Prepares Students for Life<br/>
Listening to teachers and studying for tests has little to do with life in the world of work. People in the work world create, manage, evaluate, communicate, and collaborate, like students in ICG schools.<br/>
传统的学校教育让学生为生活做准备<br/>
听教师讲课和为考试而学习与现实工作和生活实际上毫无关联。在现实世界，人们创造、管理、评判、交流、合作，就像独立课程学校的学生一样。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
