<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 教学 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/教学/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-29T09:55:19+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What make a good teacher?]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/24/what-make-a-good-teacher/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-24T21:50:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/24/what-make-a-good-teacher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post will not be another list of good teacher characters. There are already many lists. Some come from serious studies. Some come from just personal experiences or judge(like <a href="http://cgi.stanford.edu/~dept-ctl/tomprof/posting.php?ID=665">this one highly</a> recommended). Some come from student or teacher self-reports(read <a href="https://www.unicef.org/teachers/teacher/teacher.htm">this student self-report</a>). Well these lists of qualities of good teachers help little in explaining how teachers become good teachers. What I want to do here is think about the most critical character that make a teacher becoming a good teacher.</p>

<p>The best answer (I can give for now) is being serious of their teaching job is the most important character in becoming a good teacher. Being serious means the teacher really care about students' learning in class and take enough efforts to make it better. The efforts include making the place, understanding students, building connections, organizing cognitive burdens, trying different ways or strategies, critical thinking and examine their own practices, keeping learning themselves, making meanings and so on. Well, maybe it is cheating answer because it nearly included all the characters in the lists. But how can teachers become better if they don't care teaching at all.</p>

<p>The truth is that I care then I want to improve.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tony's tricks are not just tricks——week one summary]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/21/tonys-teaching-tricks/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-21T18:15:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/21/tonys-teaching-tricks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this lovely week, our students enjoyed Tony's classes. WHY? Because Tony made it a lovely place to learn. HOW? In order to answer this question, I have to go back and inquiry Tony's classes and teaching practices. I hope I can recognize not only Tony's magic tricks but also his intentions behind. If I don't write it down, the ideas may disappear and never come up to my mind again. So the FRIST goal of this post is a reflection and a record for myself.</p>

<p>It is a challenging job to decode a teacher's class, especially Tony's complicated, multicultural and bilingual class in with many educational goals, skills and strategies were embedded. Fortunately, Tony provided some clues. The clues were written on the whiteboard or explicitly said by Tony.</p>

<h3>Monday 16th Nov, Hot Water Welcome</h3>

<p>After we got in the door of Scarf building, we saw a welcome poster for our ECNU students in the corridor. It is not big, but well printed and mounted with a frame. The next day, It was put on the wall of our classroom. There were two hot water containers prepared for us. So nice! [MAKING THE PLACE]</p>

<p>The thing we did in the morning was self-introduction. Tony provided some useful scaffoldings, a map of China, pins with student names and numbers, umbrellas and format of introduction. When TAs and faculties came, they introduced themselves too.[CONNECTING THE PEOPLE]</p>

<p>In the afternoon, students went to corridor to look around their own pictures printed by Tony. The pictures were chosen by students. They stand for students' image of teaching or learning and also have special meaning for themselves. After they got back, they share a picture and the reasons why they choose it to share. Tony would welcome other students to make comments too. Then the picture owner reveal its meaning or story. [ENGAGING THE STUDENTS]</p>

<h3>Tuesday 17th Nov, Placed Based Learning</h3>

<p>Natalie introduced the place at different levels, Vancouver, BC, Canada, Turtle island, the Indigenous. Place based learning aim to make this change from I AM NO WHERE to I AM NOW HERE. Place represents layers of stories and it can included ecological education, bioregional education, critical pedagogy, experiential education, indigenous ways of knowing and being. Place based learning connects people and their places. It disrupts the idea of a one size fits all curriculum. Place is not about where we lived, buy rather about how we live where we live. Wisdom also sits in places. So our learning should not take place without a place.[PRESENT THE CONCEPTION]</p>

<p>Place based learning should answer three questions:</p>

<pre><code>WHAT IS WHERE  
WHY IS IT THERE  
WHY SHOULD I CARE  
</code></pre>

<p>Students explored the place around Scarf building in UBC. They must interview someone about the place and sit down some where in the building silently for 5 minutes to feel the place. Every group of 4 people needed to take 3 pictures and answer the three questions.[EXPLORE AND SHARE]</p>

<p>They explored many places excitedly and discovered many culture differences. The pictures were printed out and put on the wall to share. In this activity, pictures provided many learning opportunities:</p>

<pre><code>the pictures show interesting information and details  
the pictures generate questions  
the pictures have stories  
</code></pre>

<p>Natalie remind the students:</p>

<pre><code>Place making=build and construct while,  
place maker=every body make a part.   
Teachers are place maker.  
Forget place we forget how to make place.  
</code></pre>

<p>I think this [place based learning] was carefully selected for our students, because it help them to explore UBC, practice oral English and think about connections between people and places.</p>

<h3>Wednesday 19th Nov, School Visit</h3>

<p>let the children to be children</p>

<p>I wrote a post about <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school/">Norma Rose Point School</a>.</p>

<p>How Learning theories are different and alike?[fill tables]</p>

<h3>Thursday 19th Nov, Skits</h3>

<p>Task: In your group, you are to perform a short skit that illustrates an "image of schooling" drawn from your experience as either a primary, secondary, or post-secondary school student. The performance lasts 2 or 3 minutes.[ROLE PLAY]</p>

<p>How we can divide the groups?[TEACHER QUESTION]<br/>
Students' answers: by group numbers,by tables, by a game, pick card, color of clothes, by students' abilities and so on.</p>

<p>How much time do we need to prepare this skit?<br/>
Students' answers: 20 minutes; 30 minutes; 25 minutes.<br/>
Teacher: OK we choose the middle.<br/>
[Democratic the Classroom]</p>

<p>Teacher decides the activity but let students decide the time to prepare. To do so, students can have some ownership.</p>

<p>Go to the corridor and divide groups by taking off a shoe.[MAKE IT ANOTHER WAY]</p>

<pre><code>The only limit is your imagination.  
</code></pre>

<h3>Friday 20th NOV, TPI</h3>

<p>[check in]<br/>
Use check in to borrow students' ideas and questions as learning needs and learning opportunities.</p>

<p>[music as alarm]<br/>
When it is time for rest, turn on the music. When class begin, turn it off and student aware of that without a pain.</p>

<p>Group dividing strategies:<br/>
[Number the table and symbol the students]<br/>
Let students pull out the table number[Democratic the Classroom] and teacher draw the symbol like a game. This strategy can engage more students. Don't' put back the table number if you don't want one table answer twice.</p>

<p>[verbal curing]<br/>
LET students know the signal 30 seconds ahead before you give the signal.</p>

<p>Other cures:</p>

<pre><code>verbal cure  
eye contact  
visual sight  
audio sound  
</code></pre>

<p><a href="http://www.teachingperspectives.com/tpi/">Teaching Perspectives Inventory</a><br/>
Students already took the survey and sent them to Tony. Tony print them out and sent it back to students. Then Tony began to count the heads who were dominant in one perspective and write the results on board. Then he let one student read the text about one perspective and then everyone try to summary the paragraph by keywords or phrase.<br/>
Here is the result:</p>

<pre><code>TRANSMISSION 1  
    accuracy Anthony content knowledge
APPRENTICESHIP 7  
    skill norm practice
DEVELOPMENTAL 4  
    learner reasoning and thinking,make sense of something
NURTURING 23  
    safety heart support 
SOCIAL REFORM 3  
    change collective, deconstruction, who why interests
</code></pre>

<p>Tony let student write on a note what impress them most these days. Then let them post it up on the wall near their pictures.[MAKE A PLACE FOR STUDENTS to share]</p>

<p>Let us get back to the question that I asked. My best answer for now is that Tony made good social and emotional connections with our students by making a place where they feel good by his hands, heart and minds. It was not tricks at all!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[雾霾]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/22/smog/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-22T15:12:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/12/22/smog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>这不是一个新话题，但是却一直像幽灵一样挥之不去，影响人们的生活、健康，特别是心情。我担心它还会影响校园里孩子的身体健康，这是不可接受的，是红线。所以，现实强迫我们必须要认识雾霾、应对雾霾、治理雾霾。</p>

<p>一、认识雾霾<br/>
1、雾霾是什么？<br/>
雾霾，是雾和霾的组合词。雾霾常见于城市。中国不少地区将雾并入霾一起作为灾害性天气现象进行预警预报，统称为“雾霾天气”。<br/>
雾霾是特定气候条件与人类活动相互作用的结果。高密度人口的经济及社会活动排放大量细颗粒物（PM 2.5），一旦排放超过大气循环能力和承载度，细颗粒物浓度将持续积聚，此时如果受静稳天气等影响，极易出现大范围的雾霾。</p>

<p>气象学解释：<br/>
雾，是接近地面的空气因气温下降水蒸气凝结而成的悬浮的微小水滴；<br/>
霾，是大量极细微的干尘颗粒等均匀地浮游在空中，使水平能见度小于10千米的空气普遍浑浊现象，也称灰霾。<br/>
在气象学上，雾和霾的判识标准为：相对湿度小于80%时为霾；相对湿度大于90%时为雾；相对湿度在80%—90%之间时为雾和霾的混合物，其中雾和霾的程度要按照大气细颗粒物PM2.5和PM1.0（指空气动力学直径分别小于2.5和1.0微米的细颗粒）的浓度来判识。</p>

<p>值得指出的是，雾本来是一种自然现象，但是在污染导致大气细颗粒物增多的情况下，即使气象上判识为“雾”，也不再是完全的自然现象，而是有细颗粒物附着的微小水滴。</p>

<p>雾霾毒性大小，关键看携带的颗粒。颗粒如果是重金属就可能会导致重金属中毒，如果是致癌物质就会提升患癌症的概率。</p>

<p>摘自：http://tech.sina.com.cn/d/v/2015-12-10/doc-ifxmpnqf9456114.shtml</p>

<p>2、雾霾是如何形成的？<br/>
从PM2.5来源看，雾霾主要是人类活动造成的。不是天灾，是人祸。<br/>
PM2.5的来源可分为一次源（直接排放）和二次源（二次生成）。</p>

<p>一次源又可分为自然排放源和人为排放源。其中，自然排放源包括风扬尘土、火山灰、森林火灾、海浪飞沫、生物来源等。人为排放源包括工业粉尘、机动车尾气颗粒物、道路扬尘、建筑施工扬尘、厨房烟气等。</p>

<p>二次生成是指排放到大气中的气态污染物通过多种化学物理过程产生的二次细颗粒物。人类活动排放的大量气态污染物如二氧化硫SO2、氮氧化物NOx、氨气NH3、挥发性有机污染物（VOCs）等，都能在大气中被氧化产生硫酸盐、硝酸盐、铵盐和二次有机气溶胶（SOA）。这些新生成的细颗粒物是大气中PM2.5的重要来源。全球范围内，二次颗粒物贡献率在20%—80%之间，在我国中东部地区常常高达60%，在成霾时往往二次颗粒物所占比例更高。</p>

<p>也就是说，人类活动产生的二次颗粒物占比更高！从这个意义上说，雾霾主要是人类活动造成的。</p>

<p>3、雾霾的危害有哪些？<br/>
危害人体健康，特别是呼吸器官。</p>

<p>妨碍交通出行，提升安全隐患。</p>

<p>4、关于雾霾的谣言？<br/>
谣言一：只要戴口罩就能防雾霾？<br/>
谣言二： 空气净化器可以有效净化雾霾，家中必备？<br/>
谣言三：防雾霾中医药方、多吃蔬菜能防雾霾？<br/>
谣言四：雾霾是“核雾染”？<br/>
答案： 点击<a href="http://tech.sina.com.cn/d/v/2015-12-10/doc-ifxmpnqf9456114.shtml">这里</a>。</p>

<p>二、防护雾霾<br/>
1、户外活动如何防护？</p>

<p>2、室内活动如何防护？</p>

<p>3、如何调节个人活动达到防护的目的？</p>

<p>三、治理雾霾：从个体到社会，从科学到艺术，从产品到市场。<br/>
1、个人选择：从环保意识到生活习惯。<br/>
2、商业经济：如何让雾霾有利可图？<br/>
3、公共政策：让谁来买单？<br/>
4、产品研发：从口罩到空气净化机的设计。<br/>
5、科研工程：谁来把雾霾吹走？<br/>
6、文化艺术：神曲，还是神曲，没有话剧？</p>

<p><a href="http://www.iqiyi.com/w_19rrclfe59.html">雾霾版《卷珠帘》</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.iqiyi.com/w_19rrclbxvt.html">大雾版：北京北京</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ahtv.cn/swf/?video=293668">小品《雾霾！走开！》</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[孟德尔遗传定律是如何发现的]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/03/31/how-mendel-discover-genetic-rules/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-31T15:32:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/03/31/how-mendel-discover-genetic-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>平时教学中，我们的科学学习与实践往往相脱离，表现为知而不行、行而不知、知行不一。</p>

<p>比如老师过于强调所传授科学知识的对与错，而忽略知识发现和发展的过程。同时对于科学思维与实践的关注也不够。那么，如何在教学中给学生提供学习机会，发展学生科学思维与实践能力呢？</p>

<p>我们以孟德尔分离定律为例，平常教学我们注重讲清楚豌豆作为实验材料的优点、以及孟德尔一对相对性状豌豆杂交实验过程、结果以及孟德尔提出的解释和测交验证。我们在意的是学生能否能记住分离定律内容并应用其来解题、是否会写遗传图解。但是，我们对于孟德尔为什么要做这个实验、如何提出自己的假说并恰当运用科学实践方法验证自己的假说这些重要的问题，关注的还不过。</p>

<p>那么，我们是否可以让学生踏着孟德尔的脚步一起来经历分离定律的发现之旅呢？</p>

<ol>
<li><p>为什么要做植物杂交实验？<br/>
孟德尔做杂交实验是为了找出遗传的规律。找到遗传的规律就可以培育出优良的品种。比如多产的作物或者具有优质羊毛的山羊。在当时有一些流行的遗传观念，比如融合遗传，单亲遗传等。当时很少有做实验对这些观念进行严肃的检验。孟德尔不同，他亲手做了很多植物杂交的实验，其中豌豆杂交实验最为成功。</p></li>
<li><p>为什么选择豌豆？<br/>
在生物学研究中，选择恰当的实验材料是成功的第一步。孟德尔选择豌豆，主要有如下原因：<br/>
1 豌豆闭花传粉，自花授粉，很容易获得纯种。<br/>
2 豌豆有易于区分的相对性状，比如植株的高矮，籽粒的圆皱。<br/>
3 豌豆杂交实验容易实施，并且实验周期也较短。</p></li>
<li><p>如何做杂交实验？<br/>
首先孟德尔建立了自己实验纯种品系，纯种高茎，纯种矮茎。选用纯种并只观察一对相对性状可以让影响因素尽可能简化。</p></li>
</ol>


<p>因为纯种只会延续原有性状，并不能观察到更多新的遗传现象。于是孟德尔对两个品种的豌豆进行杂交。结果F1全部为高茎。这个结果支持融合遗传的假说吗？不支持。那么这个结果支持单亲遗传假说吗？还不确定。假如单亲遗传假说成立，那么将父本和母本的品系对调，结果肯定不一样。于是他又做了反交实验，结果F1还全部是高茎。因此，这个结果也不支持单亲遗传假说。</p>

<p>孟德尔在思考这个结果该怎么解释呢？为什么只出现了高茎没有矮茎呢？这个高茎和亲本中的高茎一样吗？如何检验呢？</p>

<p>于是它让F1自交，因为豌豆是闭花传粉，所以他只需要将F1收获的种子种下去就可以了。他想，如果F2都是高茎，那就说明这个F1高茎和亲本高茎一样都是纯合的。结果F2有高茎，也有矮茎。这说明这个F1高茎并不是纯合的，它能产生矮茎后代，说明它还保留着控制矮茎性状的遗传物质，因为它表现为高茎，所以它必然有控制高茎的遗传物质，这样一来，它只能是一个杂合子。他把F1自交产生F2，其中大部分为显性性状，少部分为隐性性状的现象叫做性状分离。他对F2高茎和矮茎进行了数量统计，发现高茎787，矮茎277。</p>

<p>这是一个偶然现象吗？<br/>
于是他有做了另外6对相对性状的杂交试验，结果如下表。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/seven_traits.png" alt="六对相对性状" /></p>

<p>孟德尔的神情开始凝重起来，这绝对不是一个偶然现象，那么，到底该如何解释呢？<br/>
他开始回想这个实验过程。</p>

<p>F1必然同时含有控制高茎的遗传因子和控制矮茎的遗传因子。<br/>
因此（1）遗传因子很可能是成对存在的。</p>

<p>但因为F2代又重新出现了矮茎，而且是更亲代一模一样的矮茎，这说明矮茎遗传因子并没因为和高茎遗传因子在一起而受到改变。<br/>
这说明（2）遗传因子相互独立，并不相互侵染。</p>

<p>孟德尔知道，花粉粒和卵细胞结合产生F1，那么，为了使得遗传物质总量保持不变，亲本只能将一份遗传因子通过传递给子代。也就是（3）形成配子时，成对的遗传因子相互分离分别进入不同的配子。</p>

<p>最后，（4）雌雄配子随机结合形成合子。</p>

<p>这个假说完美的解释了一对相对性状的杂交试验结果，包括3:1的分离比。</p>

<p>那么这个假说真的是正确的吗？</p>

<p>这个假说的关键是F1可以产生两种类型的配子，并且其比例是1:1。那么，如何检验F1产生的配子类型和比例呢？</p>

<p>于是，孟德尔有进行了测交实验。测交的结果，F2高茎和矮茎比例非常接近1:1。<br/>
于是，分离定律得到了进一步验证。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教学与供需]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/02/27/assignment-as-market-goods/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-27T15:33:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2016/02/27/assignment-as-market-goods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天，我想说一说教学与市场供需的关系。</p>

<p>从哪里说起呢这要从我的一堂课说起，在这堂课上，我给学生布置了一些学习任务，于是有一些学生向我抱怨，说任务太多了，怕完成不好，可不可以少布置一点？别的系好像都没有布置这么多的任务。我于是说，有些任务不重要完全可以不做，这些任务真的是精简的不能再精简了。于是师生开始了讨价还价。</p>

<p>课下的时候，我开始反思为什么会出现这样的状况。为什么在课堂上，一方面我倾向于倾听学生的意见，但是另一方面我又不愿采纳学生的意见而少布置一点任务。我心里面是不是还有那种教师权威的观念，认为教师应该说一不二。假如我的教育理念是以学生为中心的，视乎我应该听从学生的意见，纳谏如流才对。但发自我的责任心，我又想让同学们多做、多学一点东西，而且我坚持认为任务已经减少的不能再减少了。课程还没有真正的开始，布置学习任务变成了市场上的讨价还价，最后无论我是否减少任务，我都已经落了下乘。</p>

<p>通常一门课程学生学得好，要有几个前提条件。第一条，学生想学、愿意学，知道为什么学。第二条，学生知道学什么，要完成哪些任务。第三条学生知道如何学以及完成任务的方法。</p>

<p>就拿我这节课来说，我以为学生都想在这个课程上，尽量完成更多的任务、学到更多的东西，但实际上他们想学的意愿并不如我预判的那样强烈。接下来当我布置任务的时候，为了少投入一些时间，当然要跟我讨价还价了。还有一个原因，那就是部分同学确还不知道完成这些任务的方法，有一些畏难情绪。</p>

<p>我就变成了市场上面卖鱼的，顾客说不要了，我说必须要，顾客说不要那么多，我说不能再少了，自由交易成了强买强卖了，所以我仔细想了一下，还真是要把一些任务再精简一下。我不能为了自己的面子，或者所谓的教师权威，而强迫学生一定要完成，那些他们还没有认识到重要性的任务，这种强迫的教育绝对不是，好什么好的教育，不管其结果如何。这叫做，强扭的瓜不甜。</p>

<p>那么用什么方法可以扭转这样的局面？</p>

<p>其实，首先的不应该布置任务，而是应该帮助学生认识到任务的重要性，树立学习榜样和学习目标。之后才是，告诉他们哪些任务可以帮助他们达成学习目标，最后，在授予完成任务的方法，让他们知道这些任务是他们完全力所能及的。这样的教学顺序才是恰当的。也就是先有学习需要，之后有学习内容和任务，最后才是具体任务的完成方法。遵循的顺序是，why,what,how。</p>

<p>还是那个市场，我还是那个卖鱼的，这回我不是着急把鱼卖给顾客，而是要先让顾客了解到吃我这种鱼的好处：深海鱼的营养价值很高，能补充人体必需氨基酸，含有的大量多元不饱和脂肪酸，降低高血压、动脉硬化、心脏病、脑血栓等疾病的发病率，保持身体健康。鱼肉新鲜，价格公道。顾客要要多买一点，我说买多了吃不了就不新鲜了。然后再教给他烹饪的方法，顾客说怎么做，我说隔水蒸到九分熟就可以，这样最有营养了。</p>

<p>万事开头难，让学生进入到想学、愿意学的状态，往往是课程成功的第一步，假如教师忽略了这一步，就会像我一样尴尬的落到与学生讨价还价的境地，最后很容易变成强买强卖了。激发学生学习欲望和学习兴趣，是教师的看家法宝。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
