<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 教学 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/教学/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-16T15:38:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lesson plan of cell structure]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-16T11:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Topic: Cell structure/Biology<br/>
Designer: <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/about/">Chunlei Zhang</a><br/>
Student: High school students<br/>
Notes: This is just an imaginary teaching learning scenario sequences.</p>

<p>Imagine a house in your mind(or you can draw it), maybe your family house, maybe not. What does it look like from outside? What about the look of inside? What is the house composed of? What is the function of each part? Can you ask more questions about house?( who made them? which style? what is it made of? how to make a house?) cool!</p>

<p>Today we are going to study cell,similar with house, you can imagine cell as a house for a new strange life. You can ask any questions you want? (list students questions)</p>

<p>Some of your questions, scientists have answered? some question still need further inquiry.</p>

<p>Do you know why scientists study cell?(R or NR) They want to know more about life, an essential question is "What is life is made of?" They finally found the answer through a special equipment -- microscope. Their finding suggest that most organism are made of cell. There is a story of discovery of cell.(telling the story)</p>

<p>Cell are usually very very small, and invisible to the naked eye. Do you have any experience of bleeding? What is the color of blood? If you take out of the blood cells, then it looks like this.[picture] What can you infer from this picture? If you look at blood through microscope, then you can see this. These are blood cells. If you look at the blood vessel, you will see this.(video) Not only blood, every parts of your body is made of cells.(student can also draw this conclusion by observing the picture of different tissue are made of different types cells)</p>

<p>Can you guess what is inside of a cell?(Predicted answers: empty, just water or solution, there must be some structures inside)</p>

<p>If we use electron microscope, then we can see the inside structure of the cell. Here is some pictures, try to build a cell structure model as a group. You can number different structures.</p>

<p>When the structures were first discovered by scientist, they also found it hard to communicate, so they name them. Sometime they name them by their characteristics, sometimes using the scientist's name. (give the names of different structure) Can you distinguish the different structures inside a cell? Have a try in your group.</p>

<p>Group assessment, show Simulation and let students guess what is the structure and its possible function.</p>

<p>How the different structures relate with each other? We don't know. What do you suggest, if you are going to study this research question.</p>

<p>Scientists got these pictures, when they study how proteins are made and transported outside of cells.[three pictures]</p>

<p>What can you see in these pictures? What can you infer? Can you guess or infer the functions of different structures? How do they function together in this process?</p>

<p>Home work: Make a cell structure model that can represent all your group knowledge about cell. We will share and discuss our models on next lesson.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Japan Lesson Study]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/24/japan-lesson-study/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-24T22:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/24/japan-lesson-study</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I watched two vedios of Japan science teaching see my <a href="/blog/2013/08/19/timss-video-and-reflection-of-teaching-science-with-modeling/">previous post</a></p>

<p>Since then I tend to pay close attention to Japan science education including both teaching practice and teacher professional development. Tonight we talked about the lesson study in Japan and China, So googled Japan lesson study and found 2 interesting resources(attached at the end of this post).</p>

<p>I think the Japan lesson study sounds really good.</p>

<p>First, the lesson is designed and prepared by a team not a single teacher. This is different from China, where one teacher is reponsible for everything and under a great pressure. When a team prepare and co-design the lesson, teacher can really have more opportunities to learn from each other.</p>

<p>Second, the study is aiming to solve a problem or acheiving a special goal. It is not providing a common good lesson for other teachers to follow or comment. This goal-orantied study will make it more meaningful for teachers. It becomes easier for other teachers take a stand to think if they have acheived their goal or what would help.</p>

<p>Third, the team will spend 3-4 years on the same goal, they will design a long range plan to achieve it. They also refine their goal ever year. So it tend to be a continue systematic problem solving process with significant value in a special school context.</p>

<p>Fourth, the topics of discussion and reflection can cover a wide range of concerns, including content related issues(goal of unit and lesson, concepts, problem to focus on, students' solution and response), and pedagogical issues and behaviors issues, also education rationals and goals.</p>

<p>Resources:<br/>
<a href="http://www.rbs.org/SiteData/docs/yoshidaoverview/aeafddf638d3bd67526570d5b4889ae0/yoshidaoverview.pdf">Lesson Study: An Introduction By Makoto Yoshida &amp; Clea Fernandez</a></p>

<p>Japanese Lesson Study: Dr. Clea Fernandez</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/yv-7xmZDozo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors for teaching and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T23:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Metaphors for teaching:</h3>

<p>A teacher is just like a cook. You can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes, so you can also tell a good teacher by his students' acheivements. Sometimes you can also tell a good cook by observing his cooking process. Good cook can aways get everything ready quickly and easily. Good teacher do the same thing.</p>

<p>Teachers' job is adapting the curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. Effective teachers are aware of what they are currently doing, aways pursueing new effecive ways to teach the same content. It is just like cooks making foods for different customers.  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Teachers' content knowledge affect their abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driving. The taxi driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/traffic-jam.png" alt="traffic jam" /></p>

<h3>Metaphor for education reform:</h3>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The teacher is like a swimmer in a river. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-is-swimmer.png" alt="teacher is swimmer" /></p>

<p>The science teacher educator stand on the river bank and tell the swimmer where to go, how to swim, which style is more effective than others. But the most important thing for a person in the river is to keep safty and the most reliable style is the style which he already got. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and new skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not always stand by but jump into the water and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A list of science labs that rocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T00:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will make a list of science labs activities which are so fun and interesting that you can't miss.</p>

<p>Real Labs<br/>
+   Secret tube(modeling)<br/>
+   Candle in the tube above water(causal model)<br/>
+   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3600?ref=search">Transpiration lab</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/careerstart-grade8/5540">Cell theory and plant respiration G8</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/criticalthinking/6650">Water quality - Critical thinking in science</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3226?ref=search">Amazing amaryllis activitiesm G2-3 4Ws</a></p>

<p>Hands on activities<br/>
+   <a href="http://www.education.com/activity/article/Sourdough_bread/">Sourdough Science!</a><br/>
+   Making a safty harmer<br/>
+   Design a sprinkler head for watering lawn</p>

<p>Virual Labs/ Simulations<br/>
+   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
+   PhET: <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/">Free online simulations</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities/">Interactive simulation based inquiry activities - Chunlei's Blog</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ridiculous jump and serious problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/ridiculous-jump-and-serious-problem/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T22:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/ridiculous-jump-and-serious-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just watched a TV program named Ridiculous. The following is special one.</p>

<div>
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/9Cmw2m2z6_0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Really Ridiculous, I can't help laughing when thinking of the great jump.<br/>
But sometimes it can be a very serious problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bus-in-water.jpg" alt="bus in water" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/emergency-exit.jpg" alt="emergency exit" /><br/>
If you are the designer of the break glass hammer. How can you make sure people can succeed to break the glass with the hammer. What data do you need to collect or search? What physics principles you want to apply? What experiment do you want to do? What observation you want to make? Who do you want to interview?<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hammer.jpg" alt="hammer" /><br/>
This is a serious problem, but also a good challenge for you to figure it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
