<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 教学 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/教学/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-15T18:59:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Japan Lesson Study]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/24/japan-lesson-study/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-24T22:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/24/japan-lesson-study</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I watched two vedios of Japan science teaching see my <a href="/blog/2013/08/19/timss-video-and-reflection-of-teaching-science-with-modeling/">previous post</a></p>

<p>Since then I tend to pay close attention to Japan science education including both teaching practice and teacher professional development. Tonight we talked about the lesson study in Japan and China, So googled Japan lesson study and found 2 interesting resources(attached at the end of this post).</p>

<p>I think the Japan lesson study sounds really good.</p>

<p>First, the lesson is designed and prepared by a team not a single teacher. This is different from China, where one teacher is reponsible for everything and under a great pressure. When a team prepare and co-design the lesson, teacher can really have more opportunities to learn from each other.</p>

<p>Second, the study is aiming to solve a problem or acheiving a special goal. It is not providing a common good lesson for other teachers to follow or comment. This goal-orantied study will make it more meaningful for teachers. It becomes easier for other teachers take a stand to think if they have acheived their goal or what would help.</p>

<p>Third, the team will spend 3-4 years on the same goal, they will design a long range plan to achieve it. They also refine their goal ever year. So it tend to be a continue systematic problem solving process with significant value in a special school context.</p>

<p>Fourth, the topics of discussion and reflection can cover a wide range of concerns, including content related issues(goal of unit and lesson, concepts, problem to focus on, students' solution and response), and pedagogical issues and behaviors issues, also education rationals and goals.</p>

<p>Resources:<br/>
<a href="http://www.rbs.org/SiteData/docs/yoshidaoverview/aeafddf638d3bd67526570d5b4889ae0/yoshidaoverview.pdf">Lesson Study: An Introduction By Makoto Yoshida &amp; Clea Fernandez</a></p>

<p>Japanese Lesson Study: Dr. Clea Fernandez</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/yv-7xmZDozo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors for teaching and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T23:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Metaphors for teaching:</h3>

<p>A teacher is just like a cook. You can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes, so you can also tell a good teacher by his students' acheivements. Sometimes you can also tell a good cook by observing his cooking process. Good cook can aways get everything ready quickly and easily. Good teacher do the same thing.</p>

<p>Teachers' job is adapting the curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. Effective teachers are aware of what they are currently doing, aways pursueing new effecive ways to teach the same content. It is just like cooks making foods for different customers.  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Teachers' content knowledge affect their abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driving. The taxi driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/traffic-jam.png" alt="traffic jam" /></p>

<h3>Metaphor for education reform:</h3>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The teacher is like a swimmer in a river. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-is-swimmer.png" alt="teacher is swimmer" /></p>

<p>The science teacher educator stand on the river bank and tell the swimmer where to go, how to swim, which style is more effective than others. But the most important thing for a person in the river is to keep safty and the most reliable style is the style which he already got. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and new skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not always stand by but jump into the water and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A list of science labs that rocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T00:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will make a list of science labs activities which are so fun and interesting that you can't miss.</p>

<p>Real Labs<br/>
+   Secret tube(modeling)<br/>
+   Candle in the tube above water(causal model)<br/>
+   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3600?ref=search">Transpiration lab</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/careerstart-grade8/5540">Cell theory and plant respiration G8</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/criticalthinking/6650">Water quality - Critical thinking in science</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3226?ref=search">Amazing amaryllis activitiesm G2-3 4Ws</a></p>

<p>Hands on activities<br/>
+   <a href="http://www.education.com/activity/article/Sourdough_bread/">Sourdough Science!</a><br/>
+   Making a safty harmer<br/>
+   Design a sprinkler head for watering lawn</p>

<p>Virual Labs/ Simulations<br/>
+   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
+   PhET: <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/">Free online simulations</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities/">Interactive simulation based inquiry activities - Chunlei's Blog</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ridiculous jump and serious problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/ridiculous-jump-and-serious-problem/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T22:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/ridiculous-jump-and-serious-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just watched a TV program named Ridiculous. The following is special one.</p>

<div>
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/9Cmw2m2z6_0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Really Ridiculous, I can't help laughing when thinking of the great jump.<br/>
But sometimes it can be a very serious problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bus-in-water.jpg" alt="bus in water" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/emergency-exit.jpg" alt="emergency exit" /><br/>
If you are the designer of the break glass hammer. How can you make sure people can succeed to break the glass with the hammer. What data do you need to collect or search? What physics principles you want to apply? What experiment do you want to do? What observation you want to make? Who do you want to interview?<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hammer.jpg" alt="hammer" /><br/>
This is a serious problem, but also a good challenge for you to figure it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[科学教法课上的种子萌发实验]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/seed-activity-in-method-of-biology-and-earth-science-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T19:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/seed-activity-in-method-of-biology-and-earth-science-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>我有幸参与了Dr C的三次教法课，每次课一个小时。之所以第一次参与这个课堂，一个很直接的原因是我被一盆开的很漂亮的花吸引了，我想知道老师想用这盆花干什么。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-19-12.11.21.jpg" alt="漂亮的花朵" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>后面之所以继续参与课堂，则是因为我被课堂的活动吸引了，其中之一就是种子萌发这个活动。<br/>
其实种子萌发这个活动我们也中学也做，不过我中学没做过，因为当时考试不考。这次看外国本科生做这个活动，觉得很新鲜。老师到底想干嘛？<br/>
老师先让学生仔细关注天气预报中的信息，日期，温度，湿度，风力，天气等，那么这些变量可能与植物生长有什么关系呢？植物的生长受哪些因素的影响？如何影响呢？<br/>
带着这些问题，开始进行活动，每个人发一个透明的封口袋还有一些扁豆种子，然后在封口袋中放一张吸水纸，在底端1/3处用订书机打上一排钉子。然后将种子放进去，并且往里面添加一些水。写上姓名和日期。<br/>
这是第一次课8/19的照片：<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-19-12.08.01.jpg" alt="8-19" /><br/>
这是第二次课8/26的照片：<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-26-11.07.53.jpg" alt="8-26a" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-26-11.09.46.jpg" alt="8-26b" /> <br/>
这是第三次课8/30的照片：<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-30-10.56.08.jpg" alt="8-30a" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-30-10.56.33.jpg" alt="8-30b" />
第二次课上还没开始前，老师的幻灯片上就要求每个同学对种子萌发的情况进行观察、测量、记录、绘图等。有的学生的种子疯长，有的则还是老样子。他们很兴奋的讨论着这些结果和可能的原因，有的说是温度，有的说是水，有的说是光，五花八门。  <br/>
第三次课上，老师在下课前布置了一个任务，每个学生要用一个大可乐瓶制作一个植物培养瓶，老师提供了样板，学生则需要设计一个实验检验自己的某个假设，可以组成小组合作设计和控制变量。</p>

<p>这些是大四的本科生，他们毕业后可能会当科学教师。这些活动不仅仅是关注在科学研究上，同时教师也在尝试传递Model-based Learning（基于模型的学习）的理念和实践。这不是说教式的探究，而是真刀真枪的用自己的教学方式践行理念。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
