<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 教学 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/教学/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-24T14:39:31+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cognitive Apprenticeship]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T13:11:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sawyer, R. (2006). The Cambridge handbook of the learning sciences. (R. K. Sawyer, Ed.). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. doi:10.1017/CBO9780511816833</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Mscare.png" alt="Cognitive Apprenticeship" /></p>

<p>Method(Mscare):<br/>
Ways to promote the development of expertise<br/>
1.  Modeling: teacher performs a task so students can observe<br/>
1.  Scaffolding: teacher provides supports to help the student perform a task<br/>
1.  Coaching: teacher observes and facilitates while students perform a task<br/>
1.  Articulation: teacher encourages students to verbalize their knowledge and thinking<br/>
1.  Reflection: teacher enables students to compare their performance with others<br/>
1.  Exploration: teacher invites students to pose and solve their own problems</p>

<p>认知性学徒机制在网络社区甚至大学的学习实践中非常值得关注。在学习活动设计时，也应该遵循和利用上图所提到的步骤和原则。</p>

<p>比如这个表格所提到的内容、方法、次序和社区，在学习活动设计的时候就可以好好加以参照。</p>

<p>例如对于教学设计的学习：<br/>
一、内容<br/>
专业知识：前端分析（学习内容、学习者、学习需要）、教学目标设定和表述、设计教学思路和过程落实重难点、学习成果的评价设计、在具体教学情境下实施并优化。<br/>
一般性学习策略： 阅读材料、观察教学录像、见习、与专家教师交流、与同学相互交流、尝试设计和实施教学活动、自我反思。<br/>
控制策略：制定学习目标和学习计划、记录学习进度、提前准备、主动参与、主动寻求帮助、反思和总结、树立更有挑战的学习目标、掌控时间。<br/>
学习方法：通过反复强化练习口语以心理素质、通过优秀设计和教学视频找到自己的短板并模仿和创新、通过与专家教师的交流了解教学设计背后的思考和专家教师的思考和工作模式、通过微格训练锻炼基本的教学技能、通过阅读文献了解学生前科学概念研究成果、通过网络搜索查找教学素材和科学史内容。</p>

<p>二、方法<br/>
教师演示或者观看专家教师课堂录像<br/>
作为助教与一线教师共同授课或者分析课后作业<br/>
教师对师范生的学习活动组织的具体环节和过程进行校正和点评<br/>
指导老师帮助师范生理清自己的教学思路、活动和活动意图<br/>
鼓励师范生与其他师范生或者指导老师的教学做比较（目标、课堂气氛、教学技巧、学习效果等）<br/>
指导教师鼓励师范生思考和解决自己教学中遇到的问题</p>

<p>三、次序<br/>
教学设计任务应该：<br/>
由简单到复杂（观看视频、分析教学线索和设计意图、了解学生、分析内容、设计和表述教学目标、设计思路、收集素材、设计过程、学习效果评价的设计、评课、设计完整的一堂课、说课）<br/>
由一般情境到多种情境（初中、高中；农村、城市；普通、重点；传统、创新）<br/>
由总体概括到具体任务</p>

<p>四、社区<br/>
实际到中学去，看一看、相一想、试一试<br/>
建立网络分享、互助、活动学习社区<br/>
建立与一线教师和专家教师的专业对话<br/>
建立见习、实习的基地和教学训练的小组活动常规<br/>
激励内部动机，向着专家教师努力<br/>
学会集体合作、树立并完成更有挑战性的目标</p>

<p>对于此书感兴趣的人，其目录如下：<br/>
Contents</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction: The New Science of Learning 1
R. Keith Sawyer</li>
</ol>


<p>part i<br/>
FOUNDATIONS<br/>
2 . Foundations and Opportunities for an Interdisciplinary Science of Learning 19<br/>
John D. Bransford, Brigid Barron, Roy D. Pea, Andrew Meltzoff, Patricia Kuhl, Philip Bell, Reed Stevens, Daniel L. Schwartz, Nancy Vye, Byron Reeves, Jeremy Roschelle, and Nora H. Sabelli<br/>
3. Constructionism 35<br/>
Yasmin B. Kafai<br/>
4. Cognitive Apprenticeship 47<br/>
Allan Collins<br/>
5. Cognitive Tutors: Technology Bringing Learning Sciences<br/>
to the Classroom 61<br/>
Kenneth R. Koedinger and Albert Corbett<br/>
6. Learning in Activity 79<br/>
James G. Greeno<br/>
7. Knowledge Building: Theory, Pedagogy, and Technology 97<br/>
Marlene Scardamalia and Carl Bereiter</p>

<p>part ii<br/>
METHODOLOGIES<br/>
8. Learner-Centered Design: Reflections on the Past and Directions for the Future 119<br/>
Chris Quintana, Namsoo Shin, Cathleen Norris, and Elliot Soloway<br/>
9. The Evolution of Design Studies as Methodology 135<br/>
Jere Confrey<br/>
10. Design-Based Research: A Methodological Toolkit for the Learning Scientist 153<br/>
Sasha Barab<br/>
11. Guiding Inquiry-Based Math Learning 171<br/>
Paul Cobb and Kay McClain<br/>
12 . Analyzing Collaborative Discourse 187<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer<br/>
13. Assessing for Deep Understanding 205<br/>
Sharon M. Carver</p>

<p>part iii<br/>
THE NATURE OF KNOWLEDGE<br/>
14. Case-Based Reasoning 225<br/>
Janet L. Kolodner<br/>
15. The Knowledge Integration Perspective on Learning and Instruction 243<br/>
Marcia C. Linn<br/>
16. A History of Conceptual Change Research: Threads and Fault Lines 265<br/>
Andrea A. diSessa<br/>
17. Spatial Representations and Imagery in Learning 283<br/>
Daniel L. Schwartz and Julie Heiser<br/>
18. Literacy and the Learning Sciences 299<br/>
Annemarie Sullivan Palincsar and Barbara G. Ladewski</p>

<p>part iv<br/>
MAKING KNOWLEDGE VISIBLE<br/>
19. Project-Based Learning 317<br/>
Joseph S. Krajcik and Phyllis C. Blumenfeld<br/>
20. Making Authentic Practices Accessible to Learners: Design Challenges and Strategies 335<br/>
Daniel C. Edelson and Brian J. Reiser<br/>
21. BioKIDS: An Animated Conversation on the Development of Curricular Activity Structures for Inquiry Science 355<br/>
Nancy Butler Songer<br/>
22. Cultivating Model-Based Reasoning in Science Education 371<br/>
Richard Lehrer and Leona Schauble<br/>
23. Exploring Mathematics Through Construction and Collaboration 389<br/>
Richard Noss and Celia Hoyles</p>

<p>part v<br/>
LEARNING TOGETHER<br/>
24. Computer-Supported Collaborative Learning 409<br/>
Gerry Stahl, Timothy Koschmann, and Daniel D. Suthers<br/>
25. WILD for Learning: Interacting Through New Computing Devices Anytime, Anywhere 427<br/>
Roy D. Pea and Heidy Maldonado<br/>
26. Arguing to Learn 443<br/>
Jerry Andriessen<br/>
27. Learning in Online Communities 461<br/>
Amy Bruckman<br/>
part vi<br/>
LEARNING ENVIRONMENTS<br/>
28. Motivation and Cognitive Engagement in Learning Environments 475<br/>
Phyllis C. Blumenfeld, Toni M. Kempler, and Joseph S. Krajcik<br/>
29. Learning as a Cultural Process: Achieving Equity Through Diversity 489<br/>
Na’ilah Suad Nasir, Ann S. Rosebery, Beth Warren, and Carol D. Lee<br/>
30. Prospects for Transforming Schools with Technology- Supported Assessment 505<br/>
Barbara Means<br/>
31. Internet Use in Schools: Promise and Problems 521<br/>
Janet Ward Schofield<br/>
32. Teacher Learning Research and the Learning Sciences 535<br/>
Barry J. Fishman and Elizabeth A. Davis<br/>
33. Scaling Up: Evolving Innovations Beyond Ideal Settings to Challenging Contexts of Practice 551<br/>
Chris Dede<br/>
34. Conclusion: The Schools of the Future 567<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</p>

<p>Afterword: After How Comes What 581<br/>
Seymour Papert<br/>
Epilogue: The Fundamental Issue in the Learning Sciences 587<br/>
Roger C. Schank<br/>
Author Index 593<br/>
Subject Index</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demonstration of barometric pressure using a bottle of water]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T19:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Oliver gave us an assignment to design a demonstration of science teaching. I already had several ideas. One was show them <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/">The surprising trees</a>. Another one was rolling a paper roll. The last one was the bottle water activity.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bottle-water-demonstration.png" alt="bottle water demonstration" /><br/>
Today, when I was on the road home after swimming. I couldn't stop thinking a more neat idea and keep revising the activity. I was very tired because of swimming but my thinking keep running in my head, even on bed with windows closed and curtain down. I imagined what the scene would be like, what to say, what to do, in what order, what questions to ask. I even came up with a little poem and dialogue:</p>

<pre><code>Needle needle hot
Let the water jet out
Jet out, jet out
Oh my God
Nothing happen

Wait a minute, let me check out...
Hymn
Why
Maybe we need the hole more lower
Let me make another hole

Hymn
Maybe the we can lay down the bottle
Hymn
Let me think, drawing the hole of water on blackboard,talk to myself

Maybe we can make both the holes open
Maybe we can check out in the up-stand position
Why?
Why in this position it work
In this position it doesn't work
Did you see that?
So when will the water come out? 
One open hole or two? In which position? In which hole does the water come out?
How do you explain this?
Why one hole doesn't work?
Why two holes on the same height also doesn't work?
Why the two holes need to be on different height?
</code></pre>

<p>Finally, the design finished and the thinking stopped. This is the reason why I don't write at night. Thinking will not let me sleep.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[师范生课程如何设置]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/curriculum-for-preservice-teachers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T14:36:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/curriculum-for-preservice-teachers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>怎样的课程设置对未来教师的专业成长更有利？<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/curriculum-preservice-teacher.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[对教法课的反思]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/03/reflection-of-methods-class/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-03T12:48:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/03/reflection-of-methods-class</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天是本学期的最后一天。在Dr. Luft课堂上，同学们每个人5分钟报告了自己的收获，然后师生提问和评论。同学们的收获是很多元的，涉及到师生关系、与指导教师关系、科学探究、教育观念、教师角色和行为、学科知识、学生差异、教学活动、课堂提问、师生互动、教学限制、考试压力等等，或者抽象或者具体。在报告的过程中，学生顾虑到使用探究会消耗更多的时间，Dr. Luft还组织了讨论，让每个小组列出5种简单的不需要消耗多少时间的探究任务，此外还反复督促大家思考，整个学期中自己发生的改变。</p>

<p>课堂上我一直下思考，如果我是一个师范生，我会如何设定自己的理念，承担什么样的教师角色和行为。我听到了更多来自学生实践经验的声音，那么教育研究的声音呢？教育研究与实践是否吻合？那些地方不吻合？如何解释这些不吻合的地方？是否有必要在课程中增添关于教师如何学习的知识？</p>

<p>还有一个问题就是中国和美国的教法课有哪些不同？这些问题会引领我更深入的思考和行动。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lesson plan of cell structure]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-16T11:05:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Topic: Cell structure/Biology<br/>
Designer: <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/about/">Chunlei Zhang</a><br/>
Student: High school students<br/>
Notes: This is just an imaginary teaching learning scenario sequences.</p>

<p>Imagine a house in your mind(or you can draw it), maybe your family house, maybe not. What does it look like from outside? What about the look of inside? What is the house composed of? What is the function of each part? Can you ask more questions about house?( who made them? which style? what is it made of? how to make a house?) cool!</p>

<p>Today we are going to study cell,similar with house, you can imagine cell as a house for a new strange life. You can ask any questions you want? (list students questions)</p>

<p>Some of your questions, scientists have answered? some question still need further inquiry.</p>

<p>Do you know why scientists study cell?(R or NR) They want to know more about life, an essential question is "What is life is made of?" They finally found the answer through a special equipment -- microscope. Their finding suggest that most organism are made of cell. There is a story of discovery of cell.(telling the story)</p>

<p>Cell are usually very very small, and invisible to the naked eye. Do you have any experience of bleeding? What is the color of blood? If you take out of the blood cells, then it looks like this.[picture] What can you infer from this picture? If you look at blood through microscope, then you can see this. These are blood cells. If you look at the blood vessel, you will see this.(video) Not only blood, every parts of your body is made of cells.(student can also draw this conclusion by observing the picture of different tissue are made of different types cells)</p>

<p>Can you guess what is inside of a cell?(Predicted answers: empty, just water or solution, there must be some structures inside)</p>

<p>If we use electron microscope, then we can see the inside structure of the cell. Here is some pictures, try to build a cell structure model as a group. You can number different structures.</p>

<p>When the structures were first discovered by scientist, they also found it hard to communicate, so they name them. Sometime they name them by their characteristics, sometimes using the scientist's name. (give the names of different structure) Can you distinguish the different structures inside a cell? Have a try in your group.</p>

<p>Group assessment, show Simulation and let students guess what is the structure and its possible function.</p>

<p>How the different structures relate with each other? We don't know. What do you suggest, if you are going to study this research question.</p>

<p>Scientists got these pictures, when they study how proteins are made and transported outside of cells.[three pictures]</p>

<p>What can you see in these pictures? What can you infer? Can you guess or infer the functions of different structures? How do they function together in this process?</p>

<p>Home work: Make a cell structure model that can represent all your group knowledge about cell. We will share and discuss our models on next lesson.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
