<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 教学 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/教学/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-16T22:59:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modify my previous lesson ESCI7040-A1]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an assignment of Dr. Oliver's class ESCI7040(teaching strategies). The goal of this activity is to reflect on my own teaching and modify the plans for future teaching.</p>

<p>I taught learning theories to undergraduates in order to let them make sense of how students learn and apply these principles in their future teaching.</p>

<p>The guiding question is what is knowledge and how people learn? The big ideas include:<br/>
1. Different type of knowledge play different roles and people learn them differently.<br/>
2. Learning Science is not just learning scientific knowledge but also science practice and the nature of science.<br/>
3. Teacher need various types of knowledge to help students learn science.<br/>
4. Different learning theories understand people's learning differently and give different suggestions for teaching and learning.<br/>
5. Preconceptions, learning styles, learning strategies play an important role in students' learning.</p>

<p>This lesson takes 90 minutes and during 60 minutes I was lecturing.</p>

<h3>Task1: Reflections of this lesson:</h3>

<p>1 Wether the content of this lesson can effectively help them understand how students learn science and apply these principles in their teaching?<br/>
Some ideas are too general and loosely related. They should be deleted or modified.<br/>
You should focus more on students' learning not teachers' learning<br/>
Don't try to cover every learning theories, teach the most important one and the crucial strategies or tools.<br/>
You may also included some brain-based learning studies such as how learning occur and what factors may affect learning.<br/>
Conceptual change should be included in this lesson.<br/>
2 Are these goals/objectives appropriate for your students?<br/>
These goals are not challenging enough for undergraduates. More critical thinking and challenging tasks should be used in this lesson.<br/>
You can try to related your teaching methods with learning principles and invite students to think both in the role of learners and teacher(your role).</p>

<p>3 How were the goals/objectives appropriate for the course in which the unit was taught?<br/>
I found that I simply followed the sequence of the textbook. I may first teach this lesson 'learning theory' (Chapter 4) and then teach 'teaching strategies'(Chapter 3). Students should first know how leaning happen and then learn how to teach.</p>

<p>4 How the instructional strategies adequate for the learning you hoped would happen?<br/>
Lecture should be more interactive(share learning experience of yours or students, thinking aloud, student teaching), include more student-centered activities (sorting learning tasks, diagnosing students' learning difficulties, think-pair-share, one minute writing, interpret teaching clips).</p>

<p>5 How were the assessments--either formal or informal--adequate(and valid and reliable) for the task of assessing student learning?<br/>
There are two assessments: A1 explain Osmosis to high school students; A2 design a 5E lesson plan. A1 is an informal assessment on class. A2 seems not closely related with this lesson. A better assignment would be study students' preconceptions about one topic and design an activity to elicit students prior ideas.</p>

<h3>Task 2 redesign:</h3>

<h4>The big ideas that student should understand:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Learners build their knowledge on their prior knowledge collaboratively in special social context or situations.</li>
<li>Learning occur when connections are made in Neural Networks or social networks.</li>
<li>Well designed physical and social learning environment help students learn by improving their brains' function.</li>
<li>Prior ideas, emotion, metacogniton play crucial roles in students' science learning.</li>
<li>Different learning strategies suit for different learning tasks; Some tasks are more difficult than others; Student percept learning tasks differently.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The skills that student should develop:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Elicit and engage students' prior ideas of a core concept.</li>
<li>Diagnosis students' difficulties in learning a concept.</li>
<li>Design or redesign classroom learning environment to optimize students' learning.</li>
<li>Select proper learning strategies for special learning tasks.</li>
<li>Summary learning research results and its implications for teaching.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The interactive lecture and student activites:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Share personal learining stragegy (Chemical equilibrium)</li>
<li>Ask a student to thinking aloud</li>
<li>Student teaching one screen</li>
<li>sorting learning tasks</li>
<li>diagnosing students' learning difficulties in a teaching clip</li>
<li>think-pair-share</li>
<li>one minute writing</li>
</ol>


<h3>Task 3 reflect on why you change:</h3>

<p>My previous purpose is follow and cover the most important content both on the textbook and in my vision. I spent a lot of time on how to represent these content to students but did not pay too much attention to how these content serve the goal of this course. At that time, I did not have many activities to choose from and had to create my own one by one. I also had limited knowledge of how students learn science before, now I know more. So I want to include the more important ideas that I know and get rid of un important or unrelated ideas.</p>

<p>Although I believed that I should use more student-centered activities, but I just didn't have them. It took time for me to gather, test, accumulate related activities or ideas. My enriched learning experiences and pedagogical thinking also help me to generate new activities that probably work for my students.</p>

<p>Recently, I read some papers and books about evidence-based teaching and brain-based learning, they also encourage me to select the core ideas and activities for my teaching plan.</p>

<p>Conclusion: If you want to improve your teaching practice, you need to know more about the content, more about your students, more about what you can possibly do and use in your class. Of course, you also have to know what student really learn and why they do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curriculum for preservice teachers]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/curriculum-for-preservice-teachers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T14:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/curriculum-for-preservice-teachers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>怎样的课程设置对未来教师的专业成长更有利？<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/curriculum-preservice-teacher.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[对教法课的反思]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/03/reflection-of-methods-class/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-03T12:48:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/03/reflection-of-methods-class</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天是本学期的最后一天。在Dr. Luft课堂上，同学们每个人5分钟报告了自己的收获，然后师生提问和评论。同学们的收获是很多元的，涉及到师生关系、与指导教师关系、科学探究、教育观念、教师角色和行为、学科知识、学生差异、教学活动、课堂提问、师生互动、教学限制、考试压力等等，或者抽象或者具体。在报告的过程中，学生顾虑到使用探究会消耗更多的时间，Dr. Luft还组织了讨论，让每个小组列出5种简单的不需要消耗多少时间的探究任务，此外还反复督促大家思考，整个学期中自己发生的改变。</p>

<p>课堂上我一直下思考，如果我是一个师范生，我会如何设定自己的理念，承担什么样的教师角色和行为。我听到了更多来自学生实践经验的声音，那么教育研究的声音呢？教育研究与实践是否吻合？那些地方不吻合？如何解释这些不吻合的地方？是否有必要在课程中增添关于教师如何学习的知识？</p>

<p>还有一个问题就是中国和美国的教法课有哪些不同？这些问题会引领我更深入的思考和行动。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lesson plan of cell structure]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-16T11:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Topic: Cell structure/Biology<br/>
Designer: <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/about/">Chunlei Zhang</a><br/>
Student: High school students<br/>
Notes: This is just an imaginary teaching learning scenario sequences.</p>

<p>Imagine a house in your mind(or you can draw it), maybe your family house, maybe not. What does it look like from outside? What about the look of inside? What is the house composed of? What is the function of each part? Can you ask more questions about house?( who made them? which style? what is it made of? how to make a house?) cool!</p>

<p>Today we are going to study cell,similar with house, you can imagine cell as a house for a new strange life. You can ask any questions you want? (list students questions)</p>

<p>Some of your questions, scientists have answered? some question still need further inquiry.</p>

<p>Do you know why scientists study cell?(R or NR) They want to know more about life, an essential question is "What is life is made of?" They finally found the answer through a special equipment -- microscope. Their finding suggest that most organism are made of cell. There is a story of discovery of cell.(telling the story)</p>

<p>Cell are usually very very small, and invisible to the naked eye. Do you have any experience of bleeding? What is the color of blood? If you take out of the blood cells, then it looks like this.[picture] What can you infer from this picture? If you look at blood through microscope, then you can see this. These are blood cells. If you look at the blood vessel, you will see this.(video) Not only blood, every parts of your body is made of cells.(student can also draw this conclusion by observing the picture of different tissue are made of different types cells)</p>

<p>Can you guess what is inside of a cell?(Predicted answers: empty, just water or solution, there must be some structures inside)</p>

<p>If we use electron microscope, then we can see the inside structure of the cell. Here is some pictures, try to build a cell structure model as a group. You can number different structures.</p>

<p>When the structures were first discovered by scientist, they also found it hard to communicate, so they name them. Sometime they name them by their characteristics, sometimes using the scientist's name. (give the names of different structure) Can you distinguish the different structures inside a cell? Have a try in your group.</p>

<p>Group assessment, show Simulation and let students guess what is the structure and its possible function.</p>

<p>How the different structures relate with each other? We don't know. What do you suggest, if you are going to study this research question.</p>

<p>Scientists got these pictures, when they study how proteins are made and transported outside of cells.[three pictures]</p>

<p>What can you see in these pictures? What can you infer? Can you guess or infer the functions of different structures? How do they function together in this process?</p>

<p>Home work: Make a cell structure model that can represent all your group knowledge about cell. We will share and discuss our models on next lesson.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From falling objects experiment to a simulated experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/from-falling-objects-experiment-to-a-simulated-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T13:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/from-falling-objects-experiment-to-a-simulated-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I attened the Science Method class. An interesting question discussed was the experiment of falling objects-the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galileo%27s_Leaning_Tower_of_Pisa_experiment">Galileo's Leaning Tower of Pisa experiment</a>.  Dr. Luft provided us some students' responses and let us to figure out the students' thinking and how to response to students properly.</p>

<p>But the question caught my curiosity in the class was two ice cube droping from the same inclination.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bigsmallball.png" alt="two ball fall at the same height" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I asked my classmates what happens in the following situations.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/3inclinations.png" alt="picture" /></p>

<p>I acturally did the experiment using <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/en/simulation/energy-skate-park">simulation environment</a>.</p>

<p>The result is interesting. Ball B frist arrived at the bottom with lest time.(The first two curves are situation A; Next two curves are situation B)
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/skater.png" alt="Result" /></p>

<p>Ball A is the second arrived. Ball C is the last one. <br/>
From Leaning Tower of Pisa Experiment to simulated experiment, what a big change information technology has made to our science teaching and learning!</p>

<p>In fact, David Scott-Astronaut of  Apollo 15-recreated Galileo's famous experiment on the Moon by Hammer and Feather Drop.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/4mTsrRZEMwA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>You see the space technology also expanded our learning experience and provided us an amazing teaching resource-a dicrepant event.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
