<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: jigsaw | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/jigsaw/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-09T01:33:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Jigsaw of Supervision]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/23/the-jigsaw-of-supervision/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-23T21:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/23/the-jigsaw-of-supervision</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>How to make supervision sustainable?</h3>

<p>==>Design and Develop a mutual benefit and win-win relationship between participants.<br/>
It is kind of like to do a jigsaw. First you have to see every piece very clearly and then you can make the best guess and try to connect the two pieces.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/jigsaw.png" alt="Jigsaw of teaching supervision" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<h3>Look into the pieces(participants &amp; constrains):</h3>

<p>Supervisor<br/>
- typically are university professors(University)<br/>
- also can be experienced in-service teachers(Middle School)<br/>
- or principles(Middle School)<br/>
- always lack of time<br/>
- usually lack of content knowledge<br/>
- but have expertise in supervision and effective teaching research<br/>
- have lots of experiences and context knowledge</p>

<p>Supervise<br/>
- new teacher(Middle School)<br/>
- student teacher(University)<br/>
- in-service teacher who want to make a change(Middle School)<br/>
- usually have limited experiences, reflection abilities, PCK, knowledge of Supervision, effective teaching research and contexts<br/>
- sometimes lack of content knowledge</p>

<p>Facilitators<br/>
- companies<br/>
- administrators(MS)
- Professors<br/>
- stuff(MS, U)
- reformers<br/>
- NGO<br/>
- Government</p>

<h3>Possible Groups(supervisor,supervisee,facilitators):</h3>

<p>Single Community:<br/>
(student teacher, student teacher, professor)<br/>
(in-service teacher, in-service teacher, administrator)
(Experienced teacher, new teacher, stuff)</p>

<p>Cross two communities:<br/>
(Professor,(in-service teacher, student teacher),stuff)<br/>
(Professor,in-service teacher, administrators)<br/>
(Professor,(in-service teacher &amp; student teacher),stuff)<br/>
(In-service teacher, student teacher, professor)<br/>
((Professor &amp; in-service teacher),(in-service teacher &amp; student teacher),Professor)</p>

<p>Cross three communities:<br/>
(Professor,(in-service teacher &amp; student teacher), company)<br/>
(Professor,(in-service teacher &amp; student teacher),NGO)<br/>
(Professor,in-service teacher, Government)<br/>
(Professor,in-service teacher, reformers)</p>

<h3>What the literatures say about supervision?</h3>

<blockquote><p>Intensive mentoring significantly contributes to positively change in beginning elementary teachers’ learning to lead classroom discussions.<a href="#a">1</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Intensive mentoring usually can guarantee the time, but they are often short and unsustainable, sometimes teachers' various real need are ignored. Supervision can provide self-direct and continue professional development support to meet teachers special needs.</p>

<h3>Cooperating teachers have 11 ways to participate in teacher education:<a href="#b">2</a></h3>

<blockquote><p>Providers of Feedback,<br/>
Gatekeepers of the Profession,<br/>
Modelers of Practice,<br/>
Supporters of Reflection,<br/>
Gleaners of Knowledge, <br/>
Purveyors of Context, <br/>
Conveners of Relation,<br/>
Agents of Socialization,<br/>
Advocates of the Practical,<br/>
Abiders of Change, and<br/>
Teachers of Children.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/11ways.png" alt="Clarke2013" /></p></blockquote>

<h3>Possible cooperation relationships</h3>

<blockquote><p>Project Supervision was designed to develop professional development materials for school supervisors/mentors in a community of practice involving teachers – both experienced and preservice – and teacher educators.<a href="#c">3</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Six types of professional learning programs in the book of clinical supervision.<a href="#d">4</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Epert presenter<br/>
Skill trainning(theory, skills, practices, transfer to classroom)<br/>
Action research<br/>
Organization development(Specialist helps teacher and other staff diagnose strengths and weakness of their school or system, develop a plan of action, implement the plan, and evaluate its success)<br/>
Change process(staff developers help teacher make a desicion to a adopt a system-wide innovation, put the inovation into action, and institutionalize it)<br/>
Clinical supervision</p></blockquote>

<p>Only action research and clinical supervision are self-directed learning, certainly the later would be more suitable and supportive for new teachers.</p>

<p>Different types of online Mentoring programs:<a href="#e">5</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Task-based mentoring focuses on an individual’s short-term need to improve a skill or acquire knowledge in order to fulfill a new role.
Experience-based mentoring pairs an individual, who is new to an organization or a role, with a mentor who has experience in that role.
Just-in-time mentoring matches mentors with individuals who have an unanticipated need for assistance.
> One-to-one mentoring centers on a single mentor working with a single mentee
Team mentoring joins groups of mentors with groups of mentees.
Formal mentoring involves explicit expectations of the mentoring process and/or outcomes by specifying such characteristics as timelines, achievements, progress reporting, benchmarks, and communications formats.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Effective Cooperation Relationships studies</h3>

<blockquote><p>Riordan, G. P. (1995) found that the most effective collaborations were characterized by relationships that were mutually rewarding, equally valued, and based on similar and/or complimentary professional and social strengths and interests. All participants reported that the collaborative approach to supervision was worthwhile, although in the partnerships where the development of mutuality, trust, and friendship were at an early stage, teachers were less inclined to find or to make time to work with their partner or to focus on aspects of their teaching that involved risk-taking.<a href="#f">6</a></p>

<p>Levine (2011) proposed five features of professional communities that can help supervisors improve their work: norms promoting collaboration; trust and familiarity; activities deprivatizing practices; access to logistical information and shared expectations about the role of supervisors; and time for collaboration.<a href="#g">7</a></p>

<p>Nelson, Mary Lee, et al.(2008) believed in creating strong supervisory alliances, discussing evaluation early on, modeling openness to conflict, and providing timely feedback. Dependable strategies included contextualizing conflicts in light of developmental and environmental factors, seeking consultation with colleagues, self-coaching, processing conflicts, accentuating supervisee strengths, interpreting parallel processes, and withdrawing from supervisee dynamics.<a href="#h">8</a></p></blockquote>

<p>There were numerous instances of lost opportunities for student teachers to learn to teach, including sparse feedback on teaching subject matter and few links to methods courses, plus limited opportunities to develop identities as teachers. The structures that frame student teaching and its participants have deep roots in the cultures of universities and schools that must be considered if student teaching is to maximize its potential.<a href="#i">9</a></p>

<p>Summary of the characteristics of effective cooperation relationships: <br/>
1. mutually rewarding, equally valued, trust and familiarity, shared expectations about the role of supervisors; <br/>
2. modeling openness to conflict, feedback on teaching subject matter<br/>
3. time for collaboration</p>

<h3>From Supervisees' Perspective</h3>

<blockquote><p>Initial contract(non-tenured teachers) believed that the following variables influenced their reflection on practice: building trust, sharing the observation report, teacher’s focus for the lesson, constructive feedback, identified standards, sequence for conference, and areas for future growth. Yet tenured teachers only perceived two variables as influential on their reflection on practice: linking the post-conference to extended learning opportunities (professional development) and providing positive comments in the post-conference by the principal/supervisor. Analysis of open-ended items indicated that respondents valued trusting relationships, constructive feedback, reflection and areas of improvement as important elements of either conference.<a href="#j">10</a></p>

<p>BORKO and MAYFIELD (1995) recommended that university supervisors use their limited time in schools to help cooperating teachers become teacher educators. For example, they can model ways of observing student teachers and strategies for conducting conferences that focus on teaching and learning and help student teachers to become reflective about their practice. They also found that cooperating teachers who believed that they could and should play an active role in student teachers' learning, conducted longer and more frequent conferences with their student teachers, and provided more extensive feedback.<a href="#k">11</a></p>

<p>Supervisors who stress authority and identification of weaknesses build less trust than those who emphasize collegiality, productive diversity, and strengths.<a href="#l">12</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Summary of characteristics of effective supervisors:<br/>
1. providing timely feedback<br/>
2. constructive feedback<br/>
3. extended learning opportunities<br/>
4. use limited time to help cooperating teachers become teacher educators<br/>
5. emphasize collegiality, productive diversity, and strengths</p>

<h3>The best picture I can jigsaw based on these literatures.</h3>

<p>University professors should use their limited time to help cooperating teachers become teacher educators. Such as supervision and effective teaching class.</p>

<p>Cooperating teacher should play an active role using an indirect style in student teacher's learning with collaborative and trust relationships, timely positive feedback, openness to conflict, constructive suggestions and helpful learning opportunities or approaches.</p>

<p>Supervisees should be actively engaged, open minded, reflective in their process of learning to teach.</p>

<p>Facilitators:
Riordan, G. P. (1995) suggested that administrators should be aware of the extra difficulties partners may experience in working collaboratively; (2) administrators wishing to encourage collaborative clinical supervision partnerships to meet professional development goals should develop a system that allows teachers to have some input in the selection of partners, provide adequate time for conferencing, and notice and encourage teachers' collaborative efforts; (3) teachers wishing to develop relationships with their colleagues should be aware of the powerful norms of teacher autonomy and isolation;<a href="#m">13</a></p>

<p>Why supervision?<br/>
==>Value<br/>
==>Cost<br/>
==>DNA<br/>
==>Pedagogy<br/>
==>Content<br/>
==>Technology<br/>
==>Context</p>

<h3>Reference:</h3>

<h4><a id="#a">[1]</a> Stanulis, R. N., Little, S., &amp; Wibbens, E. (2012). Intensive mentoring that contributes to change in beginning elementary teachers’ learning to lead classroom discussions. Teaching and Teacher Education, 28(1), 32-43.</h4>

<p><a id="#b">[2]</a> Anthony Clarke,Valerie Triggs,Wendy Nielsen(2013) Cooperating Teacher Participation in Teacher Education:A Review of the Literature. REVIEW OF EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH September 23, 2013 0034654313499618<br/>
<a id="#c">[3]</a> Sim, C. (2010). Sustaining productive collaboration between faculties and schools. Australian Journal of Teacher Education, 35(5), 2.<br/>
<a id="#d">[4]</a> Acheson, K. A., &amp; Gall, M. D. (2003). Clinical supervision and teacher development. Wiley.<br/>
<a id="#e">[5]</a> Wortmann, Karly, et al.(2008). "Online Teacher Support Programs: Mentoring and Coaching Models." North American Council for Online Learning.<br/>
<a id="#f">[6]</a> Riordan, G. P. (1995). Teachers' Perceptions of Collaboration and Clinical Supervision.<br/>
<a id="#g">[7]</a> Levine, T. H. (2011). Features and strategies of supervisor professional community as a means of improving the supervision of preservice teachers. Teaching and Teacher Education, 27(5), 930-941.<br/>
<a id="#h">[8]</a> Nelson, Mary Lee, et al.(2008). "Working with conflict in clinical supervision: Wise supervisors' perspectives." Journal of Counseling Psychology 55.2, 172.<br/>
<a id="#i">[9]</a>  Valencia, S. W., Martin, S. D., Place, N. A., &amp; Grossman, P. (2009). Complex Interactions in Student Teaching Lost Opportunities for Learning. Journal of Teacher Education, 60(3), 304-322.<br/>
<a id="#j">[10]</a> Bret G. Range , Suzie Young &amp; David Hvidston (2013) Teacher perceptions about observation conferences: what do teachers think about their formative supervision in one US school district?, School Leadership &amp; Management: Formerly School Organisation, 33:1, 61-77, DOI:10.1080/13632434.2012.724670<br/>
<a id="#l">[11]</a> Borko, H., &amp; Mayfield, V. (1995). The roles of the cooperating teacher and university supervisor in learning to teach. Teaching and Teacher Education, 11(5), 501-518. <br/>
<a id="#l">[12]</a> Lyman, L. (1987). Principals and Teachers: Collaboration to Improve Instructional Supervision (Building Trust, Fostering Collaboration, Encouraging Collegiality).<br/>
<a id="#m">[13]</a> Riordan, G. P. (1995). Teachers' Perceptions of Collaboration and Clinical Supervision.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
