<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: list | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/list/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-11T13:30:41+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors for teaching and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T23:18:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Metaphors for teaching:</h3>

<p>A teacher is just like a cook. You can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes, so you can also tell a good teacher by his students' acheivements. Sometimes you can also tell a good cook by observing his cooking process. Good cook can aways get everything ready quickly and easily. Good teacher do the same thing.</p>

<p>Teachers' job is adapting the curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. Effective teachers are aware of what they are currently doing, aways pursueing new effecive ways to teach the same content. It is just like cooks making foods for different customers.  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Teachers' content knowledge affect their abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driving. The taxi driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/traffic-jam.png" alt="traffic jam" /></p>

<h3>Metaphor for education reform:</h3>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The teacher is like a swimmer in a river. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-is-swimmer.png" alt="teacher is swimmer" /></p>

<p>The science teacher educator stand on the river bank and tell the swimmer where to go, how to swim, which style is more effective than others. But the most important thing for a person in the river is to keep safty and the most reliable style is the style which he already got. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and new skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not always stand by but jump into the water and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A list of science labs that rocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T00:34:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will make a list of science labs activities which are so fun and interesting that you can't miss.</p>

<p>Real Labs<br/>
+   Mystery tube(modeling), see <a href="http://lasp.colorado.edu/home/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Mystery-Tube.pdf">lesson plan</a><br/>
观察和记录现象；根据现象猜想和建构模型；做出预期并验证模型；交流、修正和完善模型。<br/>
+   Candle in the tube above water(causal model)<br/>
+   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3600?ref=search">Transpiration lab</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/careerstart-grade8/5540">Cell theory and plant respiration G8</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/criticalthinking/6650">Water quality - Critical thinking in science</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3226?ref=search">Amazing amaryllis activitiesm G2-3 4Ws</a></p>

<p>Hands on activities<br/>
+   <a href="http://www.education.com/activity/article/Sourdough_bread/">Sourdough Science!</a><br/>
+   Making a safty harmer<br/>
+   Design a sprinkler head for watering lawn</p>

<p>Virual Labs/ Simulations<br/>
+   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
+   PhET: <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/">Free online simulations</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities/">Interactive simulation based inquiry activities - Chunlei's Blog</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modeling activities and reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T23:24:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I attended Dr Luft's class Methods of Science Teaching. I am becoming more and more interested in Modeling activities and I want to make a collection of these activities.</p>

<p>This is the list:<br/>
-   Candle in the water tube make it go out(Dr Luft's class)<br/>
-   Black box(<a href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=11102">How students learn: science in classroom</a> see Chp 12)<br/>
-   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
-   Mystery Tube (Dr C's class)<br/>
-   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
If you have more good modeling activities, welcome recommandations.</p>

<p>These activities provide lots of practice options for science teachers. We usually only provide standards of what students should master but little practice activites for teachers. Well, the <a href="http://www.nextgenscience.org/next-generation-science-standards">Next Generation Standard</a> is going to change this.</p>

<p>Reflections on Modeling in science teaching<br/>
The charm of modeling:<br/>
-   Naturally need students to make careful observation,recording data,drawing conclusions<br/>
-   Naturally engage students' prior ideas for explaination or application<br/>
-   Naturally put students into the test, debate and revisement of their models or prior ideas<br/>
-   Naturally let students experience the full process of science inquiry and nature of science</p>

<p>What to focus in the modeling activites as a science teacher?</p>

<p>How to keep the balance between knowledge-centered and student-centered? Individual and Community? Cognition and metacognition?</p>

<p>Welcome to join the discussion of these open questions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
