<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: pollution | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/pollution/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-25T11:38:38+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What are we throwing away?]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/01/what-are-we-throwing-away/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T13:28:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/01/what-are-we-throwing-away</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I watched two TED videos about plastic pollution. These two videos urge me to think what we are throwing away?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/van_jones_the_economic_injustice_of_plastic.html">Van Jones: The economic injustice of plastic | Video on TED.com</a></p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/van_jones_the_economic_injustice_of_plastic.html" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/capt_charles_moore_on_the_seas_of_plastic.html">Charles Moore: Seas of plastic | Video on TED.com</a></p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/capt_charles_moore_on_the_seas_of_plastic.html" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Only man can make products that can not be reused by other species; Plastic bottles are among these products. And most of the pollution industries keep running in developing countries cause the pollution standards are lower and the poor people need work to feed their families. But the pollution will destroy their land first and then the planet follows. No matter for the purpose of helping them or keeping ourselves safe, we all should do something to stop this, stop the throwaway economy.</p>

<p>One way is making zero pollution. Don't develop new pollution industries. Help and supervise our industries to achieve zero pollution.</p>

<p>Second, we should take measures to handle with our present pollution problems. Both the government and education should play a role. We are going to make our daily live zero pollution.</p>

<p>Third, all the countries on the world should collaborate. Many big challenges already laid in front of us. If we can not communicate and collaborate well, then the future of our earth is dim.</p>

<p>What are we throwing away? The plastic bottles? The seas of plastic? The living space and resources for next generations? Or our conscience as a human being and a member on earth?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
