<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: pictures | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/pictures/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-27T23:42:20+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some pictures of UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T20:56:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I went to the Main library of UGA. I had a task to search a journal from 1980 to 1990. It was my first time to be there. To my suprise, nobody stopped me to check my UGA card. So I just went around and check out the journels. It means everybody can come in and take a seat to read. It is great! The frist floor is very big and open. The book and magzines are located in the center, surrounded by many groups of tables, seats and computers. Although many students studying there, it was very quiet. I ask a library staff how to find the journal, he helped me to check it out in his computer and told me it is located at the second floor and it is also available online. So I just came out. It was at the noon, I took a picture of the main library, it is beautiful. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/library.jpg" alt="Main Library of UGA" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
I also found some interesting things at Aderhold where College of Education located. The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I entered the building in the morning, I found there were lots of names on the bricks. I guess there are the names of professors who had worked there. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/stopread.jpg" alt="Stop reading go to study" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/namebricks.jpg" alt="Name bricks in front of Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I kept looking, I saw a brick which said: "stop read the bricks, go to study". I smiled and entered the building.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
