<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: design | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-09T09:06:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[学习环境设计从课桌开始]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/learning-environment-observation-school-desk-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/learning-environment-observation-school-desk-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Boy-at-School-Desk.png" alt="Boy at school desk" /><br/>
今天突然注意到一个以前没有思考过的一个学习环境细节，似乎我们使用的课桌和Dr Luft教法课上的并不相同。不同的设计会产生哪些影响呢？</p>

<!--more-->


<p>下面是我们在大学和中学常用的课桌设计。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/school-desk.png" alt="Two traditional desk" /><br/>
这个是Dr Luft教法课上使用的课桌设计。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/movable-desk.png" alt="Movable desk" /><br/>
两者的差异就在于，一个容易移动和重新设计座位，一个更适合某种固定的座位排列方式。很显然我们的课桌设计不够灵活，这也为进行小组合作学习设置了潜在的障碍。</p>

<p>根据 Scott, Shaw, and McGuire (2001)提到的Universal Design的9条原则
  1) 均等使用（equitable use）, <br/>
  2) 使用灵活（flexibility in use）, <br/>
  3) 简单易懂（simple and intuitive）, <br/>
  4) 信息可感知（perceptible information）, <br/>
  5) 容忍错误（tolerance for error）, <br/>
  6) 低强度付出（low physical effort）, <br/>
  7) 大小和空间易用（size and space for approach）, <br/>
  8) 面向学习者群体（a community of learners）, <br/>
  9) 教学氛围（instructional climate）。</p>

<p>显然我们的课桌设计不符合第2）和7）条原则。</p>

<p>从课桌的设计可以看出，传统的课桌需求还占据着绝大部分市场分额，那么这又意味着什么？</p>

<p>我们要意识到一点，教学观念会印刻和反映在我们经常熟视无睹的设计当中，新课程改革需要我们重新设计我们的学习环境，同时我们也需要一批优秀的学习环境设计者。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for convinence for people]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/16/design-for-convinence-for-people/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-16T13:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/16/design-for-convinence-for-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most deep impressions I got of US is the pursuing of simple and comfortable life.</p>

<p>First is the bus design.<br/>
There is a button out side of the bus that customers can push to kneel the bus. Another design is that there is a string along the windows. You can pull the string to let bus stop. You don't even need to stand up.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing I discovered the yellow alert along the road. First I though it is to let people wark accross the street. But when I look into it carefully, It said "State law: stop when human on the line", it is for the car. No wonder evertime when I was on the line, the drive will stop let me pass first. What a nice law!  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/statelaw.jpg" alt="Statelaw" /><br/>
One day, when I was on my way home from supermarket, I found there is an American Bank ATM special for car drivers near the shops. I have never saw such ATM before in China. You don't have to get out of your car when you using the ATM In China, when you go to banks, usually you have wait for half an hour to get your turns in Shanghai. Why it is so different! This is a really good question to think about.</p>

<p>The last discovery is kitchen. They have kitchen not only in the apartment where I live but also in the office. There is a special kitchen room for professors and students to heat their lunch or make coffee. So nice!<br/>
Oh, I nearly forget. The water ﻿purifier﻿. It is so cool and useful, I love it too much.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/water.jpg" alt="water purifier" /></p>

<p>It is evident that the goal of American people is to pursue a simple and comfortable life. Maybe not very luxurious but comfortable.</p>

<p>How did they achieve that, market and competition may be the driving power. What it doesn't happen in China? Big question!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
