<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: design | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-11-02T10:10:48+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chinese Puzzle Pot design]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/19/chinese-puzzle-pot-design/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T14:46:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/19/chinese-puzzle-pot-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is an interesting class called Intro to the design of everything <a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/viewer#!/c-design101/l-300162902/e-441839145/m-438038764">link here</a></p>

<p>They showed a pot that can put in water by a hole at the bottom, and no water come out. It works well.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/chinese-puzzle-pot-photo.png" alt="Chinese puzzle pot photo" /></p>

<p>The following is one possible inner structure design in my mind.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/chinese-puzzle-pot-design.png" alt="Chinese puzzle pot design" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for better future]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T14:28:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I saw this in our main library when the staff cleanup the restroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/door-with-leg.png" alt="Door with leg" /><br/>
What a cool leg the door has! The idea is simple, but the result is so good. Sometimes simple change can make a big difference.</p>

<p>There also some design confuses me. Here is a table with sharp edge on the top surface. I really cannot understand what this edge serves for beyound hurting my arms when typing on my laptop.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/table-with-sharp-edge.png" alt="Sharp edge table" /></p>

<p>Another example of confusing design. I really don't know witch controler can light a fire to the stove under my pot.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/gas-stove.png" alt="gas stove" /></p>

<p>Nowadays, the environment is becoming worse and worse. One basic reason is bad design. Our company design good batteries with low-cost but ignored how to recycle and reuse the waste batteries. Similarly, the white pollution, air and water pollution all failded to take environment pollution cost into concern. These industries are all good examples of bad design and are badly need to change.</p>

<p>Well, how to solve these problems and create better future? The answer is design zero pollution industry pipeline. Just like the nature design all kinds of lives, no waste at all. For example, how to make use of clean energy as power for travelling. When you taking whole process into concern, you will find the horse and cart is one example of good designs. Of course, we will not return to this old method of travelling, but we really should rethink this design.</p>

<p>It is not just product design or pipeline design. It is also a life design. On behavior researcher found a very simple and effective way to save energy-- sending a letter of electric usage report comparing with neighborhood. After being told use more than twice electric than neighborhood, people tend to pay much attention to save energy. This is just how behavior science used to affect personal life styles.</p>

<p>Nowadays, people have learnt to make use clean energy such as wind, water,sun. Researchers are also trying to invent new technologies of producing and storing and converting these energy. We are going to and have to achieve no waste design in order to live a better life for long run on earth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[typing with sound]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/19/typing-with-sound/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T13:52:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/19/typing-with-sound</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nowardays people spend a lot of time in front of their computer. Most of the time they have to use their eyes whether they are typing or sufing on the internet.</p>

<p>But when you are using computer too much you will find your eyes hurt. Lots of students get short-sighted. A idea come to me, why not close my eye to type in front of a computer. Is it possible, may be ti is possible. So I try to find a sofware to help me to do this job. I find a one, and it works. Now I can sit in front of my computer and keep my eyes closed and typing wha I want to say. Isn't it amazing. This software will also help blind peaple to type, because it can sound the key so they can hear what they are typiing.</p>

<p>For me, it just helps to rest my eyes and concentrate on what I am writing.</p>

<p>This is not a new idea, but if is an intersting idea.</p>

<p>The above paragraph is written by me blindly.</p>

<p>Another idea interesting is using your left hand to control the mouse and use your right hand to click. This will help you to coordinate your left brain and right brain.</p>

<p>Now I am using the sound of pinyin to help myslef to type this paragraph. The pinyin sound help to pronounce a word when you are typing. It may not sound very right but it can do give a similar sound of the the word.</p>

<p>Is not it amazing.</p>

<p>(the following wrote by 2014/06/13)<br/>
I write of course with my eye open and without any sound. I confront the same problem again. I am wonderring what i can do with the mouse, computer interaction, becuase my fingers hurts when using mouse click too many times, I just wonder how this problem can be solved. I try to use both hands to use mouse, and now both my Forefinger hurts. Maybe I use computer too much. I admit that but there are also some problem with the design, the mouse design, or the user-computer interaction design. There are several ways to solve this problem:<br/>
1 redesign the mouse<br/>
2 redesign how computer react to the mouse<br/>
3 use keyboard instead of the mouse<br/>
4 forget the computer and use paper and pencil instead</p>

<p>The first two solutions are engineers and designers job.<br/>
The third is my job(the user habits)<br/>
The last one is not a solution for this problem but a solution for stopping the pain</p>

<p>continued on(2014/06/15)<br/>
I find out another solution already provided--but I did not discover before, using the touch pad of the computer. It is a solution,may be not perfect, because the user experience and the coceptural model is not what I want. It is also interesting that the user sometime ignore what had been provided.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laptop stand designed by myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-29T22:24:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is uncomfortable to work on my laptop on a table. Becuase the screen is too low and you have to bend your head which cause pain in the neck.<br/>
So I made a laptop stand using a useless shoes box. Here is the picture.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/laptopstand.png" alt="laptop stand" /></p>

<p>You can alway make a change if you want to. And small change can make a big difference sometimes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[学习环境设计从课桌开始]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/learning-environment-observation-school-desk-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T10:30:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/learning-environment-observation-school-desk-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Boy-at-School-Desk.png" alt="Boy at school desk" /><br/>
今天突然注意到一个以前没有思考过的一个学习环境细节，似乎我们使用的课桌和Dr Luft教法课上的并不相同。不同的设计会产生哪些影响呢？</p>

<!--more-->


<p>下面是我们在大学和中学常用的课桌设计。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/school-desk.png" alt="Two traditional desk" /><br/>
这个是Dr Luft教法课上使用的课桌设计。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/movable-desk.png" alt="Movable desk" /><br/>
两者的差异就在于，一个容易移动和重新设计座位，一个更适合某种固定的座位排列方式。很显然我们的课桌设计不够灵活，这也为进行小组合作学习设置了潜在的障碍。</p>

<p>根据 Scott, Shaw, and McGuire (2001)提到的Universal Design的9条原则
  1) 均等使用（equitable use）, <br/>
  2) 使用灵活（flexibility in use）, <br/>
  3) 简单易懂（simple and intuitive）, <br/>
  4) 信息可感知（perceptible information）, <br/>
  5) 容忍错误（tolerance for error）, <br/>
  6) 低强度付出（low physical effort）, <br/>
  7) 大小和空间易用（size and space for approach）, <br/>
  8) 面向学习者群体（a community of learners）, <br/>
  9) 教学氛围（instructional climate）。</p>

<p>显然我们的课桌设计不符合第2）和7）条原则。</p>

<p>从课桌的设计可以看出，传统的课桌需求还占据着绝大部分市场分额，那么这又意味着什么？</p>

<p>我们要意识到一点，教学观念会印刻和反映在我们经常熟视无睹的设计当中，新课程改革需要我们重新设计我们的学习环境，同时我们也需要一批优秀的学习环境设计者。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
