<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: metaphor | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/metaphor/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-09T01:11:25-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors for teaching and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T23:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Metaphors for teaching:</h3>

<p>A teacher is just like a cook. You can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes, so you can also tell a good teacher by his students' acheivements. Sometimes you can also tell a good cook by observing his cooking process. Good cook can aways get everything ready quickly and easily. Good teacher do the same thing.</p>

<p>Teachers' job is adapting the curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. Effective teachers are aware of what they are currently doing, aways pursueing new effecive ways to teach the same content. It is just like cooks making foods for different customers.  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Teachers' content knowledge affect their abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driving. The taxi driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/traffic-jam.png" alt="traffic jam" /></p>

<h3>Metaphor for education reform:</h3>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The teacher is like a swimmer in a river. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-is-swimmer.png" alt="teacher is swimmer" /></p>

<p>The science teacher educator stand on the river bank and tell the swimmer where to go, how to swim, which style is more effective than others. But the most important thing for a person in the river is to keep safty and the most reliable style is the style which he already got. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and new skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not always stand by but jump into the water and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The ways that content knowledge matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/the-ways-that-content-knowledge-matters/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T21:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/the-ways-that-content-knowledge-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Question:<br/>
What an expert teacher who has deep content knowledge can do?</p>

<p>Notes in class Supervision:<br/>
-give more proper instances, analogys to make student understand clearly<br/>
-relate the knowledge with students lives<br/>
-pick out the important big ideas that organizing the knowledge feild<br/>
-be able to emphasize crosscutting concepts
-be competent in science practices<br/>
-design more logical sequence of the content knowledge<br/>
-be able to understand students' difficulties and questions and has a clue</p>

<p>Additional ways(after class):<br/>
-ask good questions<br/>
-design sound learning activities and assignments<br/>
-have insights of students question or problems<br/>
-organize facts and concepts in a sense making way or framework<br/>
-have more backup examples,analogys, explainations, questions for use<br/>
-be confident to give students more opotions and more challeging jobs</p>

<p>In a word, content knowledge affect teachers' abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driver. The driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effective teaching notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T11:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was reading a book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a></p>

<p>The following are summary notes of Chapter 3 Using clinical supervision to promote effective teaching.</p>

<p>Characteristics of Good Teaching in Students' Mind?<br/>
Niss(Nice)<br/>
 *   Nice(respect, patient and easy to get along with)<br/>
 *   Interesting(makes subject interesting and fun with students engaged)<br/>
 *   Sense of humor(tell jokes and smiles a lot)<br/>
 *   Sensitive to students' need( Listent to students' question and make changes to help students learn )</p>

<p>Teacher characteristics associated with gain in students' academic achievement?<br/>
Creati<br/>
 +   Clarity<br/>
 +   Raise Variety(of materials, methods, question types and levels)<br/>
 +   Enthusiasm<br/>
 +   avoid harsh criticism<br/>
 +   Task-oriented<br/>
 +   Indirect teaching style</p>

<p>Substantive interaction that increase students' at-task time:<br/>
Equal<br/>
  -   Explain(content to students)<br/>
  -   questioning<br/>
  -   using feedback<br/>
  -   assistance<br/>
  -   list the steps or tasks(chunlei added)</p>

<p>Effective Classroom Preconditions:<br/>
Amazing
- Attention and motivation<br/>
- Meaningful(students can find personal meaning in the information being presented)<br/>
- Applications(opportunities to practice using new information)<br/>
- Include both lower-coginitive and higher-cognitive tasks or questions<br/>
- Group work process in the classroom</p>

<p>Notes taken from another book chapter-Glickman -chapter 4.pdf<br/>
Research on effective instruction() indicates that effective instruction is based on adaption of curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. In other words, effective teachers think about what they are currently doing, assess the results of their practice, explore with each other new possibilities  for teaching students, and are able to consider students' perspectives.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors of good teacher and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T22:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A good teacher just like a good cook. Of course, you can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes. So students' perfect performance is a good predictor of competent teacher. But it takes a lot effort to make the dishes OR evaluate the students. In fact, we can also tell a good cook by his preparation and operation of his cooking.  Good cook can aways make many dishes in a limited time. Because he don't stop, when heating the water, he is washing the vegatables or cutting the meat. When the water is ready he is also ready to fry them together. The teacher do the same thing in class expecially in a short class. I found this metaphor visiting Dr C's class, she give instructions as well as preparing the tools for modeling, at the same time she was also doing demonstration of what the secret tube behaviors.</p>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The science teacher is like a swimming player in a swimming poor. The science teacher educator stand beside and tell the player how to swim, which style is good which is bad. But the most important thing for a person in the swimming poor is to keep safty and the most reliable style is his primary style. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not stand by but jump into the swimming poor and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
