<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: metaphor | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/metaphor/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-27T19:58:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The metaphor of rock climbing]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/the-metaphor-of-rock-climbing/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T20:44:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/the-metaphor-of-rock-climbing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so hard to descibe how teacher develop related knowledge to teach a special topic.</p>

<p>I have come up with many analogies to assit my thinking and modeling of teacher knowledge development.</p>

<p>Here is another wonderful analogy Rock Climbing. The following is a picture:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/rock-climbing.png" alt="rock climbing" /><br/>
More about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_climbing#Crack_climbing">Rock climbing</a><br/>
The teacher developed lots of intermediate representations (just like the cracks, faces, slabs in rock climbing) to help students learning the scientific concept.</p>

<p>Good teacher can "see" the postions of students and can "arise" the right representation to help. The subject matter knowledge is the moutain. The "safety rope" is the good teacher-student relationship which keep the safe environment for learning. The routes can be fun and the goal can be challenging. They all motivates student to climb and learn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors for teaching and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T23:18:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/20/metaphors-for-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Metaphors for teaching:</h3>

<p>A teacher is just like a cook. You can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes, so you can also tell a good teacher by his students' acheivements. Sometimes you can also tell a good cook by observing his cooking process. Good cook can aways get everything ready quickly and easily. Good teacher do the same thing.</p>

<p>Teachers' job is adapting the curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. Effective teachers are aware of what they are currently doing, aways pursueing new effecive ways to teach the same content. It is just like cooks making foods for different customers.  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Teachers' content knowledge affect their abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driving. The taxi driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/traffic-jam.png" alt="traffic jam" /></p>

<h3>Metaphor for education reform:</h3>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The teacher is like a swimmer in a river. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-is-swimmer.png" alt="teacher is swimmer" /></p>

<p>The science teacher educator stand on the river bank and tell the swimmer where to go, how to swim, which style is more effective than others. But the most important thing for a person in the river is to keep safty and the most reliable style is the style which he already got. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and new skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not always stand by but jump into the water and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The ways that content knowledge matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/the-ways-that-content-knowledge-matters/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T21:16:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/the-ways-that-content-knowledge-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Question:<br/>
What an expert teacher who has deep content knowledge can do?</p>

<p>Notes in class Supervision:<br/>
-give more proper instances, analogys to make student understand clearly<br/>
-relate the knowledge with students lives<br/>
-pick out the important big ideas that organizing the knowledge feild<br/>
-be able to emphasize crosscutting concepts
-be competent in science practices<br/>
-design more logical sequence of the content knowledge<br/>
-be able to understand students' difficulties and questions and has a clue</p>

<p>Additional ways(after class):<br/>
-ask good questions<br/>
-design sound learning activities and assignments<br/>
-have insights of students question or problems<br/>
-organize facts and concepts in a sense making way or framework<br/>
-have more backup examples,analogys, explainations, questions for use<br/>
-be confident to give students more opotions and more challeging jobs</p>

<p>In a word, content knowledge affect teachers' abilities of transfroming the curriculum and materials to students in a special context to acheive a designed learning goal. It is the foundation of science teacher knowledge. If there is no good content knowledge, there is no good content to transform.</p>

<p>It is like the nutrition in the food, if the food contain no nutriton, the best cook can do nothing to help.</p>

<p>It is also like taxi driver. The driver who knows the traffic system well, is possiblely able to figure out the most quick way to go for you at a special time and location. Content knowledge just provide more pathes to consider and follow. Otherwise, it is easy to get lost and embarrassed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effective teaching notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T11:25:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was reading a book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a></p>

<p>The following are summary notes of Chapter 3 Using clinical supervision to promote effective teaching.</p>

<p>Characteristics of Good Teaching in Students' Mind?<br/>
Niss(Nice)<br/>
 *   Nice(respect, patient and easy to get along with)<br/>
 *   Interesting(makes subject interesting and fun with students engaged)<br/>
 *   Sense of humor(tell jokes and smiles a lot)<br/>
 *   Sensitive to students' need( Listent to students' question and make changes to help students learn )</p>

<p>Teacher characteristics associated with gain in students' academic achievement?<br/>
Creati<br/>
 +   Clarity<br/>
 +   Raise Variety(of materials, methods, question types and levels)<br/>
 +   Enthusiasm<br/>
 +   avoid harsh criticism<br/>
 +   Task-oriented<br/>
 +   Indirect teaching style</p>

<p>Substantive interaction that increase students' at-task time:<br/>
Equal<br/>
  -   Explain(content to students)<br/>
  -   questioning<br/>
  -   using feedback<br/>
  -   assistance<br/>
  -   list the steps or tasks(chunlei added)</p>

<p>Effective Classroom Preconditions:<br/>
Amazing
- Attention and motivation<br/>
- Meaningful(students can find personal meaning in the information being presented)<br/>
- Applications(opportunities to practice using new information)<br/>
- Include both lower-coginitive and higher-cognitive tasks or questions<br/>
- Group work process in the classroom</p>

<p>Notes taken from another book chapter-Glickman -chapter 4.pdf<br/>
Research on effective instruction() indicates that effective instruction is based on adaption of curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. In other words, effective teachers think about what they are currently doing, assess the results of their practice, explore with each other new possibilities  for teaching students, and are able to consider students' perspectives.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<p>The following was added at 2014/10/30
Evidence based Teaching notes<br/>
<a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Evidence_Based_Teaching.html?id=DZRhPQAACAAJ">Evidence-Based Teaching: A Practical Approach by Geoff Petty</a></p>

<p>==Expert teachers set challenging goals: deep learning==</p>

<p>==Expert teachers had very deep understanding of their subject  and the teaching and learning of the subject==</p>

<p>Their subject knowledge was more integrated, interrelated and built around general principles.</p>

<p>This deep learning enabled them to "make lessons uniquely their own by changing, combining, and adding to them according to their students' needs and their own goals".<br/>
p310</p>

<p>The expert teacher knowledge of the learning process was similarly deeper than that of experienced teachers. This enabled them to predict and avoid difficulties that students might have , and to see what was happening in their classrooms in terms of a deeper set of principles relating how students learn.</p>

<p>This mean that expert teacher were better able to diagnose what was happening in their classrooms, and to adapt. They were more responsive to their students as a result. The teaching and learning principles they used were probably something like those outlined  in Chapter 14.</p>

<p>==Expert teachers monitor learning and provide feedback==</p>

<p>Aim for evolution rather than revolution. Trying new methods one at a time is usually best, or your students will get unsettled even if you don't.<br/>
Teachers touch students' lives for ever - so it's worth the effort to make powerful methods work.</p>

<p>Graham Gibbs(1992)<br/>
action research approach advice:<br/>
Involve others<br/>
Identify the problem clearly<br/>
Use research evidence to convince others and to find promising strategies<br/>
Start where you can<br/>
Start small<br/>
Don't reinvent the wheel<br/>
Involve the students<br/>
Changes as you go along</p>

<p>p318</p>

<p>Review<br/>
we review our teaching in particular lesson or sequence of lessons, and look for evidence for what worked and what didn't.<br/>
Difficulties: Being brave enough to collect evidence that might be uncomfortable, andhones enough to face up to problems without blaming ourselves or our students</p>

<p>Learn<br/>
we try to lean from this review, not just what worked or didn't, but why. This creates general principles that we can apply elsewhere.<br/>
Difficulties: Asking 'why' persistently enough to enable us to lean the root cause of success or failure. Being able to 'bridge' this learning to other context by asking 'where else in my teaching could I use what I have just learned?'</p>

<p>Apply<br/>
We plan an experiment, perhaps adapting what we did in an earlier 'Do' phase.<br/>
Difficulties: Finding the courage, time and inclination to do things differently.</p>

<p>Do<br/>
we carry out our experiment. The cycle repeats.</p>

<p>p164<br/>
Seven principles common to high-quality leaning and achievement</p>

<p>1 student must see the value of the learning<br/>
2 students must believe they can do it<br/>
3 challenging goals<br/>
the goal involves student activity on constructive methods<br/>
the goal involves reasoning not just reproduction<br/>
high participation rate<br/>
students have their audience, variety and fun</p>

<p>4 feedback and dialogue on progress towards goal<br/>
students need 'medals' that give information about the extent to which they have achieved the goals<br/>
students need 'missions' that describe how to improve and progress<br/>
students need to develop a growing understanding of the goals</p>

<p>5 establish the structure of information and so its meaning<br/>
from known to unknown<br/>
from concrete to abstract<br/>
the structure first, then add the detail</p>

<p>6 time and repetition<br/>
multiple context: examples and non-examples in many different contexts in order to 'get' them
multiple perspectives: student need to see what they are leaning through different 'spectacles'. SOLO<br/>
multiple representations: right- and left-brain</p>

<p>7 teach skills as well as content</p>

<p>The PAR model<br/>
Present Apply &amp; Review</p>

<p>end notes</p>

<p>有趣的是，脑科学和认知科学也提出了若干原则和规律：<br/>
基于神经生物学研究的证据，Zull在2002年提出了3条规律：<br/>
1. 认识到情感因素的关键性作用。<br/>
2. 帮助学生建立自己掌控学习的感觉。<br/>
3. 学习必须基于自己已有的神经网络（已有知识），即使这个网络是错误的。</p>

<p>脑科学的研究发现，情绪是智慧的高级组织者，情绪能够指导认知进程和影响推理。例如长期高水平的皮质醇最终将导致与学习和记忆有关的海马神经元的损伤 ，即使是短时间的高水平皮质醇也会对短期记忆产生影响 。情绪对学习的影响具有两重性，轻松、愉快的情绪有利于学生的学习和健康发展，而过于紧张、沮丧、愤怒的情绪则不利于学生的学习。<br/>
此外无论是教育研究还是认知科学研究都显示，元认知的发展对于学习非常关键<br/>
学习者已有的知识对于学习有直接和重大的影响。学生并非头脑空空的来到教室，他们通过生活经验以及人际交流已经形成了很多概念和认识，这些概念或者完全错误，或者不完全，或者相对合理，不一而同，但是都对相关概念的学习有着重要的影响，科学教育研究者称之为前科学概念。而其脑科学的基础就是学生在已有的神经网络的基础上建造新的神经网络进而执行新的认知功能。</p>

<p>Boettcher2007年根据脑科学研究成果，提出的核心学习原则：
1：每一个结构化的学习经验都有四个元素（学习者、教师、知识、环境），它们以学习者为中心。
2：每一个学习经验都包括能够与学习者的相互作用环境。
3：我们塑造工具，工具也塑造我们。
4：教师是学习经验的导演。
5：学习者具有与该学习经验有关的个体知识、技能和态度。
6：学习者都具自己特定的最近发展区作为建构有用知识的基础。
7：概念并不是语句而是有组织的错综复杂的知识簇。
8：学习者都不需要学习所有内容，但是需要学习核心概念。
9：学习目标不同，所需教学也不同。
10：在其他条件一线的情况下，更多学习任务时间等价于更多的学习。</p>

<p>References:<br/>
Boettcher, J. (2007). Ten core principles for designing effective learning environments: Insights from brain research and pedagogical theory. Innovate: Journal of Online Education, 3(3), n3.<br/>
Zull, J. E. (2002). The art of changing the brain: Enriching the practice of teaching by exploring the biology of learning. Sterling, VA: Stylus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors of good teacher and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T22:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A good teacher just like a good cook. Of course, you can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes. So students' perfect performance is a good predictor of competent teacher. But it takes a lot effort to make the dishes OR evaluate the students. In fact, we can also tell a good cook by his preparation and operation of his cooking.  Good cook can aways make many dishes in a limited time. Because he don't stop, when heating the water, he is washing the vegatables or cutting the meat. When the water is ready he is also ready to fry them together. The teacher do the same thing in class expecially in a short class. I found this metaphor visiting Dr C's class, she give instructions as well as preparing the tools for modeling, at the same time she was also doing demonstration of what the secret tube behaviors.</p>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The science teacher is like a swimming player in a swimming poor. The science teacher educator stand beside and tell the player how to swim, which style is good which is bad. But the most important thing for a person in the swimming poor is to keep safty and the most reliable style is his primary style. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not stand by but jump into the swimming poor and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
