<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 评论 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/评论/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-25T23:56:43-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patent a special knowledge as private property]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/patent-a-special-knowledge-as-private-property/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-23T12:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/patent-a-special-knowledge-as-private-property</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why we introduces the idea of patent?<br/>
Patent is a commercial idea based on market. A patent is a limited property right the government gives inventors in exchange for their agreement to share details of their inventions with the public. Like any other property right, it may be sold, licensed, mortgaged, assigned or transferred, given away, or simply abandoned.<a href="#1">1</a> We can see the rationale of patent is to disclose the innovations to public domains for common good. What to do if patents are going to violate this original rationale? Should we still protect patents or abandon it?</p>

<p>What can be patented? What can't or shouldn't?<br/>
In order to apply for a patent the inventor should provide information about how to made and use this invention. Basically, this is a kind of knowledge about "how". So patent is both a special knowledge and a private property(intellectual property). Usually, a private property such as a chair is unique in the world and can not be given to others without losing it. But knowledge and information are different. We can transmit them without losing them. This is how education and media works. Patent means you can know it but you can't use it without license or permission. But people naturally can make use of their knowledge. It should be legal for people to make use of their knowledge to know and help themselves. So there is a question, should a special knowledge be patentable? <br/>
There is an interesting case about patent. Mr. Bowman bought gene-modified seed from Monsanto company to plant in his form. For that second crop, he bought seeds from a grain elevator filled with a mix of seeds in the reasonable hope that many of them contained Monsanto’s patented Roundup Ready gene.<a href="#2">2</a> Monsanto brought Mr. Bowman to the court for abuse of seeds with their patented Roundup Ready gene. Mr. Bowman argued that it is the natural right to make any use of the seeds that you bought. The patent should be in exhaustion when I bought the seeds from grain elevator.</p>

<p>But Mr. Bowman still lost the case. This is what Justice Kagan said:
“Under the patent exhaustion doctrine, Bowman could resell the patented soybeans he purchased from the grain elevator; so too he could consume the beans himself or feed them to his animals. But the exhaustion doctrine does not enable Bowman to make additional patented soybeans without Monsanto’s permission, that is precisely what Bowman did.” <a href="#3">3</a></p>

<p>There is another case, a farmer grow his corn in his form. But his neiborhood growed gene-moddified corn, by accident the wind blowed the pollen with modified gene to his farm. So his corn also had the modified gene. But the farmer planted corn for a Japan company that only want corn without moddified gene. So he can couldn't sell his corn to the company and lost lot of money. Who should pay for his lost?</p>

<p>Although, in this case, Mr. Bowman was intently to make use of the loophole of second buying. But it still annoy my nerves when thinking of gene-modified plant take the place of the other plants that farmers can grow and plant without any limitation, gene-modified food went into market without label, modified gene go to other plan species without control. A question emerged from this case is that Should gene be patentable?</p>

<p>How about human gene? Here is an interesting video "Who Owns You? 20% of the Genes in Your Body are Patented".<a href="#4">4</a></p>

<iframe src="http://zhangchunlei.com//player.vimeo.com/video/11755917" width="500" height="281" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This let me reflect the following questions: Should human gene be patentable? Will these patents prohibit us to know more about ourselves and make use our knowledge to benefit ourselves? Will this go against individual human rights? Is patent, or commercialization a good idea in education and human society in future?</p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a id="1">[1]</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent">Patent - Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</a></p>

<p><a id="2">[2]</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/16/business/supreme-court-to-hear-monsanto-seed-patent-case.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=0">Supreme Court to Hear Monsanto Seed Patent Case - NYTimes.com</a></p>

<p><a id="3">[3]</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/14/business/monsanto-victorious-in-genetic-seed-case.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1385229872-QGNdTtZez+JvcDHciXNSIg">Monsanto Victorious in Seed-Patent Case - NYTimes.com</a></p>

<p><a id="4">[4]</a> <a href="http://singularityhub.com/2010/08/11/who-owns-you-20-of-the-genes-in-your-body-are-patented-video/">Who Owns You? 20% of the Genes in Your Body are Patented | Singularity Hub</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[阅读立法还是阅读立项]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/14/reading-legislation-or-reading-program/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T17:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/14/reading-legislation-or-reading-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>前些日子阅读立法的事情引起了不少波澜。今天无意注意到UGA道路一角有一排类似垃圾桶的箱子，前面有个学生打开挡板取出一叠报纸边走边看。我也照样子拿了一叠报纸，一开始我还有点犹豫，是不是应该投币什么，但是仔细观察一番原来这是他们的一项免费阅读项目。真心觉得这样的项目也应该在国内多资助一些。</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/reading-program.jpg" alt="Reading Program Box" /></p>

<p>其实发现中国人阅读量不够，心里着急是国人爱国的表现。但是通过行政立法强制阅读其实是行不通的，最简单一条不具有操作性，你怎么检查呢，不读书你还拘留或者罚款吗，另外这样的立法是否有侵犯人权的嫌疑呢。但是如果真的要立法，其实倒是可以给机关、单位、组织立法，强制和支持开展一些阅读项目。比如开放全文数据库，开放大学图书馆，在乡村建设图书信息中心，在地铁提供报刊杂志，当然也需要所有人的配合，比如阅读完的杂志和报刊放回原位，或者在出站前放到指定位置。其实还真是大有可为的，做实事需要从小处着眼往往会更有效。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
