<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 反思 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/反思/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-08-01T11:09:35+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[做事的三明治法则]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/01/09/sandwith-style-working/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-09T08:55:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/01/09/sandwith-style-working</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>首先，做一件具体而简单的事</p>

<p>然后，做一件明确但是有挑战的事</p>

<p>再然后，做一件不明确但是简单的事</p>

<p>再然后，做一件不明确而且复杂的事</p>

<p>最后，做一件明确而简单的事</p>

<p>做事就好像我们吃三明治一样，容易拿在手上的面包放在两边，难拿的肉馅蔬菜放在里边。</p>

<p>这样做的好处是，容易形成积极的成功经验，有适当的缓冲，不容易望而生畏。</p>

<p>当然，最好的做事原则仍然是：要事第一。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[人生算法]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/01/05/life-algorithm/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-05T14:41:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/01/05/life-algorithm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>生命是一种形式的传承。一旦无法传承，就意味着生命的终结。而决定其命运的就是其核心算法。</p>

<p>生物如此，人也是如此。作为种族如此，作为个体也是如此。</p>

<p>1、做正确的事。<br/>
有人把成功的秘诀归结为一句话：做正确的事。找工作也好，找女朋友也好，创业也罢，要想成功就要能够在正确的时间、正确的地点、做正确的事。</p>

<p>现实是我们经常做错事儿，更糟糕的是做错了事还不自知。它就像一个牢笼，让你与成功失之交臂。</p>

<p>如何改变这种状态呢？这就需要改良你的人生算法。</p>

<p>2、人生算法<br/>
如果生命的本质是形式的传承，那么决定传承规律的就是生命的核心算法，它相当于你的DNA。实际上犯错并不可怕，世上没有人不犯错，关键是犯错能改。</p>

<p>因此能改和不能改才是关键。人的生命活动就是不断与外界环境交互的过程中迭代。有些算法会让你不断自我升级，有些算法则会让你沉入死循环。</p>

<p>那么，什么东西决定你自我迭代中能改还是不能改呢？答案是有目的行动。</p>

<p>3、有目的的行动<br/>
你可能会说，我做任何事情都是有目的的。事实可能的确如此，你追剧是为了娱乐和打发时间，你游泳是为了锻炼身体，你熬夜是为了赶工作，你查看朋友圈是为了增进友谊，但是你发现没有你做的诸多事情的目的是各不相同的，它们各自为政，甚至相互矛盾。在如今事情总是赶不完的情况下，如果你不会计划和选择，那么你将杂事缠身、迷失自我，更是达不到你自己的人生目标。因此，有目的的行动，统领自己的行为，并监控自己执行是一个非常关键而有挑战性任务。因为，你可能会随时被打扰、被中断、被牵绊、被拐骗，因此最重要不是管理时间，而是管理你自己，不是认识世界，而是认识你自己。</p>

<p>人人都以为这些都是自己能做主的，只要自己有决心就一定能行。但实际上，并不是如此简单。比如减肥就是一个最好的例子，有多少人能真正减肥成功的呢？但是不是我们就无所作为了呢，也不是，问题在于我们要找到自己的核心算法，找到算法的bug，然后再加以修正和完善，就好比基因治疗。</p>

<p>4、人生算法的套路<br/>
核心算法包含：目标选择、任务计划、执行策略、检验反馈。<br/>
APAF（Aim Plan Action Feedback）</p>

<p>目标：认识自我，找到真正想要的，才能做出正确的目标选择，活出自己的人生。</p>

<p>计划：设计可行的任务路径和计划，才能逼近目标直到目标达成。任务的可行性和灵活性是关键。</p>

<p>行动：在执行任务的时候，需要采用合理的策略应对自身和环境的变化。比如合适的自我监控机制和环境变化应对策略等。</p>

<p>反馈：明确目标达成的检验方法和反馈机制才能激励自己实现目标。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[有所不为]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/03/27/stop-doing-everything/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-27T21:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/03/27/stop-doing-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>事情是做不完的。</p>

<p>不要尝试做所有的事情。</p>

<p>紧急并不代表重要。</p>

<p>有所不为，才能有所为。</p>

<p>不是没有时间，是这件事不重要。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticism is not critical thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-19T19:45:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Tony asked our students to make up a skit to show their image of schooling. This activity provide opportunities for students to speak English and express their ideas or images of schooling which may be the first step to realize and change their own teaching perspective.</p>

<p>During the activities, an interesting phenomenon showed up. Most of them criticized the education they had in China. While,it was true that the Chinese education had many problems. But, the thinking and reasoning of the problematic educational phenomenon is shallow, or not deep enough, in other word, critical thinking is missing.</p>

<p>In order to get more from this activity, students should not jump up to conclusion too quickly. They should not ignore the context that these things took place, the social context, the historical context, the economic context, the physical context, and so on. They should also rethink the theories and rationals behind their judgement and carefully examine the proof and logic. In short, critical thinking should take the place of criticism.</p>

<p>Why harsh criticism of people's own education is not good even harmful? First, it easily leads to extreme and skin deep thinking which block more intellectual endeavor. Second, it hurt their self-image and self-confidence. Third, it can easily separate their connection with the previous themselves and places. Extreme criticisms call abandon or escape but not improvement and responsibility. Try to think of place-based learning, it heals the disconnection between people and places while harsh criticism do the opposite.</p>

<p>According to Daniel T. Willingham, critical thinking have three key features: effectiveness, novelty, and self-direction. Critical thinking is effective in that it avoids common pitfalls, such as seeing only one side of an issue, discounting new evidence that disconfirms your ideas, reasoning from passion rather than logic, failing to support statemnts with evidence, and so on.</p>

<p>Critical thinking is novel in that you don't simply remember a solution or a situation that is similar enough to guide you. Using a complex algorithm to solve a math problem is not critical thinking. But devising a new algorithm is. Critical thinking is self-directed in that the thinker must be calling the shot(making desicions themselves): awards or punishment will disrupt instead of promote critical thinking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[学问]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/16/xue-wen/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T13:04:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/16/xue-wen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>学问学问，有问耐学。问之而学之，学之而深问之。学而生问，问而新学。故无问则无学，无学则无问。问为学之始，学为问之门。</p>

<p>问天地之道，学万物之法。问宇宙之始，窥沧海之变。问处世之道，学入世之法。问世事之变，学为人之道。故有大问而后又大学，有大学而后有质问。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
