<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 反思 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/反思/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-14T12:08:23-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticism is not critical thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-19T19:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Tony asked our students to make up a skit to show their image of schooling. This activity provide opportunities for students to speak English and express their ideas or images of schooling which may be the first step to realize and change their own teaching perspective.</p>

<p>During the activities, an interesting phenomenon showed up. Most of them criticized the education they had in China. While,it was true that the Chinese education had many problems. But, the thinking and reasoning of the problematic educational phenomenon is shallow, or not deep enough, in other word, critical thinking is missing.</p>

<p>In order to get more from this activity, students should not jump up to conclusion too quickly. They should not ignore the context that these things took place, the social context, the historical context, the economic context, the physical context, and so on. They should also rethink the theories and rationals behind their judgement and carefully examine the proof and logic. In short, critical thinking should take the place of criticism.</p>

<p>Why harsh criticism of people's own education is not good even harmful? First, it easily leads to extreme and skin deep thinking which block more intellectual endeavor. Second, it hurt their self-image and self-confidence. Third, it can easily separate their connection with the previous themselves and places. Extreme criticisms call abandon or escape but not improvement and responsibility. Try to think of place-based learning, it heals the disconnection between people and places while harsh criticism do the opposite.</p>

<p>According to Daniel T. Willingham, critical thinking have three key features: effectiveness, novelty, and self-direction. Critical thinking is effective in that it avoids common pitfalls, such as seeing only one side of an issue, discounting new evidence that disconfirms your ideas, reasoning from passion rather than logic, failing to support statemnts with evidence, and so on.</p>

<p>Critical thinking is novel in that you don't simply remember a solution or a situation that is similar enough to guide you. Using a complex algorithm to solve a math problem is not critical thinking. But devising a new algorithm is. Critical thinking is self-directed in that the thinker must be calling the shot(making desicions themselves): awards or punishment will disrupt instead of promote critical thinking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[学问]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/16/xue-wen/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T13:04:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/16/xue-wen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>学问学问，有问耐学。问之而学之，学之而深问之。学而生问，问而新学。故无问则无学，无学则无问。问为学之始，学为问之门。</p>

<p>问天地之道，学万物之法。问宇宙之始，窥沧海之变。问处世之道，学入世之法。问世事之变，学为人之道。故有大问而后又大学，有大学而后有质问。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I ignored number five subconsciously]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/16/i-ignored-number-five-subconsciously/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T22:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/16/i-ignored-number-five-subconsciously</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A strange thing happend when I was reading a book and counting how many columns in a table. To my suprise, the number I counted in English didn't equal to the number counted in Chinese. In English the number is nine, but in Chinese it is eight columns. Finallly I found I missed the number five when I was couting in English. What a big discovery!</p>

<p>I don't know why I tend to ignore the number five subconsciously. But there was a real story about the number five. At that time, I was still a college student. Jelle and Ineke, friends of my advisor visited Beijing. It was their first time to be in the city, so I showed them around to visit temples, parks and other spots. We mainly took bus to travel cause it was cheap and we would have chances to experience the Chinese daily lives. One day, we were waiting for No 5 bus. My spoken English was not proficient and often make mistakes expecially in pronunciation. I said to Jelle we were going to take No 5 bus(but I pronunced like "No file bus"). But he didn't understand. I repeated but still didn't make sense. Then after a while, he understood and said No five. He even taught me how to pronunce it correctly. But I was very ashame of that, and still found it difficult for me to pronunce FIVE.</p>

<p>According to Freud's Unconscious theory, people tend to ignore or hide the unpleseant experience, this would help to explain my error in English counting.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[读《天眼》悬念小说所得]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2012/06/19/thoughts-on-reading-the-story-of-tianyan/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2012/06/19/thoughts-on-reading-the-story-of-tianyan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>《天眼》这篇小说围绕着&ldquo;盒子&rdquo;展开，故事情节跌宕起伏，用了一天时间一口气读完。虽然并应该花这么多的时间做这样的阅读消遣，但是奈何时间已经花费了，索性把自己的收获记录一番。</p>
<p>读过这篇小说，我在思考一个问题，如何写好故事？特别是如何写好教育故事和学习故事？作为教师或者学习者是否也可以写出类似引人入胜的故事？我想这种教育或学习过程的记录，同样也是问题解决的过程，同样能反映教学者或者学习者的所经所感，也就有机会反映和记录真实的专业成长过程或个人学习过程。</p>
<p>在经历了一次次劫难之后，潇伟和赵颖终于走到一起，有情人总成眷属，但也总会有不圆满，阿雪还是最后的任务中撒手人寰。经历了这么多的事情，主人公也再重新审视人生之意义，辗转几代人，几多英雄，几多磨难，到底为何执着。最后男女主人公又共同打开了雌匣，揭起新的不可预测的故事开端，笔锋戛然而止。</p>
<p>人生的重大问题永远值得思考：人生意义何在？如何找到自己真正按兴趣的事情？如何把自己感兴趣的事情做到最好？</p>
<p>但是答案却永远在变！</p></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[逃避与勇气]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2012/04/24/run-away-and-courge/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2012/04/24/run-away-and-courge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>人很容易逃避，有的时候是因为懦弱，有的时候是因为诱惑。 面对困难的时候，避重就轻是逃避；完成不了的时候寻找借口是逃避；沉迷于某事物而不能自控也是逃避。逃避很容易，直面困难往往需要真正的勇气。有的时候需要这种勇气是一刹那的决断，有的时候这种勇气是此志不渝的坚守，后者往往比前者更难。<br /><br />有的时候，想一想人活着一辈子到底追求个啥。不想这个问题是逃避，总想这样的问题也是逃避，只有偶然想一想，然后继续前行才是真理。<br /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
