<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: energy | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/energy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-23T17:34:09-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for better future]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T14:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I saw this in our main library when the staff cleanup the restroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/door-with-leg.png" alt="Door with leg" /><br/>
What a cool leg the door has! The idea is simple, but the result is so good. Sometimes simple change can make a big difference.</p>

<p>There also some design confuses me. Here is a table with sharp edge on the top surface. I really cannot understand what this edge serves for beyound hurting my arms when typing on my laptop.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/table-with-sharp-edge.png" alt="Sharp edge table" /></p>

<p>Another example of confusing design. I really don't know witch controler can light a fire to the stove under my pot.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/gas-stove.png" alt="gas stove" /></p>

<p>Nowadays, the environment is becoming worse and worse. One basic reason is bad design. Our company design good batteries with low-cost but ignored how to recycle and reuse the waste batteries. Similarly, the white pollution, air and water pollution all failded to take environment pollution cost into concern. These industries are all good examples of bad design and are badly need to change.</p>

<p>Well, how to solve these problems and create better future? The answer is design zero pollution industry pipeline. Just like the nature design all kinds of lives, no waste at all. For example, how to make use of clean energy as power for travelling. When you taking whole process into concern, you will find the horse and cart is one example of good designs. Of course, we will not return to this old method of travelling, but we really should rethink this design.</p>

<p>It is not just product design or pipeline design. It is also a life design. On behavior researcher found a very simple and effective way to save energy-- sending a letter of electric usage report comparing with neighborhood. After being told use more than twice electric than neighborhood, people tend to pay much attention to save energy. This is just how behavior science used to affect personal life styles.</p>

<p>Nowadays, people have learnt to make use clean energy such as wind, water,sun. Researchers are also trying to invent new technologies of producing and storing and converting these energy. We are going to and have to achieve no waste design in order to live a better life for long run on earth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
