<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 生活 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/生活/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-15T10:59:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[洞察力和问题解决]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2015/11/19/insight-and-problem-solving/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-19T09:54:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2015/11/19/insight-and-problem-solving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天去报销，报销是一件很耗时间的事，特别是在这个时间。到了财务处已经9点多了，外面一大堆人在排队拿号。看到这种情形我有点不知所措，我有一大堆票据，也有几张票据急需处理。于是我也来排队，排在最后面，前面有20人左右，但是队伍根本动不起来，我有些担心，因为一旦10点系统就不在吐号了。着急啊！有时着急也能急中生智。</p>

<p>我放弃了排队，跑到队伍前面拿票的地方看一看，原来号码有两种，一种是不限票据数据普通号，一种是发票不超过3张的快捷通道票。现在排长队的是拿普通号的，普通号已经被拿没了，所以只有等处理完一个，机器才会再吐号。但是快捷通道的号实际上还有剩余，我赶紧按了一下，取了一个，前面才有2个人，不一会就轮到我了，我把着急的票据处理了，问题解决，也不用再排队等了。</p>

<p>曾经读过一本书，叫《洞察力的秘密》，作者加里·克莱因基于上百个案例总结了洞察力的3个来源：急中生智，联系，自相矛盾。今天的事，好像就是急中生智的一个案例，实际上是走投无路，常规的做法就是排队拿号，但是这条路走不通，所以只好尝试其他途径。人们实际上常常会受到思维定势的影响，比如报销就是要排队拿号，而不去想排的是哪个队，只要有人在哪排，我也得去排。再有，就是抓不住主要问题，理想的情况下肯定是把所有票据都处理了会比较好，但是实际上更紧急的是把几张票据处理好。在接下来就是，利用规则。知道规则和合理利用规则不是一回事。恰当合理的利用规则，需要洞察力。</p>

<p>简单总结一下这次问题解决的关键: <br/>
1抓住关键问题；<br/>
2避免思维定势；<br/>
3巧妙利用规则。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A nice and hard trip]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/04/a-nice-trip-but-not-easy/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T16:43:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/04/a-nice-trip-but-not-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When My one-year long study life in US ended, I took a 10-days trip with my wife before returning to China. It was a impressive trip with both beautiful view and hardships on the road. I dislike surficial tours that can not let me understand more about the local people and culture. In this sense, the trip was worth the money, time and all the efforts.</p>

<p>We traveled mainly by taking Megabus, as college students or poor people did. We had lots of luggage, I know that we might get in trouble when taking buses, but I thought it would not be a big problem because I planned to pay more for the extra luggage. Everything wend very well before entering the Magebus. The city bus driver, a kind old black man, helped us pull the luggage. When I tried to give him tips, he denied. He said he helped us because he love Chinese and help us from heart not for money. He gave us a kindly smile and went back to his bus.</p>

<p>We arrived very early, so we had to wait for the megabus to arrive. It was our first time to take this kind of bus. At 3:40 PM, the megabus arrived. The driver was also a black man, but he was strong and a little fat. My wife stood most near the bus, but the drive said she was not standing in the queue, and let her to go back. We followed his directions, when it came to our turn he said you got too many luggage so you could not get on the bus. I said I could pay for the extra luggage. He said no no no. You could not pay me anything and ordered us to stand at the end of the queue.</p>

<p>After all the other passengers got on the bus, he told me that I could buy an extra ticket for the extra luggage but have to finish it in only 3 minutes. I became worried and nervous and a little angry. I worried that I couldn't catch the other magabus. I was a little angry because he already saw us with extra luggage 20 minutes before but only told us what to do when the bus was going to leave in 3 minutes. Another ridiculous thing he did was counting down when I was trying to call the company to buy an extra ticket. He was doing his job, but by no means trying to help. He seems want to bring shame on us on purpose just because we are Asian foreigners and bring two extra luggage.</p>

<p>After nearly 10 minutes, he seem enjoyed enough of the show he made, he let me get in the bus but never ask about the extra ticket. He seemed not care about the tickets at all. He did give some sarcastic remarks on this issue in his native English with black people's accent. All he said was how stickily he was following the rules of the company and it was all my fault that the bus was delayed. He let me sat on the steps beside him first and then separated me from my wife by asking me go upstairs(my wife sat at the first floor). First I went upstairs following his directions and then returned to the first floor by another ladders in the bus. My mood was terrible. My whole body was depressed and shaking. What kind of driver he was? I don't know. I also can't understand.</p>

<p>The trip had to be continued. By any means, it was not a good start.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go the big pool forget the small one]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/21/go-the-big-pool-forget-the-small-one/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-21T12:25:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/21/go-the-big-pool-forget-the-small-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so amazing to swim in the big pool; You are just like a fish swimming in the ocean. The water is clear; you can see everything in the water. It also takes less effor swimming in a big pool; you swim faster and faster with passion. Forget the small pool, come to this one.</p>

<p>It usually opens from 11 AM to 1 PM during weekdays. Enjoy it and have fun!</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/uga-swimming-pool.png" alt="UGA Swimming Pool" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lost in local extrema]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T11:28:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love this place, the library at the second floor in Aderhold Building. I love this table, which is not too big but just enough. This love can guide me back home.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/simple-desk.png" alt="simple desk" /></p>

<p>I lost myself sometimes in some very narrow area. People may ignore the whole when they are attracted and trapped by them. It can be power, It can be sex, It can also be anger and violence.</p>

<p>A picture comes to my mind when I am thinking of these dangerous Local Extrema---the local extrema. I frist notice this phenomenion in NG's machine learning class. This is the picture that he used to show local extrema. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/local-extrema.png" alt="local extrema" /></p>

<p>When the computer only have one seed, it is very likely trapped in a local extrema and return a wrong answer. It is just like a person who lost himself when he try to reach the extrema unrealized that it is only the local extrema.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[痔疮高发的原因]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/21/what-causes-hemorrhoids/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-21T20:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/21/what-causes-hemorrhoids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>现代人群中痔疮高发，这与生活方式直接相关，如果能够养成健康的生活方式或者知道缓解的办法，可以在很大程度上避免发病和缓解症状。</p>

<h3>痔疮的形成</h3>

<p>在肛管的粘膜下有一层肛管血管垫，简称“肛垫”。起闭合肛管、节制排便作用。正常情况下，肛垫疏松地附着在肛管肌上，排便后借其自身的收缩作用，缩回到肛管内。当弹性回缩作用减弱后，肛垫则充血、下移形成痔。</p>

<h3>导致痔疮的外部原因</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>马桶使用错误<br/>
调查显示城市痔疮发病率要比农村高，究其原因其实是马桶惹得祸。使用马桶时，如果坐姿向后，会使得肛垫受到更大的压力，从而下坠形成痔。缓解的办法是，使用马桶时身体前倾，让腿部帮助承担一定的压力，防护肛垫受力过大。</p></li>
<li><p>久坐和超重<br/>
现代人，特别是白领一族经常久坐在电脑前面，在加上工作压力和体重问题，都是使得痔疮的发病率增加。建议每三十分钟起身一次，适当运动一下。再或者改变坐姿，变坐为站、趟、跪等。另外要避免坐凉凳子。</p></li>
<li><p>擦拭过重</p></li>
<li><p>怀孕和分娩</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>缓解的办法</h3>

<p>当发生痔疮时，如大便出血或者肛垫下垂。缓解的方法包括：<br/>
避免坐凉凳子，冬天使用坐垫。<br/>
每天洗热水澡。<br/>
多吃蔬菜等顺肠食物，防止便秘。<br/>
及时到医院诊断和治疗，防止恶化。</p>

<p>参考：<br/>
痔疮_百度百科：[http://baike.baidu.com/view/6945.htm]
Hemorrhoids.org: Hemorrhoids Cause[http://www.hemorrhoids.org/hemorrhoids-cause.html]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
