<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 生活 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/生活/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-22T11:40:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go the big pool forget the small one]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/21/go-the-big-pool-forget-the-small-one/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-21T12:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/21/go-the-big-pool-forget-the-small-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so amazing to swim in the big pool; You are just like a fish swimming in the ocean. The water is clear; you can see everything in the water. It also takes less effor swimming in a big pool; you swim faster and faster with passion. Forget the small pool, come to this one.</p>

<p>It usually opens from 11 AM to 1 PM during weekdays. Enjoy it and have fun!</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/uga-swimming-pool.png" alt="UGA Swimming Pool" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lost in local extrema]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T11:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love this place, the library at the second floor in Aderhold Building. I love this table, which is not too big but just enough. This love can guide me back home.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/simple-desk.png" alt="simple desk" /></p>

<p>I lost myself sometimes in some very narrow area. People may ignore the whole when they are attracted and trapped by them. It can be power, It can be sex, It can also be anger and violence.</p>

<p>A picture comes to my mind when I am thinking of these dangerous Local Extrema---the local extrema. I frist notice this phenomenion in NG's machine learning class. This is the picture that he used to show local extrema. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/local-extrema.png" alt="local extrema" /></p>

<p>When the computer only have one seed, it is very likely trapped in a local extrema and return a wrong answer. It is just like a person who lost himself when he try to reach the extrema unrealized that it is only the local extrema.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[痔疮高发的原因]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/21/what-causes-hemorrhoids/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-21T20:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/21/what-causes-hemorrhoids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>现代人群中痔疮高发，这与生活方式直接相关，如果能够养成健康的生活方式或者知道缓解的办法，可以在很大程度上避免发病和缓解症状。</p>

<h3>痔疮的形成</h3>

<p>在肛管的粘膜下有一层肛管血管垫，简称“肛垫”。起闭合肛管、节制排便作用。正常情况下，肛垫疏松地附着在肛管肌上，排便后借其自身的收缩作用，缩回到肛管内。当弹性回缩作用减弱后，肛垫则充血、下移形成痔。</p>

<h3>导致痔疮的外部原因</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>马桶使用错误<br/>
调查显示城市痔疮发病率要比农村高，究其原因其实是马桶惹得祸。使用马桶时，如果坐姿向后，会使得肛垫受到更大的压力，从而下坠形成痔。缓解的办法是，使用马桶时身体前倾，让腿部帮助承担一定的压力，防护肛垫受力过大。</p></li>
<li><p>久坐和超重<br/>
现代人，特别是白领一族经常久坐在电脑前面，在加上工作压力和体重问题，都是使得痔疮的发病率增加。建议每三十分钟起身一次，适当运动一下。再或者改变坐姿，变坐为站、趟、跪等。另外要避免坐凉凳子。</p></li>
<li><p>擦拭过重</p></li>
<li><p>怀孕和分娩</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>缓解的办法</h3>

<p>当发生痔疮时，如大便出血或者肛垫下垂。缓解的方法包括：<br/>
避免坐凉凳子，冬天使用坐垫。<br/>
每天洗热水澡。<br/>
多吃蔬菜等顺肠食物，防止便秘。<br/>
及时到医院诊断和治疗，防止恶化。</p>

<p>参考：<br/>
痔疮_百度百科：[http://baike.baidu.com/view/6945.htm]
Hemorrhoids.org: Hemorrhoids Cause[http://www.hemorrhoids.org/hemorrhoids-cause.html]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[如何用微波炉煮米饭]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/16/how-to-cook-rice-with-microwave/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T20:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/16/how-to-cook-rice-with-microwave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>准备：<br/>
可以在微波炉里加热的乐扣<br/>
-  米
-  准备完毕</p>

<p>加料：<br/>
-  根据饭量加米<br/>
-  加双倍的水</p>

<p>加热：<br/>
-  首先最高档加热4分钟<br/>
-  放置10分钟<br/>
-  用中档（后者6）加热15分钟</p>

<p>取出：<br/>
-  乐扣盖子上有热水，不宜立即取出<br/>
-  待略微冷却后，取出，米饭温度适宜后即可食用</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some pictures of UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I went to the Main library of UGA. I had a task to search a journal from 1980 to 1990. It was my first time to be there. To my suprise, nobody stopped me to check my UGA card. So I just went around and check out the journels. It means everybody can come in and take a seat to read. It is great! The frist floor is very big and open. The book and magzines are located in the center, surrounded by many groups of tables, seats and computers. Although many students studying there, it was very quiet. I ask a library staff how to find the journal, he helped me to check it out in his computer and told me it is located at the second floor and it is also available online. So I just came out. It was at the noon, I took a picture of the main library, it is beautiful. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/library.jpg" alt="Main Library of UGA" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
I also found some interesting things at Aderhold where College of Education located. The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I entered the building in the morning, I found there were lots of names on the bricks. I guess there are the names of professors who had worked there. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/stopread.jpg" alt="Stop reading go to study" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/namebricks.jpg" alt="Name bricks in front of Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I kept looking, I saw a brick which said: "stop read the bricks, go to study". I smiled and entered the building.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
