<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 生活 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/生活/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-31T12:47:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some pictures of UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I went to the Main library of UGA. I had a task to search a journal from 1980 to 1990. It was my first time to be there. To my suprise, nobody stopped me to check my UGA card. So I just went around and check out the journels. It means everybody can come in and take a seat to read. It is great! The frist floor is very big and open. The book and magzines are located in the center, surrounded by many groups of tables, seats and computers. Although many students studying there, it was very quiet. I ask a library staff how to find the journal, he helped me to check it out in his computer and told me it is located at the second floor and it is also available online. So I just came out. It was at the noon, I took a picture of the main library, it is beautiful. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/library.jpg" alt="Main Library of UGA" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
I also found some interesting things at Aderhold where College of Education located. The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I entered the building in the morning, I found there were lots of names on the bricks. I guess there are the names of professors who had worked there. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/stopread.jpg" alt="Stop reading go to study" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/namebricks.jpg" alt="Name bricks in front of Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I kept looking, I saw a brick which said: "stop read the bricks, go to study". I smiled and entered the building.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to make Chinese Pancakes]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/how-to-make-chinese-pancakes/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T16:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/how-to-make-chinese-pancakes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Look at the Slide I made by Prezi:</p>

<iframe src="http://prezi.com/embed/ggepqlbagskh/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;features=undefined&amp;disabled_features=undefined" width="550" height="400" frameBorder="0"></iframe>


<p></p>

<p>Prezi is free, and this is my invitation code: <a href="http://prezi.com/recommend/uoexcohw4ztz/">http://prezi.com/recommend/uoexcohw4ztz/</a><br/>
上面的连接是我的邀请码，可以免费注册prezi。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[宝宝跳跳器——脚手架]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2012/04/26/baby-jump-helper-scaffolding/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2012/04/26/baby-jump-helper-scaffolding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><div align="center"><img style="max-width: 800px;" src="http://img.pconline.com.cn/images/upload/upc/tx/babylib/1006/30/11/33/1277890659953_300x300.jpg" /><br /></div><br /><blockquote><p><font size="2"><span style="font-family: arial,helvetica,sans-serif;">“跳跳器是一种悬挂在门框金属夹具上的塑料椅或布椅。它由链条、弹簧或橡胶和布带构成。宝宝在上面跳起，就可以弹离地面。一些宝宝不喜欢跳跳器，而其他宝宝却很喜爱，直到学会走路。</span></font></p><p><font size="2"><span style="font-family: arial,helvetica,sans-serif;">跳 跳器也有一些问题：夹具可能会松开，带子可能会磨断，从而导致宝宝掉到地上或撞到门框。一些座椅对宝宝的大腿内侧压力过大，导致瘀痕或影响血液循环。安装 跳跳器也具有一定的难度。宝宝长时间使用会导致晕眩，症状与晕船相似。同时还有鞭抽式损伤的危险，因此我们不提倡使用跳跳器。” 摘自：怎样为刚刚学走路的孩子选择用具？ 博闻网: http://health.bowenwang.com.cn/how-to-choose-baby-equipment8.htm</span></font></p></blockquote>今天偶然在路上可到有一个家庭正在给宝宝使用跳跳器，这让我联想到脚手架的原理。宝宝在还没有学会走路的时候，家长有时候会用双手架在宝宝的腋下帮助其承担一部分的重量，这样宝宝就可以在双腿力量上不足够支撑身体重量的时候学习走路，这更我们的脚手架原理是一样的，学习者在教师提供特定帮助下完成学习任务，然后这种帮助会慢慢减少，直到学习者可以独立完成任务。<br /><br />这正应了那句名言“教是为了不教”。<br />还有一句是“不教也是一种教”。<br /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[从宫廷剧能看到什么]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/12/27/what-to-learn-from-court-drama/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/12/27/what-to-learn-from-court-drama</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p><a href="http://list.iqiyi.com/www/2/-139-----------5-1-1-1---.html">宫廷剧</a>一部接着一部，一集接着一集，大有主导电视剧市场的趋势，这意味着什么？</p></p>




<p><p>最近看了几集《甄嬛传》，只是看了开头，中间几集以及结尾，70多集每集都看实在是看不过来。电视剧的情节很是吸引人，演员也不是演的不好，但是静下心来想一想，宫廷剧这种封建社会畸形人际关系实在是看多无益。而且这种封建的君臣思想以及后宫的明争暗斗都让人感到压抑、冷漠，不知道观众看到的是“皇帝的龌龊”还是“智慧”，是甄嬛的“顺应”还是“抗争”，总是觉得宫廷剧题材实在是憋闷，角色无非是皇帝、皇宫的女人、太监、医生，就像八股文，演来演去还是那些争斗，人性的负面体现的淋漓尽致，但主体性、创造性荡然无存。</p></p>




<p><p>如今的中国应该说正处于剧烈的社会经济变革之中，很多社会经济问题都是非常好的电视剧、电影题材，但是为什么没有更多的拍出来呢？</p></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[会心跳的空调]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/11/30/the-heart-beat-of-airconditioner/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/11/30/the-heart-beat-of-airconditioner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>今天天气不好，一直下着小雨，雨不是很大，但是借着较强的风势，横飞乱舞，打着伞身子也会被淋湿了一半。回到家，坐在办公桌前面打开电脑，正准备做一个flash演示文稿模板，突然听到一种很奇怪的声音，嘭~啪~嘭~啪~，周而复始，有点像流水的声音，又好像似一个人的心跳，但是家里明明只有我一个人。<br /><br />于是仗着胆子站起身来，细听声音的来处，原来就是侧对着办公桌的哪个空调发出的声音。好奇怪啊，这个空调明明没有开，怎么会有声音呢。外面的风刮的更厉害了，又传来了嘭啪嘭啪的声音，于是猜想是不是与这风有关系呢？本来想静下来做点事情的，这个空调老是给我执照噪音怎么行呢，于是就开始想解决的办法。<br /><br />我猜想可能是风速变化很大，时快时慢，使得空调的循环管受的压力不断变化，进而造成里面的液体的震荡所以产生了这种类似“心跳”的声音。加入这种猜想成立的话，如何解决呢? 首先想到的是用一个大塑料袋子把空调的风扇整个包起来来，这样这个风扇的管道就不对外开放了，但是找了一会没找到合适的袋子，而且风扇在阳台栏杆的外面，需要越过栏杆才能将其罩住，栏杆很脏，而且有一定危险性，于是放弃了这种方法。那么怎么办呢？<br /><br />仔细想了一下，由于天气有点冷，房子的门窗都关着，整个房子就好像一个秘密的容器，只有空调的循环管与外面相连，由于风速变化造成压力变化，所以会传来空调的心跳声。对了，如果我在打开一个通道不久行了嘛，于是我就把阳台的拉门打开了，果然空调的心跳停下来了，问题解决！<br /><br /><br /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
