<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 教学设计 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/教学设计/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-02T14:30:31+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教学设计——自查向导]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/12/02/instruction-design/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T12:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/12/02/instruction-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>前两天读了李敬忠老师的博文<a href="http://blog.163.com/lijingzhong4170977@126/blog/static/112426349201498102641197">以“学”为中心的教学设计实施流程</a>，很有感触，于是把博文中的一些教学设计时应该仔细思考的问题梳理了一下，并做了一些补充，姑且称之为“自查向导”，希望能有助于准教师和新教师对教学设计的反思和革新。</p>

<p>目标三问：<br/>
1、学生为什么要学这个内容，学了有什么用?<br/>
2、对于这个内容，学生原有的基础是什么?<br/>
3、这节课中，我希望学生在原有基础上有怎样的发展?</p>

<p>内容三问：<br/>
1、这节课中什么内容对学生是有价值的?<br/>
2、学生主要的精力应该放在什么内容上?<br/>
3、什么内容对学生的生活和今后的发展更有意义?</p>

<p>学生三问：<br/>
1、学生对这个内容的兴趣如何？<br/>
2、学生有哪些相关的概念和生活经验，会促进或阻碍学习？<br/>
3、学生必须具有哪些知识、技能准备，才能达成学习目标？</p>

<p>教学过程三问：<br/>
1、重点、难点在哪？<br/>
2、时间该如何分配？<br/>
3、用怎样的策略、方法、媒体开展教学？</p>

<p>学习任务三问：<br/>
1、任务如何设计才能有趣味性和挑战性，促进参与并反馈学习情况？<br/>
2、任务如何设计才有助于学生掌握重点、突破难点？<br/>
3、任务如何设计才能让各环节过渡自然、思路清晰？</p>

<p>课前自查：<br/>
（1）这样的执教思路是否足够清晰?在课堂实施时学生能理解吗?<br/>
（2）我会不会讲得太多?学生会不会思考得太少、动手得太少、体验得太少?<br/>
（3）有给学生思考的余地吗?这样的设计是否会代替学生思考?<br/>
（4）学生上课时会感到愉悦吗?有兴趣吗?<br/>
（5）这样的设计在课堂实施后，学生能否会用所学技术和方法解决实际问题?<br/>
（6）我有没有非常认真地操作过所有的课堂任务?<br/>
（7）学生可能会出现的问题预估到了吗?</p>

<p>课后反思：<br/>
（1）是否完成了预设的教学目标?<br/>
（2）学生上课兴趣怎么样?他们有没有进行真正深入的思考和主动学习?<br/>
（3）课堂出现的哪些问题是自己预设不足而导致的?<br/>
（4）各环节有没有需要改进的地方?<br/>
（5）课堂的结构、任务的设置、时间的分配是否需要调整?<br/>
（6）哪些任务学生没有完成或者做好?原因是什么?<br/>
（7）知识点讲解、语言表述（问题、例子、比喻）等是否简洁、清晰、易懂?</p>

<p>如实记录在博客或者word文档中以备日后教学参考完善。</p>

<p>参考：
以“学”为中心的教学设计实施流程 - 李敬忠的日志 - 网易博客
http://blog.163.com/lijingzhong4170977@126/blog/static/112426349201498102641197</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lesson plan of cell structure]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-16T11:05:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/16/lesson-plan-of-cell-structure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Topic: Cell structure/Biology<br/>
Designer: <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/about/">Chunlei Zhang</a><br/>
Student: High school students<br/>
Notes: This is just an imaginary teaching learning scenario sequences.</p>

<p>Imagine a house in your mind(or you can draw it), maybe your family house, maybe not. What does it look like from outside? What about the look of inside? What is the house composed of? What is the function of each part? Can you ask more questions about house?( who made them? which style? what is it made of? how to make a house?) cool!</p>

<p>Today we are going to study cell,similar with house, you can imagine cell as a house for a new strange life. You can ask any questions you want? (list students questions)</p>

<p>Some of your questions, scientists have answered? some question still need further inquiry.</p>

<p>Do you know why scientists study cell?(R or NR) They want to know more about life, an essential question is "What is life is made of?" They finally found the answer through a special equipment -- microscope. Their finding suggest that most organism are made of cell. There is a story of discovery of cell.(telling the story)</p>

<p>Cell are usually very very small, and invisible to the naked eye. Do you have any experience of bleeding? What is the color of blood? If you take out of the blood cells, then it looks like this.[picture] What can you infer from this picture? If you look at blood through microscope, then you can see this. These are blood cells. If you look at the blood vessel, you will see this.(video) Not only blood, every parts of your body is made of cells.(student can also draw this conclusion by observing the picture of different tissue are made of different types cells)</p>

<p>Can you guess what is inside of a cell?(Predicted answers: empty, just water or solution, there must be some structures inside)</p>

<p>If we use electron microscope, then we can see the inside structure of the cell. Here is some pictures, try to build a cell structure model as a group. You can number different structures.</p>

<p>When the structures were first discovered by scientist, they also found it hard to communicate, so they name them. Sometime they name them by their characteristics, sometimes using the scientist's name. (give the names of different structure) Can you distinguish the different structures inside a cell? Have a try in your group.</p>

<p>Group assessment, show Simulation and let students guess what is the structure and its possible function.</p>

<p>How the different structures relate with each other? We don't know. What do you suggest, if you are going to study this research question.</p>

<p>Scientists got these pictures, when they study how proteins are made and transported outside of cells.[three pictures]</p>

<p>What can you see in these pictures? What can you infer? Can you guess or infer the functions of different structures? How do they function together in this process?</p>

<p>Home work: Make a cell structure model that can represent all your group knowledge about cell. We will share and discuss our models in next lesson.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
