<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 日志 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/日志/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-09T17:37:08-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The beautiful leaves on the tree]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/19/the-beautiful-leaves-on-the-tree/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-19T16:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/19/the-beautiful-leaves-on-the-tree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/autumn-tree.jpg" alt="autumn-tree.jpg" /></p>

<p>On a grassy lawn near the road, standed a little girl about five years old. She was looking up at the colorful tree leaves and jumping to reach them. She jumped up using all her energy but found herself still get nothing.</p>

<p>I walked close to the girl-she was really a beautiful angel.</p>

<p>"Do you need help?" I asked.<br/>
She stared at me with her shinning black eyes without saying a word.<br/>
"Do you want some leaves? I can help!" I repeated. <br/>
"No" she answered. <br/>
"I can use the ball." She fetched a ball from the ground just several steps away.<br/>
"then the leaves will fall."<br/>
"You are very clever!" I said.<br/>
After I left, she began throw the ball up to the leaves again and again - very exitedly.</p>

<p>Well, she may never heared of the term "gravity", but she do have been aware of it and even make use of it to get the beautiful leaves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swimming pool finally found in Remsey Center]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/swimming-pool-finally-found-remsey-center/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T18:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/swimming-pool-finally-found-remsey-center</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally find a swimming poor that I can have access in UGA. It is in the Remsey Center just take the next stop of Aderhold by East-West School Bus. I purchased a membership for three months($15 per month). Today I went there to work out and swim. It is really worth every cents.</p>

<p>I took several pictures:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/work-out.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I often see people running on the road to do exercise. Sometimes man, sometimes old men stripped to the waist, sometimes women with young boy or girls. In fact, the road in Athens are not flat, so they have to run up and down. They really got the admirable sport spirits.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>
The following is a picture of the swimming pool taken from a window.  The water is blue and there many students swimming like fish in the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/swimming-pool.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Today the climbing wall is open for free. It will be one day for free per month. So if you want to try, don't miss the boat. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/climbing-wall.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I am too tired after swimming to try it. May be next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for convinence for people]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/16/design-for-convinence-for-people/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-16T13:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/16/design-for-convinence-for-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most deep impressions I got of US is the pursuing of simple and comfortable life.</p>

<p>First is the bus design.<br/>
There is a button out side of the bus that customers can push to kneel the bus. Another design is that there is a string along the windows. You can pull the string to let bus stop. You don't even need to stand up.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing I discovered the yellow alert along the road. First I though it is to let people wark accross the street. But when I look into it carefully, It said "State law: stop when human on the line", it is for the car. No wonder evertime when I was on the line, the drive will stop let me pass first. What a nice law!  <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/statelaw.jpg" alt="Statelaw" /><br/>
One day, when I was on my way home from supermarket, I found there is an American Bank ATM special for car drivers near the shops. I have never saw such ATM before in China. You don't have to get out of your car when you using the ATM In China, when you go to banks, usually you have wait for half an hour to get your turns in Shanghai. Why it is so different! This is a really good question to think about.</p>

<p>The last discovery is kitchen. They have kitchen not only in the apartment where I live but also in the office. There is a special kitchen room for professors and students to heat their lunch or make coffee. So nice!<br/>
Oh, I nearly forget. The water ﻿purifier﻿. It is so cool and useful, I love it too much.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/water.jpg" alt="water purifier" /></p>

<p>It is evident that the goal of American people is to pursue a simple and comfortable life. Maybe not very luxurious but comfortable.</p>

<p>How did they achieve that, market and competition may be the driving power. What it doesn't happen in China? Big question!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fighting with the imaginary enemy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/10/fighting-with-the-imaginary-enemy/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-10T11:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/10/fighting-with-the-imaginary-enemy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you want to run away confronting a challenge. Usually, you have your own reasons. It is too hard. It is too boring. I am not good at this. It is so painful. You want to advoid to meet it although it is important and urgent. We all know it but feel so hard to control yourself.</p>

<p>So what to do?</p>

<p>YOU have an imaginary enemy to fight. Game start! Sometimes your enemy is strong and sometimes he is endurable. Mostly, you have exaggerated your enemy and belittled yourself. Imagine you are fighting against an enemy who also have his own weakness. The wise move would be found his weakness and take all the advantage you have to beat him. If you don't fight, you are doomed to failure. If you fight, there still a hope to win.</p>

<p>In fact, you have no opotions but to fight. Your imaginary enemy would alert you and help you to beat the fearness and win the game!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observation of daily life of Americans]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/02/observation-of-daily-life-of-americans/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/02/observation-of-daily-life-of-americans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These days while I live in my apartment, I pay close attention to the daily life of people here. I have drawed a conclusion: Americans are lazy.</p>

<p>In fact, Lazy here is not used in a derogatory sense. You know, only the lazy people can invent and design a comfortable life. Americans are such kind of designers who are persueing simple but comfortable life. Let me give you some examples.</p>

<p>I live in a house department. In China, the parking area is often underground or a little far from the appartment. But in USA, the parking lot is jut in front of the hourse near the door. You can imagine when you get back from work, get out of your car, and then enter your door, it is so convinent.</p>

<p>After you get in, you can find a kitchen, a sitting room, a laundry room and a bath room. If you take a look at the kitchen, you will find a dish washer there and microwave oven. In China, most people just wash by hands, you can hardly found a dish washer, expecially in a student's department.</p>

<p>As to food, most food can be cooked just by heatting, like milk and bread. If sauces are needed, they are already mixed up and ready for use. You can find all this kind of mixed up sauces or semi-manufactured food everywhere in a food supermaket. Cooking become easy here, athough the taste may becoming a little dull. Most Chinese will not buy the mixed sauces, they may want to make their own although they will spent a lot of time on cooking.</p>

<p>One day, a ceaseless noise of machinery wake me up. I look out through the window, I found a man is using a grass cutter in front of the door. In China, people also use this kind of grass cutter, which is belted to the waist. But lawn mower like a car is hardly found in China. I often saw an american sitting on it and drive it on the lawn, it is fun. I also found people here clean the street in a differnt way, they use a air blower to blow the leaves away and make the road clean. If you walk on street in the early morning in Beijing, you will see a cleaner clean street with broom. You will never found a man with a blowing machine walk here and there.</p>

<p>And almost everyone have a car here. Once I ask a black man for directions, after telling my the way, he said don't you have a car, I sait not yet. He then added while it will be 20 to 30 minutes' walk. I follow his directions, after 10 minutes I got there. It is not that far, I said in my mind. May be they drive too much, and then have no idea how long it will take by walking.</p>

<p>So there are so many differences between the two countries. It also stand for different culture. The Americans are taking every advantage of modern science and technology to make their lives simple and comfortable. Labor is much more expensive in USA than in China. The Chinese culture advocate deligent, hard-working and Obedience.  The American culture advocate Science &amp; Technolgy, comfortable life and freedom. You can not say which one is better, but they can learn from each other.  Athough the American life is easy and comfortable, but it exhausted much more energy. Athough, Chinese food is delicious, but it is time cousuming, I think Chinese really should spend more time on inovation in S&amp;T and social system.</p>

<p>by chunlei 08/02/13 07:30AM</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
