<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 日志 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/日志/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-23T18:28:09-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A nice and hard trip]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/04/a-nice-trip-but-not-easy/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T16:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/04/a-nice-trip-but-not-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When My one-year long study life in US ended, I took a 10-days trip with my wife before returning to China. It was a impressive trip with both beautiful view and hardships on the road. I dislike surficial tours that can not let me understand more about the local people and culture. In this sense, the trip was worth the money, time and all the efforts.</p>

<p>We traveled mainly by taking Megabus, as college students or poor people did. We had lots of luggage, I know that we might get in trouble when taking buses, but I thought it would not be a big problem because I planned to pay more for the extra luggage. Everything wend very well before entering the Magebus. The city bus driver, a kind old black man, helped us pull the luggage. When I tried to give him tips, he denied. He said he helped us because he love Chinese and help us from heart not for money. He gave us a kindly smile and went back to his bus.</p>

<p>We arrived very early, so we had to wait for the megabus to arrive. It was our first time to take this kind of bus. At 3:40 PM, the megabus arrived. The driver was also a black man, but he was strong and a little fat. My wife stood most near the bus, but the drive said she was not standing in the queue, and let her to go back. We followed his directions, when it came to our turn he said you got too many luggage so you could not get on the bus. I said I could pay for the extra luggage. He said no no no. You could not pay me anything and ordered us to stand at the end of the queue.</p>

<p>After all the other passengers got on the bus, he told me that I could buy an extra ticket for the extra luggage but have to finish it in only 3 minutes. I became worried and nervous and a little angry. I worried that I couldn't catch the other magabus. I was a little angry because he already saw us with extra luggage 20 minutes before but only told us what to do when the bus was going to leave in 3 minutes. Another ridiculous thing he did was counting down when I was trying to call the company to buy an extra ticket. He was doing his job, but by no means trying to help. He seems want to bring shame on us on purpose just because we are Asian foreigners and bring two extra luggage.</p>

<p>After nearly 10 minutes, he seem enjoyed enough of the show he made, he let me get in the bus but never ask about the extra ticket. He seemed not care about the tickets at all. He did give some sarcastic remarks on this issue in his native English with black people's accent. All he said was how stickily he was following the rules of the company and it was all my fault that the bus was delayed. He let me sat on the steps beside him first and then separated me from my wife by asking me go upstairs(my wife sat at the first floor). First I went upstairs following his directions and then returned to the first floor by another ladders in the bus. My mood was terrible. My whole body was depressed and shaking. What kind of driver he was? I don't know. I also can't understand.</p>

<p>The trip had to be continued. By any means, it was not a good start.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prepare to Leave UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/07/22/prepare-to-leave-uga/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-22T11:24:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/07/22/prepare-to-leave-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is alway a lot more to learn. Athough I have been studying in UGA for 12 months, I still want to stay longer and learn more here. I like the beautiful campus and quiet main library, I also enjoy professors' classes and my classmates. Yes, I had a lot of fun here. But it is the time to say goodbye now.</p>

<p>After ten years, I think I will still remember the trees,the people, and the stories.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/home-tree.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[夏日中的两个女孩]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/09/two-girls-as-passers-by/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T17:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/09/two-girls-as-passers-by</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>星期三，5月7号，下午三点钟，我从AD楼出来，去赶公交车。这是学期的最后一天，HSC校车明天就要停开了。未来的相当一段时间里，我只有做City巴士度日了。一出门，下了台阶，太阳就火辣辣照了上来，转眼望去，一个女孩拖着一个大箱子向AD楼走来。我估量箱子很沉，她拖箱子时很费力气。望了一眼这两段陡峭的台阶，估计她要进楼很难拖得上去。她身材高挑，黑头发，黄皮肤，戴着墨镜，俨然是个亚洲人，于是我主动用英文问她是否需要帮助。她说ok，然后就把大箱子一把丢给了我，自己空着手，看着我。这也有点出乎我的意料，我本想是两个人一起把箱子抬上去，结果她要我一个人来做这个事了。唉，谁让我答应帮忙，好吧，于是我就开始费力地把这个大箱子往上面拖。拖到了中间，她问我是不是中国人，我说是？她回了一句，台湾人。第一次我没有听清楚，她又重复道，我是台湾人。我哦了一下，终于把箱子拖上去了。我看了她一眼，她没什么表示，没有用英语也没有用中文，说一声谢谢，我只好走了，她就一个人拖着箱子往门里面拽，弹簧门却故意捣乱似的卡住大箱子好几次，我本想再去帮她，但还是收住了脚步。</p>

<p>我很是好奇，她为什么不说她自己的名字，而是说台湾人。她先问我是不是中国人，我说我是中国人，但她却直接回了一句“我是台湾人”。于是，关于她我唯一了解的信息就是“她是台湾人”，一个有点骄傲的台湾人。</p>

<p>其实我的室友也是台湾人，是个男的，但是也并不像这个女孩那样。</p>

<p>我终于等到了巴士，上了车，坐到佐治亚中心换乘HSC校车。太阳还是那么毒辣，让人有个地缝都想钻进去。不巧的是等公交车的地方一棵树也没有，不过马路对面有几棵高一点的树，于是有一小块阴凉投影到我们这一边，我不自觉地钻进这小块阴凉里，为了不晒到头只好蹲下。有一个美国女孩儿，肤色略黑，也觉得太阳太难抵挡，也凑了过来。于是我们闲聊起来。我问她在等哪辆公交汽车，原来，我们等的是同一辆公交车。过去了一辆FH之后，我们的HSC就来了。上了车，我们又继续聊了一会儿，原来她是来自于美国北部的一个州，哪里的气候非常干燥，她说她花了一段时间才能适应这里湿热的气候。我说从干燥的地方到湿润的地方还是比较好适应，如果反过去就难了！我跟她讲我原来住在干燥的中国北方，但是现在工作在湿热的南方，有跟她同样的亲身体验。之后她向我介绍了她的姓名，在快要到HSC的时候她下了车，原来她不住在HSC，而是住在附近的小区里。她礼貌的跟我打了一个招呼，说很高兴见到我，我说我也是。之后她就下车了。</p>

<p>这两个女孩给我的印象极深，虽然她们的名字我已经忘了（在车上交谈时，我就说过我总忘却名字）。第一个女孩显得更时髦一些，第二个女孩儿则显得更朴实。但是，我觉得最大的不同在于她们对别人的看法以及与人交流的方式。</p>

<p>我并不是说所有的台湾人都这样，我只是一个观察点而已。但是我也至少知道了，有些台湾人多少可能会对大陆的中国人有别样的看法，甚至对帮助过她们的大陆人，也同样保留着成见。</p>

<p>有成见并不可怕，可怕的是不知道自己有成见，可怕的是不能放下成见进行平等的对话。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The beautiful leaves on the tree]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/19/the-beautiful-leaves-on-the-tree/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-19T16:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/19/the-beautiful-leaves-on-the-tree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/autumn-tree.jpg" alt="autumn-tree.jpg" /></p>

<p>On a grassy lawn near the road, standed a little girl about five years old. She was looking up at the colorful tree leaves and jumping to reach them. She jumped up using all her energy but found herself still get nothing.</p>

<p>I walked close to the girl-she was really a beautiful angel.</p>

<p>"Do you need help?" I asked.<br/>
She stared at me with her shinning black eyes without saying a word.<br/>
"Do you want some leaves? I can help!" I repeated. <br/>
"No" she answered. <br/>
"I can use the ball." She fetched a ball from the ground just several steps away.<br/>
"then the leaves will fall."<br/>
"You are very clever!" I said.<br/>
After I left, she began throw the ball up to the leaves again and again - very exitedly.</p>

<p>Well, she may never heared of the term "gravity", but she do have been aware of it and even make use of it to get the beautiful leaves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swimming pool finally found in Remsey Center]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/swimming-pool-finally-found-remsey-center/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T18:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/swimming-pool-finally-found-remsey-center</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally find a swimming poor that I can have access in UGA. It is in the Remsey Center just take the next stop of Aderhold by East-West School Bus. I purchased a membership for three months($15 per month). Today I went there to work out and swim. It is really worth every cents.</p>

<p>I took several pictures:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/work-out.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I often see people running on the road to do exercise. Sometimes man, sometimes old men stripped to the waist, sometimes women with young boy or girls. In fact, the road in Athens are not flat, so they have to run up and down. They really got the admirable sport spirits.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>
The following is a picture of the swimming pool taken from a window.  The water is blue and there many students swimming like fish in the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/swimming-pool.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Today the climbing wall is open for free. It will be one day for free per month. So if you want to try, don't miss the boat. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/climbing-wall.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I am too tired after swimming to try it. May be next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
