<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 社会观察 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/社会观察/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-04-14T14:27:10+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[后真相时代：真相依然重要]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/12/fact-is-still-important-in-the-post-truth-era/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-12T16:12:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/12/fact-is-still-important-in-the-post-truth-era</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在大众媒体和互联网信息满天飞的时代，同样一件事，会有不同的观点和立场，持有不同立场的人都只会选择性的使用所谓“事实”来佐证自己的观点。而大多网民，往往也只是选择一个立场站队而已。似乎真相已经无关紧要，这样的事发生在郭德纲和他徒弟之间纠纷中，发生在傻根和他老婆的离婚事件中，发生在冯小刚和万达对撕之间，发生在特朗普与希拉里的竞选辩论中。</p>

<p>站在一个普通网民的立场，对于一个事件可能压根就没有搞清楚事实的欲望，或者也缺乏辨别信息真伪的能力，更不愿以花费时间，最后结果就是找一个自己愿意相信的故事了事。至于真相，事不关己，也就没那么重要了。即便是某人被黑了，或者受到了舆论不公正的待遇，或者有人造谣生事。在这个时候，真相已经不重要，态度和立场已经压倒了事实。</p>

<p>如果仔细思考，这是一件非常可怕的事。我们可以称之为舆论暴力，舆论不分青红皂白就给当事人洪水猛兽般的压力和冲击，不管当事人做过还是没做过，更可拍的是打压完之后，即便错误了也没有人对所造成的后果负责。</p>

<p>这让我想起一个电影，网民通过一个非法平台来影响玩家现实行为，从接吻到冒险，甚至杀人，因为背后的网民都是匿名的，他们不负担任何责任，最后玩家一个接着一个在完成任务的过程中意外死去，直到主人公联合好友和黑客破坏了游戏平台，曝光了每个匿名网民的真实身份。</p>

<p>我们的网络舆论就像这个游戏，戏内戏外不断切换。也许上一秒你是个网民，你根据自己的喜好对冯小刚万达事件发表评论，只顾个人偏好不管事实真伪。下一秒你就变成了当事者，受到不管事实真相、不负责任的外界舆论的人肉搜索和打压。</p>

<p>我们真的希望看到一个这样的世界吗？我们真的想成为一个匿名、不负责任甚至心理变态的舆论暴力的一份子吗？公民理性何在？独立思考能力何在？如果这样的话，人人都不在乎真相，那么我们也就变成了一群网络暴民，冲动、偏激、愚蠢、不负责任、被人利用。</p>

<p>后真相时代是人们面对信息过载的一种无奈现状，千万不要把它当成终点或既成事实而不加改变。在这样的时代，真相本身以及追求真相的意识和能力实际上比任何时代都更宝贵。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Norma Rose Point School]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T22:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have been in BC for 3days. Everything is new for our ECNU students, the beautiful campus of UBC, the long NO 44 bus, the comfortable Landmark hotel, the nice professors and staffs, the exciting learning activities.</p>

<p>Today is even special. We went to visit a middle school called <a href="http://go.vsb.bc.ca/schools/normarosepoint/Pages/default.aspx">Norma Rose Point School</a>. The school is not far from UBC, in fact it is the neighborhood of UBC. It took us about 20 or 30 minutes to walk there from Scarfe building where our classroom located. There are about six hundreds of students in the school, from kindergarten to grade 8, including both elementary and secondary education. This school is very unique because of its educational rationals and teaching building design.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/ROSE_Point_school.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>They believe learning should be integrated and take place in communities instead of separated and in classrooms of each discipline. They want to give student a whole picture of the world and want them to experience this by themselves in their learning communities. In this way, students get better understanding of who they are, where they come form, how they will change the world around them. They will also take more responsibility of their learning and be proactive to inquiry the world around them rather listen to the teacher and memorize for tests.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/global_issues.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Community_learning_outcome.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The learning schedule and activities are designed and carried out by a faculty team but not a single teacher as traditionally school usually do. The teacher love this kind of collaborative teaching, it also give teacher many opportunities to learn from each others. It is much easier for new teacher to join the team to teach together. As you can see, they value collaboration very much. Student collaborate with student, teachers and even parents. Teacher collaborate with colleges, parents, and university professors. Student who are good at something can teach others. Teacher can do the same thing. They are all super heroes at that time. Super hero is a learning activity designed by the 4th grade teacher team which engage students and let them rethink what a hero means.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/grade4_learning_schedual.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Many features of the school building reflect educational wisdom. They make a window to let student who play basketball to look downstairs and notice what is happening in the football playground. All the classrooms are open without a door but only three or two walls. It means guests are always welcome to join or observe the class. There are also lots of art crafts made by student to show their understanding of their school spirits.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/art_crafts.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/open_classroom.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>It is hard to believe such an ideal school can exist and survive. ARE there any disadvantages and challenges for this kind of school? Of course there are, but who can deny their bold spirit and unique learning place design. It is beautiful! That is enough for now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[迷失在城市生活里]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/03/lost-in-the-city/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-03T22:48:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/03/lost-in-the-city</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>现代人生活节奏越来越快，每个人都步履匆匆，打电话总说自己很忙，忙不过来，忙个没完没了。</p>

<p>这让我想起一个故事：</p>

<p>有一队人正在沙漠中举步维艰的前行，突然前面的队伍停了下来，首领很生气问为什么要停下来，来人回答说：我们走的太快了，要停下了等等被落在后面的灵魂。</p>

<p>这是一个物欲横流而缺乏反思的时代，而如果任凭自己卷入洪流就会面临迷失自我的风险。别人进城，我也进城，别人买房，我也买房，别人生娃，我也生娃，别人孩子上补习班，我也让孩子上补习班，总之千万别落后。</p>

<p>我是谁，我为什么要跟随，我来自哪，我要去哪里，这些人生大问题早已被紧张的城市生活所淹没。我不在是自己的我，我成了城市街道里的一个影子，不知道从哪里来，也不知道要到哪里去，忐忑而焦急，疲于奔命的紧跟着城市的节奏。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Chinese say maybe and but]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/04/why-chinese-say-maybe-and-but/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-04T10:52:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/04/why-chinese-say-maybe-and-but</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I watched a TED recently that Sarah Jones(a actress) played the role of 11 people from different cultures to response to random questions asked by TED audiences.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/YlmZkY1uqXM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>I was impressed by the Chinese American woman she played who always repeat "BUT" and "Maybe". It heard like a typical Chinese speaker. I began to think why Chinese people tend to say these two words again and again. One reason is that they are not good at express themselves. The second reason might be they are not confident; they feel insecurity. She said that at least the food should not be poison. As you know, food, sex and sacurity are the basic needs of human according to Maslow's hierarchy of needs.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Maslow-needs.png" alt="Maslow's hierarchy of needs" /> <br/>
Why Chinese people are lack of sacurity. Well, it is a long story. To make it brief---it is becuase poisonous food, polluted air and water, dominated culture and so on. A survey report that many rich people in China want to imgrant to other country such as US, Canada. Some Corrupt officials want to have orther country's identity because they want to escape from the punishment. There also a lot of people want to go US, becuase they worry about the nature and social environment, they worry about the education and healthy of their children.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[教育回归生活]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/02/26/life-and-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-26T09:54:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/02/26/life-and-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>杜威说：教育即生活，学校即社会。陶行知说：生活即教育，社会即学校。可是我们今天的教育却是与生活完全脱轨的。教的东西用不上，用得上的东西没有教。</p>

<p>也许我这样说读者不会信服，举几个例子。我跑步的时候鞋带经常散开，于是我重新系好，跑了一会又散了，真实个让人头疼的问题。我曾经听过一个老外讲系鞋带的事，但是当时没怎么当回事。昨天又读到胡适的文章，说他系鞋带是一个外国女朋友交给他的，不会散开。于是我就在youtube上搜索了一下<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SrIjcvM6QA4&amp;list=FLrujcwoOwtITvOm7XKTnOng&amp;index=1">系鞋带的正确方法(how to tie your shoes right)</a>，果然有。做示范的女生自称是看了一个TED的节目，发现自己20多年鞋带一直是系错的。于是自己现身说法、示范给他人看。我仔细观察模仿，果然是不一样，错误系法鞋带系好之后是竖着的，前后走向，容易散开，正确的系法鞋带是横向的，像一个蝴蝶结，不容易散。跟这个女生相比，我系错了三十多年，真是汗颜。为什么会这样，因为这个东西根本没人教你。</p>

<p>你也许会说，系错了也没什么大不了的。但是你不能否认它的实用性，然而这个最实用的技巧却没人教，这是值得反思的。在举一个例子，中国的口腔问题非常严重，口臭、牙黄、牙龈出血等等一些列问题，不仅影响个人健康，还影响国际形象。实际上在很大程度上，这都跟小的时候没有学会正确刷牙有关。有很多人不是没有刷牙习惯，但是方法错误。比如用力过猛，时间过短，清洁不到位，不会选用合适的牙刷，不会使用牙线。为什么不会，因为没人教。系鞋带系错了，也许你只是摔一跤。牙不会刷则直接会影响健康和生活质量。但是这门课，家长不一定会，学校也没有认真教，甚至压根没有。</p>

<p>其实教育是生活的一部分，同时教育也是为更好的生活而服务的。再举一个例子，不过首先考考大家，你知道人民代表大会制度吗？知道的请举手。你知道如何选举吗？请举手。如果前两个问题你都举手了，那么你能讲讲民主生活吗？对于这个问题，我敢说很多人都会犯嘀咕。他知道一些概念，甚至也知道一些程序，但是让他说说自己的民主生活，他就哑口无言或者不愿意讲。中国大地上演了无数的民主闹剧，包括大学生自己的选举，这样的利益瓜葛不是很大，人群素质比较高的选举，都缺乏基本公平合理的程序和应有的态度，常常是以各种借口应付了事，甚至掌权人内定。更不要说高厉害的基层选举。有人经常批评群众的民主素养，但是更应该批评的是学校的民主教育，民主绝不是几个概念和程序，它是一种生活方式。与其让孩子们背小学生守则，不如让其参与学校的民主生活。这么重要的素养，学校培养了吗？没有。刘瑜写了本《民主的细节》，到可以拿来充饥充饥，缓解一下我们的民主教育缺乏症。</p>

<p>所以我说，我们的教育还是脱离生活的教育。这不是简单的应试教育的问题，因为你批评了应试教育，还可以出来“精英教育”、“学院教育”、“灌输式教育”，这不单单是教育目的的问题，还涉及教育内容和教育方法，这是教育文化的问题。教育只有回归生活、反映生活、为了生活，才能有生气和活力。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
