<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: physics | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/physics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-02-13T02:06:56+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From falling objects experiment to a simulated experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/from-falling-objects-experiment-to-a-simulated-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T13:42:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/from-falling-objects-experiment-to-a-simulated-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I attened the Science Method class. An interesting question discussed was the experiment of falling objects-the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galileo%27s_Leaning_Tower_of_Pisa_experiment">Galileo's Leaning Tower of Pisa experiment</a>.  Dr. Luft provided us some students' responses and let us to figure out the students' thinking and how to response to students properly.</p>

<p>But the question caught my curiosity in the class was two ice cube droping from the same inclination.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bigsmallball.png" alt="two ball fall at the same height" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I asked my classmates what happens in the following situations.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/3inclinations.png" alt="picture" /></p>

<p>I acturally did the experiment using <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/en/simulation/energy-skate-park">simulation environment</a>.</p>

<p>The result is interesting. Ball B frist arrived at the bottom with lest time.(The first two curves are situation A; Next two curves are situation B)
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/skater.png" alt="Result" /></p>

<p>Ball A is the second arrived. Ball C is the last one. <br/>
From Leaning Tower of Pisa Experiment to simulated experiment, what a big change information technology has made to our science teaching and learning!</p>

<p>In fact, David Scott-Astronaut of  Apollo 15-recreated Galileo's famous experiment on the Moon by Hammer and Feather Drop.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/4mTsrRZEMwA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>You see the space technology also expanded our learning experience and provided us an amazing teaching resource-a dicrepant event.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
