<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: notes | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-26T10:19:14+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cognitive Apprenticeship]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T13:11:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sawyer, R. (2006). The Cambridge handbook of the learning sciences. (R. K. Sawyer, Ed.). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. doi:10.1017/CBO9780511816833</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Mscare.png" alt="Cognitive Apprenticeship" /></p>

<p>Method(Mscare):<br/>
Ways to promote the development of expertise<br/>
*  Modeling: teacher performs a task so students can observe<br/>
*  Scaffolding: teacher provides supports to help the student perform a task<br/>
*  Coaching: teacher observes and facilitates while students perform a task<br/>
*  Articulation: teacher encourages students to verbalize their knowledge and thinking<br/>
*  Reflection: teacher enables students to compare their performance with others<br/>
*  Exploration: teacher invites students to pose and solve their own problems</p>

<p>认知性学徒机制在网络社区甚至大学的学习实践中非常值得关注。在学习活动设计时，也应该遵循和利用上图所提到的步骤和原则。</p>

<p>比如这个表格所提到的内容、方法、次序和社区，在学习活动设计的时候就可以好好加以参照。</p>

<p>例如对于教学设计的学习：<br/>
一、内容<br/>
专业知识：前端分析（学习内容、学习者、学习需要）、教学目标设定和表述、设计教学思路和过程落实重难点、学习成果的评价设计、在具体教学情境下实施并优化。<br/>
一般性学习策略： 阅读材料、观察教学录像、见习、与专家教师交流、与同学相互交流、尝试设计和实施教学活动、自我反思。<br/>
控制策略：制定学习目标和学习计划、记录学习进度、提前准备、主动参与、主动寻求帮助、反思和总结、树立更有挑战的学习目标、掌控时间。<br/>
学习方法：通过反复强化练习口语以心理素质、通过优秀设计和教学视频找到自己的短板并模仿和创新、通过与专家教师的交流了解教学设计背后的思考和专家教师的思考和工作模式、通过微格训练锻炼基本的教学技能、通过阅读文献了解学生前科学概念研究成果、通过网络搜索查找教学素材和科学史内容。</p>

<p>二、方法<br/>
教师演示或者观看专家教师课堂录像<br/>
作为助教与一线教师共同授课或者分析课后作业<br/>
教师对师范生的学习活动组织的具体环节和过程进行校正和点评<br/>
指导老师帮助师范生理清自己的教学思路、活动和活动意图<br/>
鼓励师范生与其他师范生或者指导老师的教学做比较（目标、课堂气氛、教学技巧、学习效果等）<br/>
指导教师鼓励师范生思考和解决自己教学中遇到的问题</p>

<p>三、次序<br/>
教学设计任务应该：<br/>
由简单到复杂（观看视频、分析教学线索和设计意图、了解学生、分析内容、设计和表述教学目标、设计思路、收集素材、设计过程、学习效果评价的设计、评课、设计完整的一堂课、说课）<br/>
由一般情境到多种情境（初中、高中；农村、城市；普通、重点；传统、创新）<br/>
由总体概括到具体任务</p>

<p>四、社区<br/>
实际到中学去，看一看、相一想、试一试<br/>
建立网络分享、互助、活动学习社区<br/>
建立与一线教师和专家教师的专业对话<br/>
建立见习、实习的基地和教学训练的小组活动常规<br/>
激励内部动机，向着专家教师努力<br/>
学会集体合作、树立并完成更有挑战性的目标</p>

<p>对于此书感兴趣的人，其目录如下：<br/>
Contents</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction: The New Science of Learning 1<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</li>
</ol>


<p>part i<br/>
FOUNDATIONS<br/>
2 . Foundations and Opportunities for an Interdisciplinary Science of Learning 19<br/>
John D. Bransford, Brigid Barron, Roy D. Pea, Andrew Meltzoff, Patricia Kuhl, Philip Bell, Reed Stevens, Daniel L. Schwartz, Nancy Vye, Byron Reeves, Jeremy Roschelle, and Nora H. Sabelli<br/>
3. Constructionism 35<br/>
Yasmin B. Kafai<br/>
4. Cognitive Apprenticeship 47<br/>
Allan Collins<br/>
5. Cognitive Tutors: Technology Bringing Learning Sciences<br/>
to the Classroom 61<br/>
Kenneth R. Koedinger and Albert Corbett<br/>
6. Learning in Activity 79<br/>
James G. Greeno<br/>
7. Knowledge Building: Theory, Pedagogy, and Technology 97<br/>
Marlene Scardamalia and Carl Bereiter</p>

<p>part ii<br/>
METHODOLOGIES<br/>
8. Learner-Centered Design: Reflections on the Past and Directions for the Future 119<br/>
Chris Quintana, Namsoo Shin, Cathleen Norris, and Elliot Soloway<br/>
9. The Evolution of Design Studies as Methodology 135<br/>
Jere Confrey<br/>
10. Design-Based Research: A Methodological Toolkit for the Learning Scientist 153<br/>
Sasha Barab<br/>
11. Guiding Inquiry-Based Math Learning 171<br/>
Paul Cobb and Kay McClain<br/>
12 . Analyzing Collaborative Discourse 187<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer<br/>
13. Assessing for Deep Understanding 205<br/>
Sharon M. Carver</p>

<p>part iii<br/>
THE NATURE OF KNOWLEDGE<br/>
14. Case-Based Reasoning 225<br/>
Janet L. Kolodner<br/>
15. The Knowledge Integration Perspective on Learning and Instruction 243<br/>
Marcia C. Linn<br/>
16. A History of Conceptual Change Research: Threads and Fault Lines 265<br/>
Andrea A. diSessa<br/>
17. Spatial Representations and Imagery in Learning 283<br/>
Daniel L. Schwartz and Julie Heiser<br/>
18. Literacy and the Learning Sciences 299<br/>
Annemarie Sullivan Palincsar and Barbara G. Ladewski</p>

<p>part iv<br/>
MAKING KNOWLEDGE VISIBLE<br/>
19. Project-Based Learning 317<br/>
Joseph S. Krajcik and Phyllis C. Blumenfeld<br/>
20. Making Authentic Practices Accessible to Learners: Design Challenges and Strategies 335<br/>
Daniel C. Edelson and Brian J. Reiser<br/>
21. BioKIDS: An Animated Conversation on the Development of Curricular Activity Structures for Inquiry Science 355<br/>
Nancy Butler Songer<br/>
22. Cultivating Model-Based Reasoning in Science Education 371<br/>
Richard Lehrer and Leona Schauble<br/>
23. Exploring Mathematics Through Construction and Collaboration 389<br/>
Richard Noss and Celia Hoyles</p>

<p>part v<br/>
LEARNING TOGETHER<br/>
24. Computer-Supported Collaborative Learning 409<br/>
Gerry Stahl, Timothy Koschmann, and Daniel D. Suthers<br/>
25. WILD for Learning: Interacting Through New Computing Devices Anytime, Anywhere 427<br/>
Roy D. Pea and Heidy Maldonado<br/>
26. Arguing to Learn 443<br/>
Jerry Andriessen<br/>
27. Learning in Online Communities 461<br/>
Amy Bruckman<br/>
part vi<br/>
LEARNING ENVIRONMENTS<br/>
28. Motivation and Cognitive Engagement in Learning Environments 475<br/>
Phyllis C. Blumenfeld, Toni M. Kempler, and Joseph S. Krajcik<br/>
29. Learning as a Cultural Process: Achieving Equity Through Diversity 489<br/>
Na’ilah Suad Nasir, Ann S. Rosebery, Beth Warren, and Carol D. Lee<br/>
30. Prospects for Transforming Schools with Technology- Supported Assessment 505<br/>
Barbara Means<br/>
31. Internet Use in Schools: Promise and Problems 521<br/>
Janet Ward Schofield<br/>
32. Teacher Learning Research and the Learning Sciences 535<br/>
Barry J. Fishman and Elizabeth A. Davis<br/>
33. Scaling Up: Evolving Innovations Beyond Ideal Settings to Challenging Contexts of Practice 551<br/>
Chris Dede<br/>
34. Conclusion: The Schools of the Future 567<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</p>

<p>Afterword: After How Comes What 581<br/>
Seymour Papert<br/>
Epilogue: The Fundamental Issue in the Learning Sciences 587<br/>
Roger C. Schank<br/>
Author Index 593<br/>
Subject Index</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Principles of Instruction and teaching strategies]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/11/principles-to-improve-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-11T10:32:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/11/principles-to-improve-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Seven Principles for Good Practice in Undergraduate Education (Chickering &amp; Gamson, 1987):</h3>

<ol>
<li>Good practice encourages interaction between students and faculty.</li>
<li>Good practice encourages interaction and collaboration between students.</li>
<li>Good practice uses active learning techniques.</li>
<li>Good practice gives prompt feedback.</li>
<li>Good practice emphasizes time on task.</li>
<li>Good practice communicates high expectations.</li>
<li>Good practice respects diversity—talents, experience, and ways of learning.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Seven Learner-Centered Principles to Improve Teaching (Ambrose et al., 2010):</h3>

<ol>
<li>Students’ prior knowledge can help or hinder learning.</li>
<li>How students organize knowledge influences how they learn and apply what they know.</li>
<li>Students’ motivation determines, directs, and sustains what they do to learn.</li>
<li>To develop mastery, students must acquire component skills, practice integrating them, and know when to apply what they have learned.</li>
<li>Goal-directed practice coupled with targeted feedback enhances the quality of students’ learning.</li>
<li>Students’ current level of development interacts with the social, emotional, and intellectual climate of the course to impact learning.</li>
<li>To become self-directed learners, students must learn to monitor and adjust their approaches to learning.</li>
</ol>


<p>Principles based on brain science(Zull, 2002):<br/>
1. recognize the importance of emotion.<br/>
2. help students feel in control of their learning.<br/>
3. build on existing neuronal networks (prior knowledge), even if these networks are wrong.</p>

<p>The following was added 2015-02-28</p>

<h3>Glaser's Seven Principles of Instruction</h3>

<p>1 Structured Knowledge.<br/>
'Instruction should foster increasingly articulated conceptual structures that enable inference and reasoning in various domains of knowledge and skill' (17).</p>

<p>2 Use of Prior Knowledge and Cognitive Ability.<br/>
'Relevant prior knowledge and intuition of the learner is ... an important source of cognitive ability that can support and scaffold new learning ... the assessment and use of cognitive abilities that arise from specific knowledge can facilitate new learning in a particular domain' (18).</p>

<p>3 Metacognition Generative Cognitive Skill.<br/>
'The use of generative self- regulatory cognitive strategies that enable individuals to reflect on, construct meaning from, and control their own activities ... is a significant dimension of evolving cognitive skill in learning from childhood onward... These cognitive skills are critical to develop in instructional situations because they enhance the acquisition of knowledge by overseeing its use and by facilitating the transfer o</p>

<p>4 Active and Procedural Use of Knowledge in Meaningful Contexts.<br/>
'Learning activities must emphasize the acquisition of knowledge, but this information must be connected with the conditions of its use and procedures for its applicability... School learning activities must be contextualized and situated so that the goals of the enterprise are apparent to the participants' (19, emphasis in original).</p>

<p>5 Social Participation and Social Cognition.<br/>
'The social display and social modelling of cognitive competence through group participation is a pervasive mechanism for the internalization and acquisition of knowledge and skill in individuals. Learning environments that involve dialogue with teachers and between peers provide opportunities for learners to share, critique, think with, and add to a common knowledge base' (19)</p>

<p>6 Holistic Situations for Learning.<br/>
'Learners understand the goals and meanings of an activity as they attain specific competencies... Competence is best developed through learning that takes place in the course of supported cognitive apprenticeship abilities within larger task contexts' (19-20).</p>

<p>7 Making Thinking Overt.<br/>
'Design situations in which the thinking of the learner is made apparent and overt to the teacher and to students. In this way, student thinking can be examined, questioned, and shaped as an active object of constructive learning' (20).</p>

<h3>Psychologists Identify the Best Ways to Study</h3>

<p><a href="http://archive-e.blogspot.it/2013/08/psychologists-identify-best-ways-to.html">click here for more details</a><br/>
1. Self-Testing: Quizzing Yourself Gets High Marks<br/>
2. Distributed Practice: For Best Results, Spread Your Study over Time<br/>
3. Elaborative Interrogation: Channel Your Inner Four-Year-Old<br/>
4. Self-Explanation: How Do I Know?<br/>
5. Interleaved Practice: Mixing Apples and Oranges<br/>
自测，分散复习，自我审问和解释，混合练习。</p>

<p>High Leverage Practices<br/>
<a href="http://www.teachingworks.org/work-of-teaching/high-leverage-practices">read more</a><br/>
1. Making content explicit through explanation, modeling, representations, and examples<br/>
2. Leading a whole-class discussion<br/>
3. Eliciting and interpreting individual students’ thinking<br/>
4. Establishing norms and routines for classroom discourse central to the subject-matter domain <br/>
5. Recognizing particular common patterns of student thinking in a subject-matter domain<br/>
6. Identifying and implementing an instructional response to common patterns of student thinking<br/>
7. Teaching a lesson or segment of instruction<br/>
8. Implementing organizational routines, procedures, and strategies to support a learning environment<br/>
9. Setting up and managing small group work<br/>
10. Engaging in strategic relationship-building conversations with students<br/>
11. Setting long- and short-term learning goals for students referenced to external benchmarks<br/>
12. Appraising, choosing, and modifying tasks and texts for a specific learning goal<br/>
13. Designing a sequence of lessons toward a specific learning goal<br/>
14. Selecting and using particular methods to check understanding and monitor student learning
15. Composing, selecting, interpreting, and using information from methods of summative  assessment<br/>
16. Providing oral and written feedback to students on their work<br/>
17. Communicating about a student with a parent or guardian<br/>
18. Analyzing instruction for the purpose of improving <br/>
19. Communicating with other professionals</p>

<p>References:<br/>
Ambrose, S. A., Bridges, M. W., DiPietro, M. Lovett, M. C., &amp; Norman, M. K. (2010). How learning works: Seven research-based principles for smart teaching. San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass.<br/>
Chickering, A. W., &amp; Gamson, Z. F. (1987, March). Seven principles for good practice in undergraduate education. American Association for Higher Education Bulletin, 39(7), 3-7.<br/>
Zull, J. E. (2002). The art of changing the brain: Enriching the practice of teaching by exploring the biology of learning. Sterling, VA: Stylus.<br/>
GLASER, R. (1995). Application and theory: Learning theory and the design of learning environments. Paper presented at the 23rd International Congress of Applied Psychology, July 17-22,1994, Madrid,Spain.<br/>
Duschl, R. A., &amp; Osborne, J. (2002). Supporting and Promoting Argumentation Discourse in Science Education. Studies in Science Education. doi:10.1080/03057260208560187</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[District standards and position description]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/18/district-standards-and-position-description/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T13:34:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/18/district-standards-and-position-description</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following is from the book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a>  .</p>

<h3>District standards of competent performance</h3>

<p>A standard is composed of three parts: a statement which establishes a general behavior, a list of indicators which specify how that behavior will be identified, and a principal's judgment as to the level of competent performance. The statement and indicators are listed for each standard. The level of expected performance of these standards will be determined by the professional judgment of the pnncipal. The judgment is influenced by the teacher's assignment, class size, experience, and available resources. To determine if the requirements of the standard have been met, the statement of general teacher behavior, all of the indicators, and the performance level must be considered.</p>

<p>Section I—Instructional development<br/>
Area: Diagnosing
Standard 1 The competent teacher establishes procedures for gathering data by<br/>
a. completing the diagnosis for each student<br/>
b. using the diagnostic tools which are pertinent to the teacher's goals<br/>
c. using a variety of diagnostic instruments and techniques<br/>
d. requesting assistance from others, when needed, for more comprehensive diagnosis</p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Standard 2 The competent teacher interprets diagnostic data to identify the needs and concerns of both the individual and the group by<br/>
a. identifying the achievement level of each student<br/>
b. explaining the significance of the achievement level diagnosed</p>

<p>Area: Prescribing<br/>
Standard 3 The competent teacher utilizes diagnostic data to establish instructional objectives and relates these to individual needs by<br/>
a. writing instructional objectives<br/>
b. preparing objectives that show the data gathered in diagnosis are utilized<br/>
c. preparing objectives in terms of student performance<br/>
d. preparing objectives that are measurable<br/>
e. preparing both short- and long-term objectives for any assigned class</p>

<p>Standard 4 The competent teacher plans lessons to meet individual and group needs by<br/>
a. planning lessons that are consistent with the objectives<br/>
b. planning lessons that include appropriate activities which meet individual and group needs<br/>
c. planning to use appropriate resource materials related to instructional objectives<br/>
d. planning alternatives to meet the needs of individual students<br/>
e. accepting and using student feedback in planning instruction</p>

<p>Area: Facilitating<br/>
Standard 5 The competent teacher utilizes knowledge of subject matter by<br/>
a. using words and content appropriate to the subject area and students' abilities<br/>
b. using available media effectively and efficiently<br/>
c. requesting and using materials and facilities based on instructional objectives<br/>
d. knowing and utilizing community agencies, groups, and individuals to further the educational
program</p>

<p>Standard 6 The competent teacher uses effective classroom management techniques by<br/>
a. showing respect for students<br/>
b. providing an atmosphere in which students remain at task<br/>
c. exhibiting consistency when dealing with behavior problems<br/>
d. exhibiting positive verbal and nonverbal influence on students</p>

<p>Standard 7 The competent teacher applies learning theory by<br/>
a. utilizing and building upon students' interests and prior knowledge<br/>
b. providing feedback as students progress toward goals<br/>
c. allowing for a balance between intake of information and the expression of student ideas<br/>
d. providing the individual with activities to develop attitudes, appreciations, and values</p>

<p>Standard 8 The competent teacher uses a variety of instructional techniques appropriate to the students' needs by<br/>
a. giving directions in a clear, concise manner<br/>
b. phrasing questions so students may respond appropriately<br/>
C. using strategies which involve students in higher levels of thinking<br/>
d. pacing the activities within a lesson according to the needs of students</p>

<p>Area: Student Performance Evaluation<br/>
Standard 9 The competent teacher establishes procedures for assessing student performance by<br/>
a. selecting means of evaluation which are appropriate to the objectives<br/>
b. planning measurement procedures for specific purposes<br/>
C. utilizing procedures whereby students receive feedback on their individual performance<br/>
d. presenting information that indicates evaluation has taken place for each student</p>

<p>Standard 10 The competent teacher interprets the results of student performance assessment by<br/>
a.identifs ing the reasons why students have or have not met the performance objectives</p>

<p>Standard 11 The competent teacher utilizes the results of student performance assessment by<br/>
a. using objective data to arrive at a grade or indicator of student progress to be reported to parents and student<br/>
b. providing feedback that facilitates the student accomplishment of goals.<br/>
c. planning changes in teaching strategies based on the results of the evaluation.</p>

<p>Section II—Professional development<br/>
Area: Communication<br/>
Standard 12 The competent teacher communicates effectively with students by<br/>
a. listening to and considering student comments and suggestions<br/>
b. being open to suggestions about ways in which to present material<br/>
c. conveying an attitude that promotes participation in activities<br/>
Standard 13 The competent teacher communicates effectively with colleagues and staff by<br/>
a. participating in the group decision-making process<br/>
b. listening to and considering suggestions from the staff<br/>
c. sharing ideas and resources with others</p>

<p>Standard 14 The competent teacher communicates responsibly to the public the significance of the school program by<br/>
a. answering parents' inquiries promptly, honestly, and discretely<br/>
b. initiating when necessary communication with parents<br/>
c. having available or locating information to relate district philosophy to the community at large</p>

<p>Area: School Relationships<br/>
Standard 15 The competent teacher has a consistent and professional attitude toward accomplishment of own school goals by<br/>
a. contributing to the decision-making process and abiding by group decisions
b. accepting shared responsibilities in and out of the classroom during the school day
c. maintaining consistency in record keeping as defined by building or district administrative regulations and procedures<br/>
d. using adopted courses of study or adjusting teaching objectives to include such adoptions<br/>
e. carrying out reasonable requests given by proper authority</p>

<p>Standard 16 The competent teacher has a consistent and professional attitude toward the accom
plishment of district and state goals by<br/>
a adhering to and enforcing school law, state board regulations, school board policy, and established administrative procedures.<br/>
b. adhering to the Employee Conduct and Responsibility requirements as stated in the Board Policy Handbook.</p>

<p>Source: Adapted from Beaverton, Oregon Schools Personnel Handbook.</p>

<h3>Position description</h3>

<p>Position: Teacher
Reports to: Principal (or His/Her Designee)
Position Purpose:
Implements, supervises, and maintains a high quality learning environment Tor students within the specific curriculum and standards of the district.<br/>
Nature and Scope:
The teacher is a professional with the responsibility for implementing a curriculum. Inherent in this responsibility is the requirement of related academic knowledge, technical skills, and professional attitudes and judgments.<br/>
The teacher must have the ability to diagnose the needs of learners and to evaluate their performance. The teacher must also be able to prescribe learning activities appropriate to student needs and to constructively evaluate these activities. The teacher effects an optimum learning climate through appropriate and maximum use of all resources available, and through the use of effective instructional and classroom management techniques.<br/>
In addition to the requirement of technical competence, the teacher maintains an attitude and
conduct which is consistent with the district policy of professional conduct. The teacher follows building and district procedural guidelines and policy.<br/>
Primary Accountabilities:
1. Identifies the needs of students through diagnostic procedures and relates instructional objectives to these needs. Plans, prepares, and executes appropriate lessons, utilizing appropriate resource materials and activities.<br/>
2. Maintains student records as required by the school.<br/>
3. Communicates with parents, students, and other professional staff regarding student progress(behavioral and academic).<br/>
4. Follows a curriculum that is prescribed by state, district, or building.<br/>
5. Assures students of learning opportunities within a classroom environment that facilitates learning.<br/>
6. Meets the district's Standards of Competent Performance at all times.<br/>
7. Follows district and school policies, procedures, rules, regulations, and guidelines and the provisions of the contract.</p>

<p>Source: School District 48J, Beaverton, OR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effective teaching notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T11:25:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was reading a book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a></p>

<p>The following are summary notes of Chapter 3 Using clinical supervision to promote effective teaching.</p>

<p>Characteristics of Good Teaching in Students' Mind?<br/>
Niss(Nice)<br/>
 *   Nice(respect, patient and easy to get along with)<br/>
 *   Interesting(makes subject interesting and fun with students engaged)<br/>
 *   Sense of humor(tell jokes and smiles a lot)<br/>
 *   Sensitive to students' need( Listent to students' question and make changes to help students learn )</p>

<p>Teacher characteristics associated with gain in students' academic achievement?<br/>
Creati<br/>
 +   Clarity<br/>
 +   Raise Variety(of materials, methods, question types and levels)<br/>
 +   Enthusiasm<br/>
 +   avoid harsh criticism<br/>
 +   Task-oriented<br/>
 +   Indirect teaching style</p>

<p>Substantive interaction that increase students' at-task time:<br/>
Equal<br/>
  -   Explain(content to students)<br/>
  -   questioning<br/>
  -   using feedback<br/>
  -   assistance<br/>
  -   list the steps or tasks(chunlei added)</p>

<p>Effective Classroom Preconditions:<br/>
Amazing
- Attention and motivation<br/>
- Meaningful(students can find personal meaning in the information being presented)<br/>
- Applications(opportunities to practice using new information)<br/>
- Include both lower-coginitive and higher-cognitive tasks or questions<br/>
- Group work process in the classroom</p>

<p>Notes taken from another book chapter-Glickman -chapter 4.pdf<br/>
Research on effective instruction() indicates that effective instruction is based on adaption of curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. In other words, effective teachers think about what they are currently doing, assess the results of their practice, explore with each other new possibilities  for teaching students, and are able to consider students' perspectives.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<p>The following was added at 2014/10/30
Evidence based Teaching notes<br/>
<a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Evidence_Based_Teaching.html?id=DZRhPQAACAAJ">Evidence-Based Teaching: A Practical Approach by Geoff Petty</a></p>

<p>==Expert teachers set challenging goals: deep learning==</p>

<p>==Expert teachers had very deep understanding of their subject  and the teaching and learning of the subject==</p>

<p>Their subject knowledge was more integrated, interrelated and built around general principles.</p>

<p>This deep learning enabled them to "make lessons uniquely their own by changing, combining, and adding to them according to their students' needs and their own goals".<br/>
p310</p>

<p>The expert teacher knowledge of the learning process was similarly deeper than that of experienced teachers. This enabled them to predict and avoid difficulties that students might have , and to see what was happening in their classrooms in terms of a deeper set of principles relating how students learn.</p>

<p>This mean that expert teacher were better able to diagnose what was happening in their classrooms, and to adapt. They were more responsive to their students as a result. The teaching and learning principles they used were probably something like those outlined  in Chapter 14.</p>

<p>==Expert teachers monitor learning and provide feedback==</p>

<p>Aim for evolution rather than revolution. Trying new methods one at a time is usually best, or your students will get unsettled even if you don't.<br/>
Teachers touch students' lives for ever - so it's worth the effort to make powerful methods work.</p>

<p>Graham Gibbs(1992)<br/>
action research approach advice:<br/>
Involve others<br/>
Identify the problem clearly<br/>
Use research evidence to convince others and to find promising strategies<br/>
Start where you can<br/>
Start small<br/>
Don't reinvent the wheel<br/>
Involve the students<br/>
Changes as you go along</p>

<p>p318</p>

<p>Review<br/>
we review our teaching in particular lesson or sequence of lessons, and look for evidence for what worked and what didn't.<br/>
Difficulties: Being brave enough to collect evidence that might be uncomfortable, andhones enough to face up to problems without blaming ourselves or our students</p>

<p>Learn<br/>
we try to lean from this review, not just what worked or didn't, but why. This creates general principles that we can apply elsewhere.<br/>
Difficulties: Asking 'why' persistently enough to enable us to lean the root cause of success or failure. Being able to 'bridge' this learning to other context by asking 'where else in my teaching could I use what I have just learned?'</p>

<p>Apply<br/>
We plan an experiment, perhaps adapting what we did in an earlier 'Do' phase.<br/>
Difficulties: Finding the courage, time and inclination to do things differently.</p>

<p>Do<br/>
we carry out our experiment. The cycle repeats.</p>

<p>p164<br/>
Seven principles common to high-quality leaning and achievement</p>

<p>1 student must see the value of the learning<br/>
2 students must believe they can do it<br/>
3 challenging goals<br/>
the goal involves student activity on constructive methods<br/>
the goal involves reasoning not just reproduction<br/>
high participation rate<br/>
students have their audience, variety and fun</p>

<p>4 feedback and dialogue on progress towards goal<br/>
students need 'medals' that give information about the extent to which they have achieved the goals<br/>
students need 'missions' that describe how to improve and progress<br/>
students need to develop a growing understanding of the goals</p>

<p>5 establish the structure of information and so its meaning<br/>
from known to unknown<br/>
from concrete to abstract<br/>
the structure first, then add the detail</p>

<p>6 time and repetition<br/>
multiple context: examples and non-examples in many different contexts in order to 'get' them
multiple perspectives: student need to see what they are leaning through different 'spectacles'. SOLO<br/>
multiple representations: right- and left-brain</p>

<p>7 teach skills as well as content</p>

<p>The PAR model<br/>
Present Apply &amp; Review</p>

<p>end notes</p>

<p>有趣的是，脑科学和认知科学也提出了若干原则和规律：<br/>
基于神经生物学研究的证据，Zull在2002年提出了3条规律：<br/>
1. 认识到情感因素的关键性作用。<br/>
2. 帮助学生建立自己掌控学习的感觉。<br/>
3. 学习必须基于自己已有的神经网络（已有知识），即使这个网络是错误的。</p>

<p>脑科学的研究发现，情绪是智慧的高级组织者，情绪能够指导认知进程和影响推理。例如长期高水平的皮质醇最终将导致与学习和记忆有关的海马神经元的损伤 ，即使是短时间的高水平皮质醇也会对短期记忆产生影响 。情绪对学习的影响具有两重性，轻松、愉快的情绪有利于学生的学习和健康发展，而过于紧张、沮丧、愤怒的情绪则不利于学生的学习。<br/>
此外无论是教育研究还是认知科学研究都显示，元认知的发展对于学习非常关键<br/>
学习者已有的知识对于学习有直接和重大的影响。学生并非头脑空空的来到教室，他们通过生活经验以及人际交流已经形成了很多概念和认识，这些概念或者完全错误，或者不完全，或者相对合理，不一而同，但是都对相关概念的学习有着重要的影响，科学教育研究者称之为前科学概念。而其脑科学的基础就是学生在已有的神经网络的基础上建造新的神经网络进而执行新的认知功能。</p>

<p>Boettcher2007年根据脑科学研究成果，提出的核心学习原则：
1：每一个结构化的学习经验都有四个元素（学习者、教师、知识、环境），它们以学习者为中心。
2：每一个学习经验都包括能够与学习者的相互作用环境。
3：我们塑造工具，工具也塑造我们。
4：教师是学习经验的导演。
5：学习者具有与该学习经验有关的个体知识、技能和态度。
6：学习者都具自己特定的最近发展区作为建构有用知识的基础。
7：概念并不是语句而是有组织的错综复杂的知识簇。
8：学习者都不需要学习所有内容，但是需要学习核心概念。
9：学习目标不同，所需教学也不同。
10：在其他条件一线的情况下，更多学习任务时间等价于更多的学习。</p>

<p>References:<br/>
Boettcher, J. (2007). Ten core principles for designing effective learning environments: Insights from brain research and pedagogical theory. Innovate: Journal of Online Education, 3(3), n3.<br/>
Zull, J. E. (2002). The art of changing the brain: Enriching the practice of teaching by exploring the biology of learning. Sterling, VA: Stylus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
