<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-12T11:41:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Firefox extension FireGesture Scripts]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/firefox-extension-firegesture-scripts/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T18:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/firefox-extension-firegesture-scripts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found the firefox extension Firegesture is very useful. You can self-define the function of your gestures.</p>

<p>The following are my scripts:<br/>
1.  Sina Weibo(DUDU)<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>var sel = 'http://v.t.sina.com.cn/share/share.php?title='+encodeURIComponent(document.title)+'&amp;url='+encodeURIComponent(window.content.location.href)+'&amp;source=bookmark';
gBrowser.loadOneTab(sel, {
    inBackground: true,
    relatedToCurrent: true
});
</code></pre>

<p></code>
2. iciba(RLR)<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>var word = getBrowserSelection();
if (!word)
    return;
var sel = 'http://www.iciba.com/'+encodeURIComponent(word);
gBrowser.loadOneTab(sel, {
    inBackground: true,
    relatedToCurrent: true
});
</code></pre>

<p></code>
3.  Copy the title and url</p>

<pre><code>
const AS_HTML = false;

function htmlEscape(s) {
  s = s.replace(/&/g, "&amp;");
  s = s.replace(/>/g, "&gt;");
  s = s.replace(/</g, "&lt;");
  s = s.replace(/"/g, "&quot;");
  return s;
}
var url = window.content.location.href;
var title = window.content.document.title;
var txt = AS_HTML ? 
  '<a href="' + htmlEscape(url) + '">' + htmlEscape(title) + '</a>' : 
  title + "\n" + url;
var clipboard = Cc["@mozilla.org/widget/clipboardhelper;1"]
                .getService(Ci.nsIClipboardHelper);
clipboard.copyString(txt);
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strong sense of crisis make a nation grow sturdy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/strong-sense-of-crisis-make-a-nation-grow-sturdy/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T15:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/strong-sense-of-crisis-make-a-nation-grow-sturdy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People who have strong sense of crisis tend to study and practice hard. Nation with strong sense of crisis is more likely to grow sturdy.</p>

<p>American people and Unite States are good examples.</p>

<p>Here are some pictures evidence.<br/>
The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /><br/>
&lt;--!more-->
The safety shower is just at the right of the door.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Safety_Shower.jpg" alt="Emergency Shower in Classroom" /></p>

<p>Im my apartment, there is a white notice like following.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/safetyalert.jpg" alt="Safety Alert in Apartment" /></p>

<p>It doesn't look nice on the door. But it is there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why we teach science in school and how]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T21:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Why</h3>

<p>It is important for students to survive in such an era full of science and technology products and information.<br/>
It is also important for a country to have enough science literate talents and labors in order to survive in the global economy.<br/>
Why science important? You can go on reading another blog post<a href="http://www.letstalkscience.ca/about-us/why-science">Why science?</a></p>

<h3>We</h3>

<p>Science teacher is a career but also a job. They are playing the most important role in developing the science literacy of the next generation. We choose it and we do it.</p>

<h3>Teach</h3>

<p>Good teaching is not an accident. It is a pursely planed activity fiting students' needs and level.</p>

<h3>Science</h3>

<p>Authentic science not just includ scientific knowledge(facts, concepts, theories), but also the process of science and the nature of science.</p>

<h3>In school</h3>

<p>While school education system is still the dominant formal learning place today. So it is an crutial battle feild of science education. But science learning can happen anywhere not just in school.</p>

<h3>Why has science teaching changed over time?</h3>

<p>Science is changing everyday. New discovery, New papers, New theories and models, in fact science update itself everyday.<br/>
Student is changing every year. Students today are not like before. They have iphone, ipad, facebook. Even kids at the same age in different class response significant differently to the same question.<br/>
Society is changing too. It need more talents who are good at 4Cs: Communication, Collaboration, Critical thinking and Creativity.<br/>
Should science teaching keep the same as before? Never.</p>

<h3>How should science be taught in science classrooms?</h3>

<p>Well, It is really a hard question.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some pictures of UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I went to the Main library of UGA. I had a task to search a journal from 1980 to 1990. It was my first time to be there. To my suprise, nobody stopped me to check my UGA card. So I just went around and check out the journels. It means everybody can come in and take a seat to read. It is great! The frist floor is very big and open. The book and magzines are located in the center, surrounded by many groups of tables, seats and computers. Although many students studying there, it was very quiet. I ask a library staff how to find the journal, he helped me to check it out in his computer and told me it is located at the second floor and it is also available online. So I just came out. It was at the noon, I took a picture of the main library, it is beautiful. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/library.jpg" alt="Main Library of UGA" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
I also found some interesting things at Aderhold where College of Education located. The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I entered the building in the morning, I found there were lots of names on the bricks. I guess there are the names of professors who had worked there. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/stopread.jpg" alt="Stop reading go to study" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/namebricks.jpg" alt="Name bricks in front of Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I kept looking, I saw a brick which said: "stop read the bricks, go to study". I smiled and entered the building.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interactive simulation based inquiry activities]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T12:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes it is hard to let students collect data to test their ideas about nature. For example to make observations how stars move for a long time, or do experiment about why plant grow to the sunlight. In this case, when oboservation and experiment difficult to carry out in classroom, computer software or interactive simulations can help a lot. There are two examples.</p>

<p>In a middle school biology class, students can play with the following flash game to figure out why plant grow to the sun.</p>

<object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" 
codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/
cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0" 
width="468" height="60" 
 id="mymoviename"> 
<param name="movie"  

value="http://bioteahouse.wikispaces.com/file/view/Gmodel3.swf/446433960/Gmodel3.swf" /> 
<param name="quality" value="high" /> 
<param name="bgcolor" value="#ffffff" /> 

<embed src="http://bioteahouse.wikispaces.com/file/view/Gmodel3.swf/446433960/Gmodel3.swf" quality="high" bgcolor="#ffffff"
width="468" height="60" 
name="mymoviename" align="" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" 
pluginspage="http://www.macromedia.com/go/getflashplayer"> 
</embed> 
</object>


<!--more-->


<p>
In a elementary school science class, student can stuy how much water does a crow drink every day. They can also study their own diet using the same method.</p>

<object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" 
codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/
cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0" 
width="468" height="60" 
 id="mymoviename"> 
<param name="movie"  

value="http://bioteahouse.wikispaces.com/file/view/crows+drink+water.swf/391202546/crows%20drink%20water.swf" /> 
<param name="quality" value="high" /> 
<param name="bgcolor" value="#ffffff" /> 

<embed src="http://bioteahouse.wikispaces.com/file/view/crows+drink+water.swf/391202546/crows%20drink%20water.swf" quality="high" bgcolor="#ffffff"
width="468" height="60" 
name="mymoviename" align="" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" 
pluginspage="http://www.macromedia.com/go/getflashplayer"> 
</embed> 
</object>


<p>Interactive simulations can help:<br/>
-   enage students, just give a cool show and some questions, then let them play with it.
-   stimulate students to ask questions
-   make observations and collect data or evidences<br/>
-   test their ideas</p>

<p>If teachers can guide and organize them to make explainations or argue with each other based on evidence, and make predictions and test them, at last provide opportunities for self-evaluation and community evaluations, then this approach would be more effective for learning science in classroom.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
