<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-13T12:54:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[learning or no learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/learning-or-no-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T12:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/learning-or-no-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Learning is dangerous; Not learning is lethal.</p>

<p>Why learning is dangerous? Because when are learning you have to change--habits, beliefs,knowledge,actions and so on, every change may let you sit in an uncomfortable place unsure of the following consequence.</p>

<p>But not learning is lethal. Because the world change in every minutes, even every seconds, if you act the same way as before, you will be very likely lost your job, get a stroke and worry about your food and Pension.</p>

<p>What to do then?</p>

<p>Learn with a teacher, learn with your friends and learn in your own feasible and effective ways. Of course you have to study how learning happen to you at first.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HungerU]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T14:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to MLC to attend a lecture by Dr Michelle Smith. In front of MLC, I saw a strange thing. You can see the picture below.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hungeru.png" alt="hungeru" /></p>

<p>The fact and statistics is printed on it. Food still occupy a large percentage(39.8%) in their total household spend. In Congo, 70% goes to food, it means people there are more likely in hunger.</p>

<p>I asked where is the data from? They told me they gathered these data last Saturday, and the survey is still going on.</p>

<p>How can I participate? I asked. Just let people know this fact and then we can change this fact and statistic. Isn't it a good idea? College students may not give money directly, but they can collect data and spread the fact all over the world.</p>

<p>Although the program is funded by Farm Journal Foundation, I guess volunteer college students played a role in the Survey and HungerU Tour in different countries. This is the responsibility that our college students are able to and should shoulder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubuntu crash on graphic driver]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/ubuntu-crash-on-graphic-driver/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-08T22:14:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/ubuntu-crash-on-graphic-driver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I updated ubuntu, and then I can't start it any more. It show tyy1 login. In fact I met this problem several times before, I know it is caused by the graphic driver update. I have to reinstall the right driver. But I forget where is the driver file and how to setup it.</p>

<p>I tried many times and finially I got it back to normal. The solving process:</p>

<pre><code>#login with your username and password
cd Downloads # where my dirver is
sudo sh amd-driver-64.run
setup it (always select the first selection and ok)
#restart
</code></pre>

<p>I have copied the driver in the folder dirver. so next time I can found it more easily.</p>

<p>The problem I have to solve:<br/>
1.  How to stop the update for the graphic driver?<br/>
2.  How to recover my ubuntu quickly?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TMUX and VIM in ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/tmux-and-vim-in-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-08T13:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/08/tmux-and-vim-in-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Learning to use a new language is not easy. Learning to use all the shortcut keys of TMUX and VI also takes time.</p>

<p>Today, I want to record what I had learnt about TMUX and Vi.</p>

<p>While, I should divided this post into two posts, but TMUX only takes a little ink, so I just put it here.</p>

<p>TMUX is a tool to help you divide your screen of your terminals into several screens. Whenever you want to use hotkeys, you have to press Ctrl + B first, then you can press the hot key. You can change the pre hot key, but I just leave it unchanged. The most used keys are the following:<br/>
REMEMBER to press Ctrl+B first!!</p>

<pre><code>%  #divide screen left and right  
"  #divede screen up and down  
Ctrl + Down #make the down screen smaller  
exit #cancel present screen  
n  #new dash window  
</code></pre>

<p>That is it.</p>

<p>Then let me record the tips of VI. Well it is much complex than the former. Generally, it has three mode, i mode(insert and edit), v mode(copy and paste), and : mode(file operation). Ok let me write down the most used keys:</p>

<pre><code>Ctrl +: #this will let you enter the file operation mode  
i       #this will let you enter the edit mode, Press Esc to enter : mode  
v       #this will let you enter copy and paste mode, Press Esc to enter : mode  
</code></pre>

<p>When you press 'v' in the : mode, you can press Arrow Button to select the text you want to copy or delete, and then press:</p>

<pre><code>y       #copy  
d       #delete
p       #paste  
Ctrl+:  #show clipped board  
:%s/ski/sky/g  #replace ski with sky in all place  
</code></pre>

<p>Isn't easy. But it takes time to get used to them and operate unconsioucely.</p>

<p>I also want to keep down some hot keys of Ubuntu, let me google first. Ok here are they:</p>

<pre><code>Ctrl + Alt + L     lock the desktop  
Win                applications desktop  
Ctrl + Alt + Left  shift to left desktop  
Alt + Tab          shitt applications  
Alt + F4           shut down present application  
Ctrl+Win+Up        Maxilize present window  
Ctrl+Win+Down      Minilize presnet window  
Ctrl+Alt+T         Open terminal
$ command1 &amp;&amp; command2 # execute command1 first and succeed then execute command2  
Ctrl+Shift+Arrow   Shift Workplace  
Ctrl+Shift+Alt+Arrow   move present window to Workplace  
</code></pre>

<p>Want to know more, click <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/KeyboardShortcuts">here</a><br/>
Now almost done, and wait to be expanded.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do the job or have fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/do-the-job-or-have-fun/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T19:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/do-the-job-or-have-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes when something becomes your job, even you love it, when you have to do if before a deadline, you tend to lose the fun you had before.</p>

<p>Something you don't have to do it, but you are interested and want to try. You are more likely to do better and have a lot of fun.</p>

<p>As a teacher, how do you apply this rule to your teaching?</p>

<p>Is it the reason why teacher drop out in their early career?</p>

<p>How to let teachers have fun in their teaching?</p>

<p>How to let students have fun in their learning?</p>

<p>Why people have fun in doing something? The following is a list of "something" can offer:<br/>
1. Provide new/pleasant experience<br/>
People are born with curiosity, and love to have new experience. They like to do the thing they have never done before or doing the same thing but in new ways.<br/>
2. Engage emotion<br/>
Passion, curiosity, sense of acheivement even superiority are all emotions letting people have fun. So if the design can engage these emotions, then it becomes hot.<br/>
3. Match their habits and mindset<br/>
They don't need to take much effort in order to operate or understand. It is user friendly designed.<br/>
4. Meet various needs<br/>
5. Be simple and neat</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
