<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-17T15:27:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why football is so influential in US]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/11/why-football-is-so-influential-in-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-11T11:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/11/why-football-is-so-influential-in-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Football is very influential in United States.</p>

<p>If you walk in the streets in Athens, you will see bulldogs everywhere, not the real bulldog but the statues, pictures, logos of bulldogs. Why? Because bulldog is the nickname of their UGA football team and it is also the mascot of their team.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bulldog.png" alt="bulldog Uga" /></p>

<p>When you take buses, you can see slogans such as "Go Dawgs!" "Beat Kentucky!" on the screen of the UGA buses. The University even made a special holiday for students to watch football game. A professor told me this story. When there was a game in Florida vs Georgia Bulldog, many students dropped the class to go to Florida to watch the game. So the university decided to make this Friday a holiday for students.</p>

<p>The football game is a full day events on Saturday. When there is a home base game in Sanford stadium, many people come to enjoy the game, the road becomes very crowed and it is so inconvenient and expensive to park that many people nearby decide to walk nearly an hour to get the stadium. People usually wear some red, such as red T-shirt or hat. A home base ticket cost 50~200$ according to the position of the seats. So it is not cheap, and most people would go game for five or six times in a year, which means they will spend about 500$ for game. Why they would like to spent so much money and time on football? Well, the answer is it is not only a game.</p>

<p>Before entering the stadium, people often bring there lunch and eat together siting somewhere. This is called "Tailgating". Some people even use their car to make tent and bring their TV set and have a barbecue in their auto tent. In the tailgating, every people prepare some dishes, and share with each other, it is not only a time to eat but also to chat with leacher other and get known to each other.</p>

<p>Every time I went to the football game, there are some events. Sometimes they are honor events. University professors, athletes or players, all the outstanding people in many field come to the ground to show up in front of audience, it is a great honor to be on the green ground. Sometimes they are surprising events. The first time I went football, I saw a solider appear in the ground and gave his family a big surprise after honored on the ground. The mother ran to his son and hug him, it is so touching, tears welled from many audience's faces.</p>

<p>In the second game I visited, the senior students were going to leave the game ground, so they come and give a performance of instrumental ensemble, the audience flag "Once Dawg always Dawg", the cheer team print "Georgia Senior" and "Senior" on their T shirt or bodies. The flags were small; One or two people can held them; People might made them by themselves.</p>

<p>The game is interactive and full of passion. The stadium is full of red people raising their flag or hands and sing the same song at the start of the game. During the game, the players would encourage the audience to make noise to cheer for their offence or defense. There is also some game for audience to guess which cup contain the food on the big screen. Many photographers stand around the stadium not only record what happen on ground but also in audience seats. They would project audience on the big screen, such as little boy, girl, beauties, man, old women. People become very exited when their image is on the big screen. There are lots ways for audiences to cheer for their team including both lingual and body lauguage.</p>

<p>In fact, Saturday football has become a part of American life, just like Sunday church. On Monday class, students usually greeting each other by asking "Did you go to the game?" And then they start talk about the game.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[what robot can do]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/what-robot-can-do/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T20:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/what-robot-can-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am very interested in robot. I believed that someday it can play a very important role in our society and personal life.</p>

<p>There are many amazing things that robot can do. They become more clever and skilled in lots of feild: Some robots talk; Some walk; Some can carry; Some fly; Some can drive; Some teach; Some have expressions; Some have skins.</p>

<p>Today I watched a TED video in which robots help Henry -- a stroke patient -- regain his life.</p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/henry_evans_and_chad_jenkins_meet_the_robots_for_humanity.html" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>What robot can do? It depends on what they are used for. In the global market, if you want a awesome job, learn and do something that robots can't do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eco-life Design and Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/eco-life-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T18:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/eco-life-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In agriculture age,people don't have to worry about pollution. Because all the products are degradable. Nature itself is a great designer, everything can be reused and recycled. But as human entered the age of industry, the situation changed. Human want to create new stuff that never existed in natural world. Yes they made it but they are not born good designers; Many waste are produced but can not be recycled.</p>

<p>There is a simple logic. If human want live in earth forever, then everything should be recycled, otherwise there will be not enough resources or room for human beings.</p>

<p>China have made a miracle of economic growth, but the growth cost dear -- air and water pollution, increasing gap between rich and poor, village and city, east and west. This growth also can not be sustainable because the environment is getting worse and worse and the resources is getting fewer and fewer. In order to live a healthy life, China must reconsider its style of economic growth and design more environmentally friendly industry,agriculture and living system. But do China have enough designers to design the eco-life system? It is questionalble. STEM education may play a crucial role in preparing these future designers in China.</p>

<p>If you look into Chinese secondary and primary curriculum, you will find there is little content of enginering or designing in their class learning activities. How to assess the curriculum content to tell if it is updated and suitable for preparing future citizens? How teachers address this problem in their classroom teaching? Is there a lack of designing education in our curriculum system? If not, is the content and education good enough for preparing our future designers? These questions matters for the future development of China.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Risk management]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/risk-management/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-25T22:57:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/risk-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have never learn to how control risk in my education. Recently, several things I experienced force me to pay more attention to this issue.</p>

<p>After watched a film "Mongol", I want to use my iphone to contact my family. But I can't find it. I used to put it on my desk or pocket, but it is not there. I checked a lot of other places, the bed, drawers, kichens, even closet and clothes. It still didn't show up. I began to worry about it, I felt my heart beating quickly, I wondered if I lost it in my road back from food store. It would be a disaster if I really lost it, because many personal information was in it.</p>

<p>I sit down infront of the desk and tried to calm down. I still could not figure out where it can be left. Suddenly an idea come to my mind, how can i check out if the phone was in my hourse using wifi. Could I try to contack the person who found it? So I trun on my computer and use QQ(a kind of software like skype) to send a message to my iphone. The messeage said "Could you return my iphone?", then I clicked sent button and heared a sound in the room. It was from my phone. I tried to send again and listen where the sound come from. Finally I found my phone lay on the carpet under my bed. It must slip onto the carpet from my bed.</p>

<p>I had a great relief. Then I began to think what to do to reduce the risk of losing my iphone. How to keep my personal informaton safer. I read serveral posts on tips to keep your iphone safe. They suggested first you should set a password for unlocking. Then you can also install an app called "find my iphone" to locate your phone in case you lost it. The last suggestion is do not keep important personal information in your phone.</p>

<p>In fact, all these tips are trying to control the risk or reduce the risk. In dealiing with risk, we have serveral options, sometimes we have to accept it, there are always a risk that you can do nothing to control, e.g. traffic accident. In this case, people usually buy insurance to transfer the risk to insurer. We can also take some measures to ruduce the risk, such as put a piece of paper with your email or address at the back of your phone. If somebody find your phone, he or she may return it to you according to the information you provided. I found I need to learn more about risk management and get prepared for any risk in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emotion control]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/emotion-control/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-25T00:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/emotion-control</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes people lost control of their emotion, which usually do harm to themselves and others. It is an very important thing to learn to control and even make use of one's emotion.</p>

<p>Emotion takes long time to form and change. It is like the parameters in hidden layer of NN, taking more instances to evolve and even more instances to adapt themselves to new changes. Emotion can help people to judge people and things(e.g.. good or bad, friends or enemy) and decide what to do(e.g.. quit or persist). It can also work as the energy source of people. People are most easily motivated by emotion than reason. Students tend to remember something deeply with a special emotion aroused. You would also feel very strange if you are talking with some people emotionless and feel hard to build trust on his.</p>

<p>Although, emotion play a very important role in our life, but we usually ignore emotion education in our formal or informal education. We should provide opportunity for people to know how emotion affect our cognition and social interactions. How to cope with ones' emotion and keep emotional health.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
