<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-09T16:47:55+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cognitive Apprenticeship]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T13:11:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sawyer, R. (2006). The Cambridge handbook of the learning sciences. (R. K. Sawyer, Ed.). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. doi:10.1017/CBO9780511816833</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Mscare.png" alt="Cognitive Apprenticeship" /></p>

<p>Method(Mscare):<br/>
Ways to promote the development of expertise<br/>
*  Modeling: teacher performs a task so students can observe<br/>
*  Scaffolding: teacher provides supports to help the student perform a task<br/>
*  Coaching: teacher observes and facilitates while students perform a task<br/>
*  Articulation: teacher encourages students to verbalize their knowledge and thinking<br/>
*  Reflection: teacher enables students to compare their performance with others<br/>
*  Exploration: teacher invites students to pose and solve their own problems</p>

<p>认知性学徒机制在网络社区甚至大学的学习实践中非常值得关注。在学习活动设计时，也应该遵循和利用上图所提到的步骤和原则。</p>

<p>比如这个表格所提到的内容、方法、次序和社区，在学习活动设计的时候就可以好好加以参照。</p>

<p>例如对于教学设计的学习：<br/>
一、内容<br/>
专业知识：前端分析（学习内容、学习者、学习需要）、教学目标设定和表述、设计教学思路和过程落实重难点、学习成果的评价设计、在具体教学情境下实施并优化。<br/>
一般性学习策略： 阅读材料、观察教学录像、见习、与专家教师交流、与同学相互交流、尝试设计和实施教学活动、自我反思。<br/>
控制策略：制定学习目标和学习计划、记录学习进度、提前准备、主动参与、主动寻求帮助、反思和总结、树立更有挑战的学习目标、掌控时间。<br/>
学习方法：通过反复强化练习口语以心理素质、通过优秀设计和教学视频找到自己的短板并模仿和创新、通过与专家教师的交流了解教学设计背后的思考和专家教师的思考和工作模式、通过微格训练锻炼基本的教学技能、通过阅读文献了解学生前科学概念研究成果、通过网络搜索查找教学素材和科学史内容。</p>

<p>二、方法<br/>
教师演示或者观看专家教师课堂录像<br/>
作为助教与一线教师共同授课或者分析课后作业<br/>
教师对师范生的学习活动组织的具体环节和过程进行校正和点评<br/>
指导老师帮助师范生理清自己的教学思路、活动和活动意图<br/>
鼓励师范生与其他师范生或者指导老师的教学做比较（目标、课堂气氛、教学技巧、学习效果等）<br/>
指导教师鼓励师范生思考和解决自己教学中遇到的问题</p>

<p>三、次序<br/>
教学设计任务应该：<br/>
由简单到复杂（观看视频、分析教学线索和设计意图、了解学生、分析内容、设计和表述教学目标、设计思路、收集素材、设计过程、学习效果评价的设计、评课、设计完整的一堂课、说课）<br/>
由一般情境到多种情境（初中、高中；农村、城市；普通、重点；传统、创新）<br/>
由总体概括到具体任务</p>

<p>四、社区<br/>
实际到中学去，看一看、相一想、试一试<br/>
建立网络分享、互助、活动学习社区<br/>
建立与一线教师和专家教师的专业对话<br/>
建立见习、实习的基地和教学训练的小组活动常规<br/>
激励内部动机，向着专家教师努力<br/>
学会集体合作、树立并完成更有挑战性的目标</p>

<p>对于此书感兴趣的人，其目录如下：<br/>
Contents</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction: The New Science of Learning 1<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</li>
</ol>


<p>part i<br/>
FOUNDATIONS<br/>
2 . Foundations and Opportunities for an Interdisciplinary Science of Learning 19<br/>
John D. Bransford, Brigid Barron, Roy D. Pea, Andrew Meltzoff, Patricia Kuhl, Philip Bell, Reed Stevens, Daniel L. Schwartz, Nancy Vye, Byron Reeves, Jeremy Roschelle, and Nora H. Sabelli<br/>
3. Constructionism 35<br/>
Yasmin B. Kafai<br/>
4. Cognitive Apprenticeship 47<br/>
Allan Collins<br/>
5. Cognitive Tutors: Technology Bringing Learning Sciences<br/>
to the Classroom 61<br/>
Kenneth R. Koedinger and Albert Corbett<br/>
6. Learning in Activity 79<br/>
James G. Greeno<br/>
7. Knowledge Building: Theory, Pedagogy, and Technology 97<br/>
Marlene Scardamalia and Carl Bereiter</p>

<p>part ii<br/>
METHODOLOGIES<br/>
8. Learner-Centered Design: Reflections on the Past and Directions for the Future 119<br/>
Chris Quintana, Namsoo Shin, Cathleen Norris, and Elliot Soloway<br/>
9. The Evolution of Design Studies as Methodology 135<br/>
Jere Confrey<br/>
10. Design-Based Research: A Methodological Toolkit for the Learning Scientist 153<br/>
Sasha Barab<br/>
11. Guiding Inquiry-Based Math Learning 171<br/>
Paul Cobb and Kay McClain<br/>
12 . Analyzing Collaborative Discourse 187<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer<br/>
13. Assessing for Deep Understanding 205<br/>
Sharon M. Carver</p>

<p>part iii<br/>
THE NATURE OF KNOWLEDGE<br/>
14. Case-Based Reasoning 225<br/>
Janet L. Kolodner<br/>
15. The Knowledge Integration Perspective on Learning and Instruction 243<br/>
Marcia C. Linn<br/>
16. A History of Conceptual Change Research: Threads and Fault Lines 265<br/>
Andrea A. diSessa<br/>
17. Spatial Representations and Imagery in Learning 283<br/>
Daniel L. Schwartz and Julie Heiser<br/>
18. Literacy and the Learning Sciences 299<br/>
Annemarie Sullivan Palincsar and Barbara G. Ladewski</p>

<p>part iv<br/>
MAKING KNOWLEDGE VISIBLE<br/>
19. Project-Based Learning 317<br/>
Joseph S. Krajcik and Phyllis C. Blumenfeld<br/>
20. Making Authentic Practices Accessible to Learners: Design Challenges and Strategies 335<br/>
Daniel C. Edelson and Brian J. Reiser<br/>
21. BioKIDS: An Animated Conversation on the Development of Curricular Activity Structures for Inquiry Science 355<br/>
Nancy Butler Songer<br/>
22. Cultivating Model-Based Reasoning in Science Education 371<br/>
Richard Lehrer and Leona Schauble<br/>
23. Exploring Mathematics Through Construction and Collaboration 389<br/>
Richard Noss and Celia Hoyles</p>

<p>part v<br/>
LEARNING TOGETHER<br/>
24. Computer-Supported Collaborative Learning 409<br/>
Gerry Stahl, Timothy Koschmann, and Daniel D. Suthers<br/>
25. WILD for Learning: Interacting Through New Computing Devices Anytime, Anywhere 427<br/>
Roy D. Pea and Heidy Maldonado<br/>
26. Arguing to Learn 443<br/>
Jerry Andriessen<br/>
27. Learning in Online Communities 461<br/>
Amy Bruckman<br/>
part vi<br/>
LEARNING ENVIRONMENTS<br/>
28. Motivation and Cognitive Engagement in Learning Environments 475<br/>
Phyllis C. Blumenfeld, Toni M. Kempler, and Joseph S. Krajcik<br/>
29. Learning as a Cultural Process: Achieving Equity Through Diversity 489<br/>
Na’ilah Suad Nasir, Ann S. Rosebery, Beth Warren, and Carol D. Lee<br/>
30. Prospects for Transforming Schools with Technology- Supported Assessment 505<br/>
Barbara Means<br/>
31. Internet Use in Schools: Promise and Problems 521<br/>
Janet Ward Schofield<br/>
32. Teacher Learning Research and the Learning Sciences 535<br/>
Barry J. Fishman and Elizabeth A. Davis<br/>
33. Scaling Up: Evolving Innovations Beyond Ideal Settings to Challenging Contexts of Practice 551<br/>
Chris Dede<br/>
34. Conclusion: The Schools of the Future 567<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</p>

<p>Afterword: After How Comes What 581<br/>
Seymour Papert<br/>
Epilogue: The Fundamental Issue in the Learning Sciences 587<br/>
Roger C. Schank<br/>
Author Index 593<br/>
Subject Index</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A nice and hard trip]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/04/a-nice-trip-but-not-easy/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T16:43:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/04/a-nice-trip-but-not-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When My one-year long study life in US ended, I took a 10-days trip with my wife before returning to China. It was a impressive trip with both beautiful view and hardships on the road. I dislike surficial tours that can not let me understand more about the local people and culture. In this sense, the trip was worth the money, time and all the efforts.</p>

<p>We traveled mainly by taking Megabus, as college students or poor people did. We had lots of luggage, I know that we might get in trouble when taking buses, but I thought it would not be a big problem because I planned to pay more for the extra luggage. Everything wend very well before entering the Magebus. The city bus driver, a kind old black man, helped us pull the luggage. When I tried to give him tips, he denied. He said he helped us because he love Chinese and help us from heart not for money. He gave us a kindly smile and went back to his bus.</p>

<p>We arrived very early, so we had to wait for the megabus to arrive. It was our first time to take this kind of bus. At 3:40 PM, the megabus arrived. The driver was also a black man, but he was strong and a little fat. My wife stood most near the bus, but the drive said she was not standing in the queue, and let her to go back. We followed his directions, when it came to our turn he said you got too many luggage so you could not get on the bus. I said I could pay for the extra luggage. He said no no no. You could not pay me anything and ordered us to stand at the end of the queue.</p>

<p>After all the other passengers got on the bus, he told me that I could buy an extra ticket for the extra luggage but have to finish it in only 3 minutes. I became worried and nervous and a little angry. I worried that I couldn't catch the other magabus. I was a little angry because he already saw us with extra luggage 20 minutes before but only told us what to do when the bus was going to leave in 3 minutes. Another ridiculous thing he did was counting down when I was trying to call the company to buy an extra ticket. He was doing his job, but by no means trying to help. He seems want to bring shame on us on purpose just because we are Asian foreigners and bring two extra luggage.</p>

<p>After nearly 10 minutes, he seem enjoyed enough of the show he made, he let me get in the bus but never ask about the extra ticket. He seemed not care about the tickets at all. He did give some sarcastic remarks on this issue in his native English with black people's accent. All he said was how stickily he was following the rules of the company and it was all my fault that the bus was delayed. He let me sat on the steps beside him first and then separated me from my wife by asking me go upstairs(my wife sat at the first floor). First I went upstairs following his directions and then returned to the first floor by another ladders in the bus. My mood was terrible. My whole body was depressed and shaking. What kind of driver he was? I don't know. I also can't understand.</p>

<p>The trip had to be continued. By any means, it was not a good start.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prepare to Leave UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/07/22/prepare-to-leave-uga/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-22T11:24:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/07/22/prepare-to-leave-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is alway a lot more to learn. Athough I have been studying in UGA for 12 months, I still want to stay longer and learn more here. I like the beautiful campus and quiet main library, I also enjoy professors' classes and my classmates. Yes, I had a lot of fun here. But it is the time to say goodbye now.</p>

<p>After ten years, I think I will still remember the trees,the people, and the stories.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/home-tree.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demonstration of barometric pressure using a bottle of water]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T19:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/27/demonstration-of-barometric-pressure-using-a-bottle-of-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Oliver gave us an assignment to design a demonstration of science teaching. I already had several ideas. One was show them <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/">The surprising trees</a>. Another one was rolling a paper roll. The last one was the bottle water activity.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bottle-water-demonstration.png" alt="bottle water demonstration" /><br/>
Today, when I was on the road home after swimming. I couldn't stop thinking a more neat idea and keep revising the activity. I was very tired because of swimming but my thinking keep running in my head, even on bed with windows closed and curtain down. I imagined what the scene would be like, what to say, what to do, in what order, what questions to ask. I even came up with a little poem and dialogue:</p>

<pre><code>Needle needle hot
Let the water jet out
Jet out, jet out
Oh my God
Nothing happen

Wait a minute, let me check out...
Hymn
Why
Maybe we need the hole more lower
Let me make another hole

Hymn
Maybe the we can lay down the bottle
Hymn
Let me think, drawing the hole of water on blackboard,talk to myself

Maybe we can make both the holes open
Maybe we can check out in the up-stand position
Why?
Why in this position it work
In this position it doesn't work
Did you see that?
So when will the water come out? 
One open hole or two? In which position? In which hole does the water come out?
How do you explain this?
Why one hole doesn't work?
Why two holes on the same height also doesn't work?
Why the two holes need to be on different height?
</code></pre>

<p>Finally, the design finished and the thinking stopped. This is the reason why I don't write at night. Thinking will not let me sleep.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The surprising trees]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T16:26:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A tree can have its own home.<br/>
It can also step over the wall.<br/>
A tree can free your minds.<br/>
It can also make the spirit call.<br/>
A tree can become your home.<br/>
And you will never forget it anymore.</p>

<p>The tree that owns itself.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-owns-itself.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that steps over the wall.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/the-tree-step-over-wall.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/the-tree-step-over.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that frees your mind.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-free-your-mind.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-free-your-mind2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that touchs your soul.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-touch-you.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree can be your home and you will not forget it anymore.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/home-tree.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
