<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-17T14:55:50-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inquiry and demonstration]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T14:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Dr. Oliver gave us an amazing class about demonstration and inquiry. He first asked what question to think about or ask ourselves when using demonstration. Then we played two demonstration games with everybody totally engaged.</p>

<p>The first is radiometer (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crookes_radiometer">Crookes radiometer - Wikipedia</a>).<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/radiometer.jpg" alt="Crookes Radiometer" /></p>

<p>He just put it on a table and lighted up another bulb, it began to rotate. It was my first time to see this, I was very curious of its work principle. After close observation, I found that it rotated always the same direction with white vane in front and black vane behind.</p>

<p>Then we began to wonder what factors caused the vanes to rotate. Lights? But how? Temperature? how? What else? How can we found out? Try it. I tried using different angles of the light.</p>

<p>We also tried to use hot water and cold water to pure on it. It rotate exactly the same direction as using light when using hot water but the opposite direction when using cold water.<br/>
Nobody came up with a good explantion at the end. First I thought it was because the momentum of the absorbed Photon just like Crookes did which was wrong in this situation.</p>

<p>Then we began to do another game --Buoyancy.<br/>
First Dr. Oliver sent out a pre-test with 3 yes no questions about buoyancy followed why you believe so. Then we talked about each question a little while. Students answers and opinions are totally different.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pre-test.png" alt="Pre-test" /><br/>
Let us found out. So he did another demonstration droppiing a brass cube into water cup which had been balanced. He asked us what would happen if he immersed it into the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/drop-into-water.png" alt="Brass cube into water" /><br/>
We made our predictions and then we did the experiment. We also tried some other settings which were carefully designed but playfully demonstrated.</p>

<p>At the end of the class, he use his front pocket quesitons to reflect this lesson:<br/>
Does it elict students' ideas for teaching?<br/>
Does it it help student make sense of the material activity?<br/>
Dose it press students for evidenced based reasoning and communicating?</p>

<p>Yes it does! Yeah, we succeed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modify my previous lesson ESCI7040-A1]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an assignment of Dr. Oliver's class ESCI7040(teaching strategies). The goal of this activity is to reflect on my own teaching and modify the plans for future teaching.</p>

<p>I taught learning theories to undergraduates in order to let them make sense of how students learn and apply these principles in their future teaching.</p>

<p>The guiding question is what is knowledge and how people learn? The big ideas include:<br/>
1. Different type of knowledge play different roles and people learn them differently.<br/>
2. Learning Science is not just learning scientific knowledge but also science practice and the nature of science.<br/>
3. Teacher need various types of knowledge to help students learn science.<br/>
4. Different learning theories understand people's learning differently and give different suggestions for teaching and learning.<br/>
5. Preconceptions, learning styles, learning strategies play an important role in students' learning.</p>

<p>This lesson takes 90 minutes and during 60 minutes I was lecturing.</p>

<h3>Task1: Reflections of this lesson:</h3>

<p>1 Wether the content of this lesson can effectively help them understand how students learn science and apply these principles in their teaching?<br/>
Some ideas are too general and loosely related. They should be deleted or modified.<br/>
You should focus more on students' learning not teachers' learning<br/>
Don't try to cover every learning theories, teach the most important one and the crucial strategies or tools.<br/>
You may also included some brain-based learning studies such as how learning occur and what factors may affect learning.<br/>
Conceptual change should be included in this lesson.<br/>
2 Are these goals/objectives appropriate for your students?<br/>
These goals are not challenging enough for undergraduates. More critical thinking and challenging tasks should be used in this lesson.<br/>
You can try to related your teaching methods with learning principles and invite students to think both in the role of learners and teacher(your role).</p>

<p>3 How were the goals/objectives appropriate for the course in which the unit was taught?<br/>
I found that I simply followed the sequence of the textbook. I may first teach this lesson 'learning theory' (Chapter 4) and then teach 'teaching strategies'(Chapter 3). Students should first know how leaning happen and then learn how to teach.</p>

<p>4 How the instructional strategies adequate for the learning you hoped would happen?<br/>
Lecture should be more interactive(share learning experience of yours or students, thinking aloud, student teaching), include more student-centered activities (sorting learning tasks, diagnosing students' learning difficulties, think-pair-share, one minute writing, interpret teaching clips).</p>

<p>5 How were the assessments--either formal or informal--adequate(and valid and reliable) for the task of assessing student learning?<br/>
There are two assessments: A1 explain Osmosis to high school students; A2 design a 5E lesson plan. A1 is an informal assessment on class. A2 seems not closely related with this lesson. A better assignment would be study students' preconceptions about one topic and design an activity to elicit students prior ideas.</p>

<h3>Task 2 redesign:</h3>

<h4>The big ideas that student should understand:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Learners build their knowledge on their prior knowledge collaboratively in special social context or situations.</li>
<li>Learning occur when connections are made in Neural Networks or social networks.</li>
<li>Well designed physical and social learning environment help students learn by improving their brains' function.</li>
<li>Prior ideas, emotion, metacogniton play crucial roles in students' science learning.</li>
<li>Different learning strategies suit for different learning tasks; Some tasks are more difficult than others; Student percept learning tasks differently.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The skills that student should develop:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Elicit and engage students' prior ideas of a core concept.</li>
<li>Diagnosis students' difficulties in learning a concept.</li>
<li>Design or redesign classroom learning environment to optimize students' learning.</li>
<li>Select proper learning strategies for special learning tasks.</li>
<li>Summary learning research results and its implications for teaching.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The interactive lecture and student activites:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Share personal learining stragegy (Chemical equilibrium)</li>
<li>Ask a student to thinking aloud</li>
<li>Student teaching one screen</li>
<li>sorting learning tasks</li>
<li>diagnosing students' learning difficulties in a teaching clip</li>
<li>think-pair-share</li>
<li>one minute writing</li>
</ol>


<h3>Task 3 reflect on why you change:</h3>

<p>My previous purpose is follow and cover the most important content both on the textbook and in my vision. I spent a lot of time on how to represent these content to students but did not pay too much attention to how these content serve the goal of this course. At that time, I did not have many activities to choose from and had to create my own one by one. I also had limited knowledge of how students learn science before, now I know more. So I want to include the more important ideas that I know and get rid of un important or unrelated ideas.</p>

<p>Although I believed that I should use more student-centered activities, but I just didn't have them. It took time for me to gather, test, accumulate related activities or ideas. My enriched learning experiences and pedagogical thinking also help me to generate new activities that probably work for my students.</p>

<p>Recently, I read some papers and books about evidence-based teaching and brain-based learning, they also encourage me to select the core ideas and activities for my teaching plan.</p>

<p>Conclusion: If you want to improve your teaching practice, you need to know more about the content, more about your students, more about what you can possibly do and use in your class. Of course, you also have to know what student really learn and why they do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The tree that owns itself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/14/the-trees-that-owns-itself/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-14T14:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/14/the-trees-that-owns-itself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a happy time of lunch, Julie drive us to see a tree that owns itself. It took us only several minutes to get there from the Grit.</p>

<p>Here is the picture of the tree.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-owns-itself.png" alt="Tree owns itself" /></p>

<p>The owner of the nearby house loved this tree too much, he wanted to protect the tree as long as possible. So he claimed that he conveyed the right of this tree and nearby land to this tree itself.</p>

<p>The view of values of Americans are well presented in the story of this tree. They love and respect nature and the natural organism. They also respect and trust laws. There are more willing to share and respect other peoples' love and willings.</p>

<p>This cultural values may answer at least partly the questions: why the sky is still blue and the water is still clean; why birds sing in the morning and squallers run around; why people like to go nature for holiday and spend more money to buy green electricity.</p>

<p>This may be the big thing that China lacks and we want to rebuild, in both Chinese culture and education system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing paper for publication]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-14T10:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing is an very important skill as speaking. It aims to send message, from people to people, from generation to generation, from country to country. One of the most efficient way to do this is publishing in good journals. Nowadays, publication has become a crucial part of resume or CV, and people write papers not just for sending messages but also seeking for promotions. So good universities ask faculties for good papers; good researchers look for good journals to publish. Good journals want good impactors or indexes. Good researchers tend to cite more good papers from good journals. But can this system help sending necessary message to those in-need audiences? It may not necessarily be the case. It is just a game of numbers dominated by the for-profit companies and ambitious universities who care little what the content really mean.</p>

<p>Complain is enough. We still have to write anyway. But I believe we are writing for our audiences not for universities or journal companies. We write because we have the impulse to share. As a beginning researcher, I'd like to co-write with partners at first. I can learn easier and faster by observing the writing process and talking to them about it. So I would also recommend you co-write with somebody at first.</p>

<p>Although you may not like the game, it is still good to know the rules and the tools. Here are some useful resources for writhing educational journals:</p>

<p>I found writhing is both hard and complicated. It is like a hedgehog rolls itself as a ball; you can hardly approach anyhow. First it is hard because it is hard. Especially if you don't write often, it takes time to develop your own writing skills. Second, it is complex and complicated. Writhing a paper may include many small jobs: reading, citing, linking, analyzing, reasoning, revising, formatting, managing. It will remain hard unless you cut the job into small pieces that you can play with; Cutting tasks is a crucial managing skill.</p>

<h3>Writing tips:</h3>

<pre><code>* Write down your thoughts while you read.  
* Write it down when it come up to you.  
* Write timely before the deadline.  
* Write summary periodically.  
* Write, and then shut down disturbs.  
* Write with your ear, your mouth, and anything that helps.  
* Write briefly and clear; Every word tell.  
* Write as yourself and to be yourself.  
* Write as you are talking to a friend about your new discovery(emotion)  
</code></pre>

<h3>Writing steps:</h3>

<pre><code>1  abstract, title, journal  
2  results, logic, 5pages  
3  enrich each paragraph and link together  
4  revise and formatting  
</code></pre>

<h3>What make a paragraph good</h3>

<p>Focus on one idea<br/>
Format paragraph<br/>
  -Topic sentence<br/>
  -explanation evidence logic<br/>
-not too long: 3 sentences<br/>
-Concluding/Beginning sentence<br/>
-Paragraph work together<br/>
-unity(pronoun, sense, tongue)</p>

<h3>What make good sentence</h3>

<p>-no cluster, brief, clear, concise every word tell<br/>
-use strong verb<br/>
-make it colorful</p>

<h3>The hard thing:</h3>

<p>When you are wrting,it is hard to make the right decisions:<br/>
when to quit (something you don't want to do now);<br/>
when to search for help (something necessary but you can't do yourself);<br/>
when to just do the job no matter you like it or not.</p>

<h3>Writing tools:</h3>

<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/">Google Drive</a> can help you co-write online.<br/>
<a href="http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</a> can help you manage your references.<br/>
<a href="http://interest.science.thomsonreuters.com/forms/HistCite/">HisCite</a> can make graph to let you know how paper cited each other.<br/>
<a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/analytics/spss/">SPSS</a> can help you analyze the data.<br/>
<a href="http://latex-project.org/intro.html">LaTeX</a> is a good document preparation system especially useful when you have lots of equations and graphs(generated with R).<br/>
There are lots of other text editors such as Miscro-soft Word, EditPlus for consider.</p>

<h3>Useful books:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Publication-Manual-American-Psychological-Association-ebook/dp/B00CPUBEBM">Publication Manual by APA</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.apastyle.org/">APA Style website</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Writing-Well-30th-Anniversary-Edition/dp/0060891548">On Writing Well</a> by Zinsser</p>

<h3>Journal Rankings Search:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.scimagojr.com/journalrank.php?area=0&amp;category=3304&amp;country=all&amp;year=2012&amp;order=sjr&amp;min=0&amp;min_type=cd">Journal Rankings on Education</a><br/>
<a href="http://admin-apps.webofknowledge.com/JCR/JCR?RQ=HOME">Web of Science JCR-WebSearch Engine</a></p>

<h3>Journals and their impactors(2012 JCR Social Science Edition):</h3>

<p>REVIEW OF EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH 4.2<br/>
LEARNING AND INSTRUCTION 3.3<br/>
Journal of the Learning Sciences 3.0<br/>
COMPUTERS &amp; EDUCATION 2.7</p>

<p>JOURNAL OF RESEARCH IN SCIENCE TEACHING 2.5<br/>
<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1002/%28ISSN%291098-237X">SCIENCE EDUCATION 2.4</a><br/>
<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1002/%28ISSN%291098-237X/homepage/ForAuthors.html">for-authors</a><br/>
<a href="http://jte.sagepub.com/">Journal of Teacher Education 1.6</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.sagepub.com/journals/Journal200961/manuscriptSubmission">for-authors</a><br/>
JOURNAL OF COMPUTER ASSISTED LEARNING 1.6<br/>
<a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?show=aimsScope&amp;journalCode=tsed20#.U3QKWCggtes">INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.3</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/action/authorSubmission?journalCode=tsed20&amp;page=instructions#.U3QLWiggtes">for-authors</a></p>

<p>British Journal of Educational Technology 1.3<br/>
<a href="http://www.journals.elsevier.com/teaching-and-teacher-education/">TEACHING AND TEACHER EDUCATION 1.2</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.journals.elsevier.com/teaching-and-teacher-education/">For Authors</a><br/>
RESEARCH IN SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.1</p>

<h3>NARST Proposal Review Rubric</h3>

<p>(from <a href="http://www.narst.org/">NARST website</a>)</p>

<pre><code>
For each category, three criteria are required. Given the constraints of the 5-page limit  
for proposals, please assign a numerical rating using the following descriptors as a guide:
5 Highly evident: Proposal provides clear, substantive, and coherent evidence of all criteria
4 Evident: Proposal adequately describes all criteria in the category.
3 Mostly evident: Proposal adequately describes 2 out of 3 criteria in the category
2 Somewhat evident: Proposal adequately describes 1 out of 3 criteria in the category
1 Not evident Proposal does not adequately describe any of the criteria in the category
Subject/Problem
1. Is there a clear focus for the study?
2. Does the proposal include a clear rationale for the study?
3. Does the proposal describe the model, theoretical framework, or philosophy of the study?
Design or Procedure
Empirical Studies
1. Does the proposal clearly describe the methodology (theory of method)?
2. Does the proposal clearly describe the research methods, design, and study context?
3. Are the methodology, procedure, and design appropriate for the study?
Non-Empirical Studies (e.g., conceptual or position papers, reviews of literature)
1. Does the proposal clearly describe the approach used to develop the argument or conduct the review?
2. Are the ideological/philosophical positions of the author and sources made clear?
3. Does the proposal include an appropriate range of literature?
Analyses and Findings
Empirical Studies
1. Do the data analyses appear to be appropriate, coherent, and complete?
2. Are the arguments or interpretations supported by the data?
3. Does the proposal discuss alternative interpretations, bias, reliability, or validity as appropriate?
Non-Empirical Studies (e.g., conceptual or position papers, reviews of literature)
1. Do the syntheses of ideas appear to be appropriate, coherent, and complete?
2. Are the arguments or interpretations supported by evidence?
3. Does the proposal discuss alternative interpretations, counter-arguments, or bias, as appropriate?
Contribution
1. Do the conclusions add to, refine, or refute the oretical constructs?
2. Do conclusions contribute valuable insights into teaching/learning/researching science education?
3. Does the proposal clearly describe implications for teaching/learning/researching science education?
Cohesiveness*(Related Paper-Sets ONLY)
1. Are all of the papers in the set focused on a similar concept/theme?
2. Do all papers contribute new information to the set, making a meaningful strongly-related whole?
3. Are all papers of high enough quality to be accepted individually?
General Interest
1. Does the content of the presentation promise to be of general interest to NARST members?
2. Is the content presented in a way that will be meaningful to NARST members?
3. Does the paper promise to be of interest to the education community at large?
Overall Rating
(1-not recommended; 5 highly recommended)  
</code></pre>


<h3>Basic Paper Structure(ITDFD)</h3>

<pre><code>
Title
Author
Abstract
Keywords

Introduction
  Background
  Literature
Theoretical Framework 
  Theoretical foundation
  Research questions
Design/Procedure
  Participants
  Instrument & Procedure
  Reliability & Validity
Findings
  Tables & Figures
Discussion
  Findings review
  Conclusions
  Implications

Acknowledgements
References
</pre>


<p></code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lost in local extrema]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T11:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/29/lost-in-local-extrema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love this place, the library at the second floor in Aderhold Building. I love this table, which is not too big but just enough. This love can guide me back home.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/simple-desk.png" alt="simple desk" /></p>

<p>I lost myself sometimes in some very narrow area. People may ignore the whole when they are attracted and trapped by them. It can be power, It can be sex, It can also be anger and violence.</p>

<p>A picture comes to my mind when I am thinking of these dangerous Local Extrema---the local extrema. I frist notice this phenomenion in NG's machine learning class. This is the picture that he used to show local extrema. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/local-extrema.png" alt="local extrema" /></p>

<p>When the computer only have one seed, it is very likely trapped in a local extrema and return a wrong answer. It is just like a person who lost himself when he try to reach the extrema unrealized that it is only the local extrema.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
