<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-03T13:31:03-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Machine learning and Octave]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/machine-learning-and-octave/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T12:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/03/machine-learning-and-octave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I joined NG' class of <a href="https://class.coursera.org/ml-004/class/index">Machine Learning</a></p>

<p>I start to learn programing with <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/octave/about.html">Octave</a></p>

<p>Here is the Basic Commands from Ng's class notes<br/>
<code>
PS1('>> '); % make pre short<br/>
1==2 %false<br/>
1~=2<br/>
1 &amp;&amp; 2 % AND<br/>
1 || 0 % OR<br/>
xor(1,0) % OR
a=3; % semicolon supressing output<br/>
b='hi';<br/>
disp(sprintf('2 decimals: %0.2f',a))<br/>
a=pi;<br/>
format long<br/>
format short<br/>
A=[1 2; 3 4; 5 6]<br/>
ones(3,1)<br/>
zeros(1,3)<br/>
rand(1,3)<br/>
hist(-6+sqrt(10)<em>(randn(1,10000)))<br/>
size(A,1)<br/>
save hello.txt v -ascii % save as text<br/>
eye(6)<br/>
length(A)<br/>
load featuresX.dat<br/>
load priceY.dat<br/>
load('featuresX.dat')<br/>
who<br/>
clear priceY<br/>
clear<br/>
v=priceY(1:10)<br/>
A(3,1)<br/>
A(2,:) % ":" means every element along that row/column<br/>
A([1 3],:) % get 1,3 row<br/>
A(:,2)=[10;11;12]<br/>
A=[A,[100;101;102]]<br/>
A(:) % put all elements into a single vector<br/>
C=[A B]<br/>
C=[A; B]<br/>
sum(A)<br/>
prod(A)<br/>
floor(A)<br/>
ceil(A)<br/>
max(A,[],1)<br/>
max(A,[],2)<br/>
max(A)<br/>
flipud(eye(9))<br/>
t=[0:0.01:0.98]<br/>
y1=sin(2</em>pi<em>4</em>t);
y2=cos(2<em>pi</em>4*t);<br/>
plot(t,y1);<br/>
plot(t,y2,'r')<br/>
xlabel('time')<br/>
ylabel('value')<br/>
legent('sin','cos')<br/>
title('my plot')<br/>
print -dpng 'myPlot.png'<br/>
close<br/>
figure(1);plot(t,y1);<br/>
figure(2);plot(t,y2);<br/>
subplot(1,2,1); % divides plot a 1x2 grid, acce<br/>
axis([0.5 1 -1 1]) &amp; x [0.5 1] y[-1 1]<br/>
clf;
imagesc(A)<br/>
imagesc(A), colorbar, colormap gray;</p>

<p>indices=1:10;<br/>
for i=indices,
   disp(i);
end;</p>

<p>i=1;<br/>
while i &lt;=5;<br/>
  v(i)=100;<br/>
  i=i+1;<br/>
end;</p>

<p>i=1;<br/>
while true,<br/>
  v(i)=999;<br/>
  i=i+1;<br/>
  if i==6,</p>

<pre><code>break;  
</code></pre>

<p>  end;<br/>
end;</p>

<p>v(1)=2;<br/>
if v(1)==1,<br/>
  disp('equal one')<br/>
elseif v(1)==2,<br/>
  disp('equal two')<br/>
else<br/>
  disp('not one or two')<br/>
end;</p>

<p>pwd<br/>
ls</p>

<p>addpath('C:users\ang\Desktop') % octave search path<br/>
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conflicts between commercialization of science and education equity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/30/conflicts-between-commercialisation-of-science-and-education-equity/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T23:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/30/conflicts-between-commercialisation-of-science-and-education-equity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I attended Dr Jackson' class <a href="http://djackson.myweb.uga.edu/8990/Daily/Day12.html">ESCI 8990 Daily Page</a>.</p>

<p>We discussed questions:<br/>
1.  whether scientific knowledge is a private product?<br/>
2.  whether is it right to use grants to apply patent or develop products for profits?<br/>
3.  conflicts between patent protection and equal access to scientific knowledge.</p>

<p>I didn't say a word because I was the only Chinese around the table and intellectual property protection in China has a bad reputation although the situation is improving. I don't want to defend too much, but I guess everyone may only have one story about the IPP in China. But just as Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie said: <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/chimamanda_adichie_the_danger_of_a_single_story.html">There is a danger of a single story</a>. So it will always be good to know more than one story.</p>

<p>The idea of patent protection became popular in industry culture. In order to encourage people and companies to develop more new type of products for society goodness, we give them such protects and advantages in using the patent that they invented first.</p>

<p>But, in agricultural civilization, such as accent China, there is no such idea. Some people may keep their special way of making food or drinks as their secrets, but once the secrets were known by others, they can also make the same food and drinks, and it is legal. The government may also help to publish and transmit some technologies, such as paper making and the printing. If they apply for the patent of making paper and printing, how much money they can earn? But this may also slow down the development of human society. So every patent has limited period for protection. The patent finally becomes common property of human society.</p>

<p>In agricultural civilization, labor is the main value source of a product. Yes, patent tell how to make a product, but it is the labor make it realized. This is not true in industrial civilization, the people or company who possess the patent earn the most of the profit. You will never know how cheap labor become in China nowadays. Is it equal? Is it a new kind of colonization? Many developed country put their factories into developing countries, they use their labor, resources and make wastes and pollution. Is it fair? Is it sustainable? Will it leads to wars? You can read more about <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/drloveccsu/ecojustice-pedagogy">Ecojustice</a>.</p>

<p>Well, industrialization and consumerism are both come from western culture. Human rights is also declared in the western. But there is conflicts between commercialization of science and education equity. The following paragraph is from:<a href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/">The Universal Declaration of Human Rights</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Article 26.
   (1) Everyone has the right to education. Education shall be free, at least in the elementary and fundamental stages. Elementary education shall be compulsory. Technical and professional education shall be made generally available and higher education shall be equally accessible to all on the basis of merit.</p></blockquote>

<p>Poor people receive poor education and they remain poor, becomes a circle. This will only lead to hate and war. Patent protection can help develop new products and technologies and promote the progress of society. It can also benefit some people and groups and hurt the others. Especially, when the researchers use grants(money from citizens) to do research and apply for patents only benefit for a special organization or people. Then it is unfair.</p>

<p>It is also disputable whether something should be a patent. For example, the people invent the product later by his own, will lost all the value of his effort because it would be illegal to for him to use the same way to make product.</p>

<p>The company own the patent seems own a new kind of capital -- Intellectual Capitalism. Government tend to protect their patent rights in order to encourage more company to do research and development. But sometimes it will lead to monopolization and the price of their products becomes unreasonable(several times higher than its actual cost). Will government still protect?</p>

<p>With the global industrial production, with consumerism and commercialization, will this new kind of capitalism -- Intellectual Capitalism create a new colonial history. Do we want this happen? Or it already happened.</p>

<p>There should be a balance between patent protection and common benefit, between efficiency and fairness, between developed and developing countries, between industrial civilization and agricultural civilization, between human and nature, otherwise we are making troubles and potential dangers for ourselves!</p>

<p>iphone</p>

<p>克隆文化
有性繁殖与无性繁殖</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laptop stand designed by myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-29T22:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is uncomfortable to work on my laptop on a table. Becuase the screen is too low and you have to bend your head which cause pain in the neck.<br/>
So I made a laptop stand using a useless shoes box. Here is the picture.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/laptopstand.png" alt="laptop stand" /></p>

<p>You can alway make a change if you want to. And small change can make a big difference sometimes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't alienate disabled people]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/27/dont-alienate-disabled-people/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T09:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/27/dont-alienate-disabled-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, a TED talk at TEDxStanford moved me deeply. It was given by Rhodes Scholar Rachel Kolb -- who was born deaf. She showed what is possible through family support and self-belief, and proves that what is assumed about you and what you can actually achieve don't always match up. In the United States, two-thirds of hearing-impaired people do not complete high school.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://zhangchunlei.com//www.youtube.com/embed/uKKpjvPd6Xo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<!--more-->


<p>When I attended a coteaching workshop, an American teacher asked me if there were any disabled students in Chinese schools. I said very few. In my experiences, from elementary school to high school, even in university, I had never meet a disabled students, who was deaf or blind. Where are they? They do exist, but may live alienated lives out of our eyes.</p>

<p>In UGA, I saw many students sitting on their wheelchairs in streets, classroom, libraries, even on buses. They really provide good access for disabled.</p>

<p>In China, the situation in Beijing and Shanghai may be better than other cities. But we still hardly see disabled people appear in front us, when they do appear, they usually have many accompanies who help them to overcome the unexpected obstacles posed by people unconsciously.</p>

<p>Disabled people do deserve to live a normal life. Please don't alienate them!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The metaphor of rock climbing]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/the-metaphor-of-rock-climbing/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T20:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/25/the-metaphor-of-rock-climbing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so hard to descibe how teacher develop related knowledge to teach a special topic.</p>

<p>I have come up with many analogies to assit my thinking and modeling of teacher knowledge development.</p>

<p>Here is another wonderful analogy Rock Climbing. The following is a picture:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/rock-climbing.png" alt="rock climbing" /><br/>
More about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_climbing#Crack_climbing">Rock climbing</a><br/>
The teacher developed lots of intermediate representations (just like the cracks, faces, slabs in rock climbing) to help students learning the scientific concept.</p>

<p>Good teacher can "see" the postions of students and can "arise" the right representation to help. The subject matter knowledge is the moutain. The "safety rope" is the good teacher-student relationship which keep the safe environment for learning. The routes can be fun and the goal can be challenging. They all motivates student to climb and learn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
