<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-22T10:54:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IRT learning resources]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/22/irt-learning-resources/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-22T09:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/22/irt-learning-resources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a lot learing resources for IRT(Item Response Theory). But the most useful onese are those fit you well.</p>

<p>Here is a list which helped me a lot.<br/>
Books:<br/>
The Basics of Item Response Theory: Frank B. Baker: 9781886047037: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Basics-Item-Response-Theory/dp/1886047030">Amazon.com: Books-link</a><br/>
Item Response Theory: Parameter Estimation Techniques, Second Edition (Statistics: A Series of Textbooks and Monographs): Frank B. Baker, Seock-Ho Kim: 9780824758257: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Item-Response-Theory-Estimation-Techniques/dp/0824758250">Amazon.com: Books link</a></p>

<p>Vedios:<br/>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SrdbllMYq8M">A Conceptual Introduction to Item Response - YouTube</a></p>

<p>Pdf Documents:<br/>
A visual guide to item response theory <a href="http://www.metheval.uni-jena.de/irt/VisualIRT.pdf">VisualIRT.pdf</a><br/>
<a href="http://echo.edres.org:8080/scripts/cat/genicc.asp">IRT mini-tutorial interactive</a><br/>
<a href="http://echo.edres.org:8080/irt/baker/final.pdf">The Basics of Item Response Theory (by Frank Baker)</a></p>

<p>Slides:<br/>
<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/akdhamija/irt-dipr-1">IRT - Item response Theory</a><br/>
<a href="http://wenku.baidu.com/view/a4e5c8a6dd3383c4bb4cd28a.html">基于项目反映理论_宋慧鹏</a></p>

<p>Websites:<br/>
<a href="http://echo.edres.org:8080/irt/">Item Response Theory GOOD</a><br/>
<a href="http://luna.cas.usf.edu/~mbrannic/files/pmet/irt.htm">Item Response Theory cas.usf.edu</a></p>

<p>Softwares:<br/>
<a href="http://www.ssicentral.com/irt/index.html">SSI - Scientific Software International, Inc.</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.umass.edu/remp/software/simcata/wingen/homeF.html">WinGen: Windows software that Generates IRT parameters and item responses</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Principles to improve teaching]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/11/principles-to-improve-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-11T10:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/11/principles-to-improve-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Seven Principles for Good Practice in Undergraduate Education (Chickering &amp; Gamson, 1987):<br/>
1. Good practice encourages interaction between students and faculty.<br/>
2. Good practice encourages interaction and collaboration between students.<br/>
3. Good practice uses active learning techniques.<br/>
4. Good practice gives prompt feedback.<br/>
5. Good practice emphasizes time on task.<br/>
6. Good practice communicates high expectations.<br/>
7. Good practice respects diversity—talents, experience, and ways of learning.</p>

<p>Seven Learner-Centered Principles to Improve Teaching (Ambrose et al., 2010):<br/>
1. Students’ prior knowledge can help or hinder learning.<br/>
2. How students organize knowledge influences how they learn and apply what they know.<br/>
3. Students’ motivation determines, directs, and sustains what they do to learn.<br/>
4. To develop mastery, students must acquire component skills, practice integrating them, and know when to apply what they have learned.<br/>
5. Goal-directed practice coupled with targeted feedback enhances the quality of students’ learning.<br/>
6. Students’ current level of development interacts with the social, emotional, and intellectual climate of the course to impact learning.<br/>
7. To become self-directed learners, students must learn to monitor and adjust their approaches to learning.</p>

<p>Principles based on brain science(Zull, 2002):<br/>
1. recognize the importance of emotion.<br/>
2. help students feel in control.<br/>
3. build on existing neuronal networks (prior knowledge), even if these networks are wrong.</p>

<p>References:<br/>
Ambrose, S. A., Bridges, M. W., DiPietro, M. Lovett, M. C., &amp; Norman, M. K. (2010). How learning works: Seven research-based principles for smart teaching. San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass.<br/>
Chickering, A. W., &amp; Gamson, Z. F. (1987, March). Seven principles for good practice in undergraduate education. American Association for Higher Education Bulletin, 39(7), 3-7.<br/>
Zull, J. E. (2002). The art of changing the brain: Enriching the practice of teaching by exploring the biology of learning. Sterling, VA: Stylus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for better future]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T14:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I saw this in our main library when the staff cleanup the restroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/door-with-leg.png" alt="Door with leg" /><br/>
What a cool leg the door has! The idea is simple, but the result is so good. Sometimes simple change can make a big difference.</p>

<p>Nowadays, the environment is becoming worse and worse. One basic reason is bad design. Our company design good batteries with low-cost but ignored how to recycle and reuse the waste batteries. Similarly, the white pollution, air and water pollution all failded to take environment pollution cost into concern. These industries are all good examples of bad design and are badly need to change.</p>

<p>Well, how to solve these problems and create better future? The answer is design zero pollution industry pipeline. Just like the nature design all kinds of lives, no waste at all. For example, how to make use of clean energy as power for travelling. When you taking whole process into concern, you will find the horse and cart is one example of good designs. Of course, we will not return to this old method of travelling, but we really should rethink this design.</p>

<p>It is not just product design or pipeline design. It is also a life design. On behavior researcher found a very simple and effective way to save energy-- sending a letter of electric usage report comparing with neighborhood. After being told use more than twice electric than neighborhood, people tend to pay much attention to save energy. This is just how behavior science used to affect personal life styles.</p>

<p>Nowadays, people have learnt to make use clean energy such as wind, water,sun. Researchers are also trying to invent new technologies of producing and storing and converting these energy. We are going to and have to achieve no waste design in order to live a better life for long run on earth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What are we throwing away?]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/01/what-are-we-throwing-away/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T13:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/01/what-are-we-throwing-away</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I watched two TED videos about plastic pollution. These two videos urge me to think what we are throwing away?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/van_jones_the_economic_injustice_of_plastic.html">Van Jones: The economic injustice of plastic | Video on TED.com</a></p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/van_jones_the_economic_injustice_of_plastic.html" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/capt_charles_moore_on_the_seas_of_plastic.html">Charles Moore: Seas of plastic | Video on TED.com</a></p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/capt_charles_moore_on_the_seas_of_plastic.html" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Only man can make products that can not be reused by other species; Plastic bottles are among these products. And most of the pollution industries keep running in developing countries cause the pollution standards are lower and the poor people need work to feed their families. But the pollution will destroy their land first and then the planet follows. No matter for the purpose of helping them or keeping ourselves safe, we all should do something to stop this, stop the throwaway economy.</p>

<p>One way is making zero pollution. Don't develop new pollution industries. Help and supervise our industries to achieve zero pollution.</p>

<p>Second, we should take measures to handle with our present pollution problems. Both the government and education should play a role. We are going to make our daily live zero pollution.</p>

<p>Third, all the countries on the world should collaborate. Many big challenges already laid in front of us. If we can not communicate and collaborate well, then the future of our earth is dim.</p>

<p>What are we throwing away? The plastic bottles? The seas of plastic? The living space and resources for next generations? Or our conscience as a human being and a member on earth?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merry Christmas]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/24/merry-christmas/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T23:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/24/merry-christmas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>亲爱的老婆圣诞节快乐！</p>

<p>今天是12月25号，我离开家到美国访学刚好5个月整。这五个月我知道老婆特别辛苦，也受了不少委屈，不仅仅是因为我在地球的另一端，你没了往日的依靠，而是你还要担负着做不满周岁的宝宝的母亲的责任，以及家庭和工作的双重重担。</p>

<p>2013年2月12号，我们的宝宝然然出生了：）。由于长时间坐着哺乳，大腿血液流通不畅造成了局部组织坏死，你的大腿上留下了两块死斑。你修完产假已经快要放暑假了，我就劝你别去上班了，你说不能耽误工作，结果还是上班了。我知道你很有责任心，也不娇气，但是我还是心疼。</p>

<p>7月25号我出国访学，你送我到机场，当飞机起飞的那一刹那，我的心情很沉重，我知道你将担负起整个家庭的责任。婆媳关系本来就难处，但你却处理的很好，从没有跟妈拌过嘴。</p>

<p>QQ聊天时你经常跟我说头晕，我知道你睡眠不足。你经常要熬夜赶稿子，我嘴上说“不要把工作带到家里”，实际上是不想你熬夜，因为我知道你第二天还要早起，要坐两个小时的公交车才能到学校。以前在家里，一般都是我送你出门，你经常来不及在家吃早饭，到了包子铺，你拿了包子就走，我来结账，就是为了赶时间，不迟到。</p>

<p>11月4号下午爸突发脑出血，是你带爸及时去了医院救治，幸亏救治及时咱爸才保平安。当天晚上你守了爸一夜，端屎端尿，这些本来应该是我来做的。我跟妈说，桃子不仅是我的老婆，还是宝宝的妈妈，你们的儿媳，而且还做了本应该由我这个儿子做的事情，你就像对我这个儿子一样对待这个儿媳吧。我也因为你只顾忙着工作，忽略了家里，生过你的气，但是有什么办法呢，该做的总是要做的。但是我还是要说你，健康是第一重要的，下次体检一定要去，要抽出些时间锻炼身体。</p>

<p>祝老婆永远年轻、健康、漂亮！</p>

<p>爱你的老公<br/>
12月24日 圣诞夜<br/>
于佐治亚</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
