<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-15T16:31:53-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let us do 'lecture']]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/15/let-us-do-lecture/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T12:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/15/let-us-do-lecture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I participated the method class by Dr. Luft and responsed to her question "How students learn best? by rehearing something, learning the vocabulary, or by doing science".</p>

<p>My response was: the answer was obvious doing science will let student learn most, but if we take out of the word "best", all approches can help student learn in special situations.</p>

<p>I know it is a little misleading and I am afraid that some students in the classroom might misunderstood me. Well, by saying that, I don't mean we should really repeat our explainations to students again and again or let students master only vocabularies or terms. But I do want say we should not put 'lecutre' on the opposite side of 'inqury'. I also want to point out that we should be very careful to use these two words to label teaching practices, expecially those of student teachers.</p>

<p>Well, lecture, You can lecture; Some teacher is only able to lecture. But if you decide to use lecture, try to do it good. Because lecutrue can be totally different styles and outcomings.</p>

<p>It is interesting -- we did not teach student teachers how to lecture, although this conception exist in their mind, and they are very likely to use this approach in the beginning of their carrers -- isn't it.</p>

<p>Ok, let's do lecture.(really?)<br/>
There are different levels of lectures.<br/>
1.  Some teacher just stands there and say something, whether related or not. Student are very easily lost interests and get boring and then sleeping. Sometime they appear awake, but their mind are sleep.<br/>
2.  Some teacher stand there say something interesting, student are engaged and listen carefully, some can even retell the intersting stories to others. It is better, right.<br/>
3.  Some stand there say something putting students on uncomfortable positions, let students think critically about the demila or issues and discuss with each other, which may have a big impact on what student believe and act in the future.</p>

<p>Some lecturer also do some performance or something tricky or funny; Some lecture even let audience participate, here is a example of <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZGY0wPAnus">TED lecture: the art of misdirection</a>. Whether lecture or inquiry, they are just labels. Label itself can not gurantee your teaching quality and students' learning outcomes. We should keep this in mind.</p>

<p>In fact, what teachers can do and only do is creat learning opportunitiy by engaging student in learning activities. Student learn new knowledge through their learning experience. But, different learning experience have different concequences. The following is the learnig pyriod.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/learningpyramid.png" alt="learning pyramid" /></p>

<p>You can see from the picture above, student can sit and listen, learn by listenning and reading. This process just get information into their short term memory not long term memory. So they may just listen and forget, rarely transfer the new knowledge into new situations.</p>

<p>They can also study by doing science,trying to figure out questions such as what can I do with this stuff ? How to relate all these stuff? What data to collect? How to collect? What is happenning? What is going to happen? Why it happen? Why it doesn't happen? and so on. This approach not only work on the working memory, but also interact with the long term memory. They have to recall what they had learned and experienced in order to solve all these problems.</p>

<p>In the learning pyramid, the most effective way is learning by teaching,just as what the student teacher are doing now. Usually we suppose student teachers already have enough content knowledge for teaching the topic, but it is not ture. Many studies showed that begining teachers' content knowledge are usually Fragmented and less connected, it was also structured for doing test not teaching.[] Maybe it is enough for exam but not teaching.</p>

<p>Inquiry research showed that good inquiry are significantly better than lecture, but it has a precondition -- the teacher have good knowledge ground.[] But students usually lack of this ground, they are stuglling with intergrating inquiry into their lessons. It is not an easy thing acheived overnight, but a step by step continuing process.</p>

<p>Recently, I read a book review <a href="http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108010/chapters/Learning,-or-Not-Learning,-in-School.aspx">Learning,or not Learning,in school</a>. The author of the book argued teacher can not give a model or demonstrition, and then let student follow the model to do on their own(the mistake I also made in my teaching). There should be some middle stages, such as discussing or doing together or let students do it collaboratly, before let them do it by their own. The big idea is Gradually ownership shifting, or gradual release of responsibility. It is not a new idea, but I like it.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/learningshift.png" alt="learning shift" />
This picture is from: <a href="http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108010/chapters/Learning,-or-Not-Learning,-in-School.aspx">Learning,or not Learning,in school</a></p>

<p>Why I want to highlight the point that DO NOT put lecture in the opposite position of Iquiry, I have other concerns. Try to think:</p>

<blockquote><p>What happen if student teacher believe in inquiry but can not do it well?</p>

<blockquote><p>They drop out. Because they tend to believe themselves not suitable for teaching.</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Another extrim concern is:</p>

<blockquote><p>What happen if teacher only believe lecture and only one direction approach?</p>

<blockquote><p>They refuse to change.</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>We were taught to not label students, right? We also should avoid to label teachers. Abused labels can cause problems even disasters, for example, students who labeled themselves as visual learner would say, I can't learn very well because the teacher used very little pictures, similations. In fact, the label just limit students' learning approaches instead of expanding.</p>

<p>Who should take the responsibility for learning? Teacher? Students? Or both? Or the responsibility gradually shift from teacher to students?</p>

<p>What stratiges or methods are suitable for this shifting?</p>

<p>These are the questions that are worth to think over.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assess for Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/14/assess-for-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-14T13:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/14/assess-for-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to a the seminar <a href="http://www.ctl.uga.edu/node/486">Teaching and Assessing so Your Students Learn More: Maximizing Learning-Centered Pedagogy</a> by Dr. Phyllis Blumberg.</p>

<p>We did some interactive activities,such as drawing a picture of learning-centered teaching, think and discuss, group disscussion of a special topic and report. I attended the discussion of how to use assessment to promote students' learning with 6 people.</p>

<p>Although most participants are college faculties, but when assigned to group work, some tend to speak more than the others, unaware of someone not speaking a word. I want to rearrange the process by divided into two small groups, but I feel hard to interupt and unsure which way will work better. Athough we do discussed sometimes one student dominates the group work and coversation, some people are too shy to say anything. You see, sometimes people say it but not do it and even unaware of this inconsistence.</p>

<p>There are various assessments that can be used for different purposes.<br/>
Before class you can give students questiong to guide their reading and explore their prior ideas.</p>

<pre><code>multiple choice question  
guiding questions  
open questions  
Dilemma  
Senario  
judgement  
</code></pre>

<p>In class, you can give student short quiz to know if students get the point of if they are able to apply them.</p>

<pre><code>Clicker  
Online analysis  
Open questions and discussion  
short quiz  
Drawing      
</code></pre>

<p>After class, assignments can help students review, exercise and enhance what they learned.</p>

<pre><code>Online assessment  
observation  
hand-on  
Reading  
Design  
Problem soving  
exercise  
learning activities judgement and improvement  
</code></pre>

<p>Final exam can report students' acheivement.</p>

<pre><code>interview(when there are only several students, this would be a good choice)  
project(which let student really take the ownership)  
write a paper/story  
design  
make vedio/prezi  
oral presentation/defence  
Fair or competition  
Paper exam  
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The passion of his life]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/the-passion-of-his-life/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T19:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/the-passion-of-his-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>He was a UGA professor. He died today, of a Severe disease. His wife is also a UGA professor in Pysics Department. She said his husband only left two sentences to his friends and students in UGA.</p>

<p>First, he just say GOODBYE.</p>

<p>Second, he said must guarantee every student have access to his collection, because it is really his passion--lifelong passion.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[learning or not learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/learning-or-not-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T12:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/13/learning-or-not-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Learning is dangerous; Not learning is lethal.</p>

<p>Why learning is dangerous? Because when are learning you have to change--habits, beliefs,knowledge,actions and so on, every change may let you sit in an uncomfortable place unsure of the following consequence.</p>

<p>But not learning is lethal. Because the world change in every minutes, even every seconds, if you act the same way as before, you will be very likely lost your job, get a stroke and worry about your food and Pension.</p>

<p>What to do then?</p>

<p>Learn with a teacher, learn with your friends and learn in your own feasible and effective ways. Of course you have to study how learning happen to you at first.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HungerU]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T14:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to MLC to attend a lecture by Dr Michelle Smith. In front of MLC, I saw a strange thing. You can see the picture below.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hungeru.png" alt="hungeru" /></p>

<p>The fact and statistics is printed on it. Food still occupy a large percentage(39.8%) in their total household spend. In Congo, 70% goes to food, it means people there are more likely in hunger.</p>

<p>I asked where is the data from? They told me they gathered these data last Saturday, and the survey is still going on.</p>

<p>How can I participate? I asked. Just let people know this fact and then we can change this fact and statistic. Isn't it a good idea? College students may not give money directly, but they can collect data and spread the fact all over the world.</p>

<p>Although the program is funded by Farm Journal Foundation, I guess volunteer college students played a role in the Survey and HungerU Tour in different countries. This is the responsibility that our college students are able to and should shoulder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
