<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-09T14:01:17-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticism is not critical thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-19T19:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Tony asked our students to make up a skit to show their image of schooling. This activity provide opportunities for students to speak English and express their ideas or images of schooling which may be the first step to realize and change their own teaching perspective.</p>

<p>During the activities, an interesting phenomenon showed up. Most of them criticized the education they had in China. While,it was true that the Chinese education had many problems. But, the thinking and reasoning of the problematic educational phenomenon is shallow, or not deep enough, in other word, critical thinking is missing.</p>

<p>In order to get more from this activity, students should not jump up to conclusion too quickly. They should not ignore the context that these things took place, the social context, the historical context, the economic context, the physical context, and so on. They should also rethink the theories and rationals behind their judgement and carefully examine the proof and logic. In short, critical thinking should take the place of criticism.</p>

<p>Why harsh criticism of people's own education is not good even harmful? First, it easily leads to extreme and skin deep thinking which block more intellectual endeavor. Second, it hurt their self-image and self-confidence. Third, it can easily separate their connection with the previous themselves and places. Extreme criticisms call abandon or escape but not improvement and responsibility. Try to think of place-based learning, it heals the disconnection between people and places while harsh criticism do the opposite.</p>

<p>According to Daniel T. Willingham, critical thinking have three key features: effectiveness, novelty, and self-direction. Critical thinking is effective in that it avoids common pitfalls, such as seeing only one side of an issue, discounting new evidence that disconfirms your ideas, reasoning from passion rather than logic, failing to support statemnts with evidence, and so on.</p>

<p>Critical thinking is novel in that you don't simply remember a solution or a situation that is similar enough to guide you. Using a complex algorithm to solve a math problem is not critical thinking. But devising a new algorithm is. Critical thinking is self-directed in that the thinker must be calling the shot(making desicions themselves): awards or punishment will disrupt instead of promote critical thinking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Norma Rose Point School]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T22:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have been in BC for 3days. Everything is new for our ECNU students, the beautiful campus of UBC, the long NO 44 bus, the comfortable Landmark hotel, the nice professors and staffs, the exciting learning activities.</p>

<p>Today is even special. We went to visit a middle school called <a href="http://go.vsb.bc.ca/schools/normarosepoint/Pages/default.aspx">Norma Rose Point School</a>. The school is not far from UBC, in fact it is the neighborhood of UBC. It took us about 20 or 30 minutes to walk there from Scarfe building where our classroom located. There are about six hundreds of students in the school, from kindergarten to grade 8, including both elementary and secondary education. This school is very unique because of its educational rationals and teaching building design.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/ROSE_Point_school.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>They believe learning should be integrated and take place in communities instead of separated and in classrooms of each discipline. They want to give student a whole picture of the world and want them to experience this by themselves in their learning communities. In this way, students get better understanding of who they are, where they come form, how they will change the world around them. They will also take more responsibility of their learning and be proactive to inquiry the world around them rather listen to the teacher and memorize for tests.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/global_issues.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Community_learning_outcome.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The learning schedule and activities are designed and carried out by a faculty team but not a single teacher as traditionally school usually do. The teacher love this kind of collaborative teaching, it also give teacher many opportunities to learn from each others. It is much easier for new teacher to join the team to teach together. As you can see, they value collaboration very much. Student collaborate with student, teachers and even parents. Teacher collaborate with colleges, parents, and university professors. Student who are good at something can teach others. Teacher can do the same thing. They are all super heroes at that time. Super hero is a learning activity designed by the 4th grade teacher team which engage students and let them rethink what a hero means.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/grade4_learning_schedual.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Many features of the school building reflect educational wisdom. They make a window to let student who play basketball to look downstairs and notice what is happening in the football playground. All the classrooms are open without a door but only three or two walls. It means guests are always welcome to join or observe the class. There are also lots of art crafts made by student to show their understanding of their school spirits.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/art_crafts.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/open_classroom.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>It is hard to believe such an ideal school can exist and survive. ARE there any disadvantages and challenges for this kind of school? Of course there are, but who can deny their bold spirit and unique learning place design. It is beautiful! That is enough for now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NARST 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2015/04/17/narst-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-17T13:24:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2015/04/17/narst-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second time I attend NARST. Like last time, lots of thing is going on at the same time, but I can catch much more than before.</p>

<p>Here are some pictures of my presentations and my academic families.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/NARST2015_chunlei1.jpg" alt="Chunlei Presenting 1" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/NARST2015_chunlei2.jpg" alt="Chunlei Presenting 2" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Liu_family.jpg" alt="With Professor Liu family" /></p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/raw/master/Luft_family.jpg" alt="With Dr Luft family" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/NARST2015_Chicago_day.jpg" alt="Chicago on day" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/NARST2015_Chicago_Night.jpg" alt="Chicago on night" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NoS and PCK and CK]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2015/04/13/nos-and-pck-and-ck/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-13T04:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2015/04/13/nos-and-pck-and-ck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday(04,02,2015) I attend NARST 2015 session#3 stand 4(Science teaching--Middle and high school Grade 5-12) and strand 8 (The handbook of research on science education: implications for inservice teacher education) and strand 13 (History, Philosophy, and Sociology of science). In summary, it was all about PCK, PK and NoS.</p>

<p>There are two lines of questions to address:<br/>
What is the difference between PK and PCK? What is PK? Is there any Pedagogy content free? What is knowledge?<br/>
There are always content for teaching, right? You can not teaching nothing, can you? But of course, you can teach anything. You can also teach teaching, even at this time, you still need something as your teaching object in you examples or as your context. Sometimes we cannot think clearly about PK and PCK, because we do not make our view of knowledge clear. I will argue that Knowledge need to have some function for a population to exist and pass on from generation to generation. CK is about how the world works. Some people need to understand science. Some need to be able to do science. Some people apply science to improve living level. While, PK, in the context of science education, is all about how teacher help students learn science, how teaching works. It help teachers understand the what is teaching, how to teach better, why some strategies work while some not. Just like package, teacher need to know what content is inside? How is this content different from others? and which package suit for this content? How to make the package? how does this package work? how does it bridge the content and the students. How students approach this package? Did we use the right package in the right way?</p>

<p>Why NoS? Why NoS teaching fail? Why researchers suggest to use explicit way to teach NoS? What do you mean by explict?<br/>
We don't select to teach NoS simply for more and more researchers ask to do so. We do teach NoS because it has value for student to understant science, do science and apply science. Sometimes, we expect that students can learn NoS by themselves through science practices. But it is wrong. Researchers found that it is hard for students grasp NoS themselves. In this case, teachers should teach NoS purposely. They should design their lesson with NoS in mind and get students there intentionally. The explict way of teaching NoS, is not just tell the student what science is, but guide students' attention to it. It is not give students a bird, but show them where the bird located. For example, give student a bird locked in a cage help students feel and see where the bird is. But do we need improve their bird seeking skills? or do we just care the have the bird. To address this questions another way, Which is more important? To discover NoS through science practise or just understand NoS which reflect a better image of science(the image that science education reseachers and scientist captured). The answer is both are valuable learning outcomes. The process and the result both matter.</p>

<p>Don't put the car in front of the house.</p>

<p>Pay attention to the details.</p>

<p>Fit or not?<br/>
English writing?<br/>
Major fake?<br/>
Blind</p>

<p>You may change or you may refuse to change, but you have to respond to not buy very requests.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cognitive Apprenticeship]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T13:11:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/09/22/cognitive-apprenticeship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sawyer, R. (2006). The Cambridge handbook of the learning sciences. (R. K. Sawyer, Ed.). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. doi:10.1017/CBO9780511816833</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Mscare.png" alt="Cognitive Apprenticeship" /></p>

<p>Method(Mscare):<br/>
Ways to promote the development of expertise<br/>
*  Modeling: teacher performs a task so students can observe<br/>
*  Scaffolding: teacher provides supports to help the student perform a task<br/>
*  Coaching: teacher observes and facilitates while students perform a task<br/>
*  Articulation: teacher encourages students to verbalize their knowledge and thinking<br/>
*  Reflection: teacher enables students to compare their performance with others<br/>
*  Exploration: teacher invites students to pose and solve their own problems</p>

<p>认知性学徒机制在网络社区甚至大学的学习实践中非常值得关注。在学习活动设计时，也应该遵循和利用上图所提到的步骤和原则。</p>

<p>比如这个表格所提到的内容、方法、次序和社区，在学习活动设计的时候就可以好好加以参照。</p>

<p>例如对于教学设计的学习：<br/>
一、内容<br/>
专业知识：前端分析（学习内容、学习者、学习需要）、教学目标设定和表述、设计教学思路和过程落实重难点、学习成果的评价设计、在具体教学情境下实施并优化。<br/>
一般性学习策略： 阅读材料、观察教学录像、见习、与专家教师交流、与同学相互交流、尝试设计和实施教学活动、自我反思。<br/>
控制策略：制定学习目标和学习计划、记录学习进度、提前准备、主动参与、主动寻求帮助、反思和总结、树立更有挑战的学习目标、掌控时间。<br/>
学习方法：通过反复强化练习口语以心理素质、通过优秀设计和教学视频找到自己的短板并模仿和创新、通过与专家教师的交流了解教学设计背后的思考和专家教师的思考和工作模式、通过微格训练锻炼基本的教学技能、通过阅读文献了解学生前科学概念研究成果、通过网络搜索查找教学素材和科学史内容。</p>

<p>二、方法<br/>
教师演示或者观看专家教师课堂录像<br/>
作为助教与一线教师共同授课或者分析课后作业<br/>
教师对师范生的学习活动组织的具体环节和过程进行校正和点评<br/>
指导老师帮助师范生理清自己的教学思路、活动和活动意图<br/>
鼓励师范生与其他师范生或者指导老师的教学做比较（目标、课堂气氛、教学技巧、学习效果等）<br/>
指导教师鼓励师范生思考和解决自己教学中遇到的问题</p>

<p>三、次序<br/>
教学设计任务应该：<br/>
由简单到复杂（观看视频、分析教学线索和设计意图、了解学生、分析内容、设计和表述教学目标、设计思路、收集素材、设计过程、学习效果评价的设计、评课、设计完整的一堂课、说课）<br/>
由一般情境到多种情境（初中、高中；农村、城市；普通、重点；传统、创新）<br/>
由总体概括到具体任务</p>

<p>四、社区<br/>
实际到中学去，看一看、相一想、试一试<br/>
建立网络分享、互助、活动学习社区<br/>
建立与一线教师和专家教师的专业对话<br/>
建立见习、实习的基地和教学训练的小组活动常规<br/>
激励内部动机，向着专家教师努力<br/>
学会集体合作、树立并完成更有挑战性的目标</p>

<p>对于此书感兴趣的人，其目录如下：<br/>
Contents</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction: The New Science of Learning 1<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</li>
</ol>


<p>part i<br/>
FOUNDATIONS<br/>
2 . Foundations and Opportunities for an Interdisciplinary Science of Learning 19<br/>
John D. Bransford, Brigid Barron, Roy D. Pea, Andrew Meltzoff, Patricia Kuhl, Philip Bell, Reed Stevens, Daniel L. Schwartz, Nancy Vye, Byron Reeves, Jeremy Roschelle, and Nora H. Sabelli<br/>
3. Constructionism 35<br/>
Yasmin B. Kafai<br/>
4. Cognitive Apprenticeship 47<br/>
Allan Collins<br/>
5. Cognitive Tutors: Technology Bringing Learning Sciences<br/>
to the Classroom 61<br/>
Kenneth R. Koedinger and Albert Corbett<br/>
6. Learning in Activity 79<br/>
James G. Greeno<br/>
7. Knowledge Building: Theory, Pedagogy, and Technology 97<br/>
Marlene Scardamalia and Carl Bereiter</p>

<p>part ii<br/>
METHODOLOGIES<br/>
8. Learner-Centered Design: Reflections on the Past and Directions for the Future 119<br/>
Chris Quintana, Namsoo Shin, Cathleen Norris, and Elliot Soloway<br/>
9. The Evolution of Design Studies as Methodology 135<br/>
Jere Confrey<br/>
10. Design-Based Research: A Methodological Toolkit for the Learning Scientist 153<br/>
Sasha Barab<br/>
11. Guiding Inquiry-Based Math Learning 171<br/>
Paul Cobb and Kay McClain<br/>
12 . Analyzing Collaborative Discourse 187<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer<br/>
13. Assessing for Deep Understanding 205<br/>
Sharon M. Carver</p>

<p>part iii<br/>
THE NATURE OF KNOWLEDGE<br/>
14. Case-Based Reasoning 225<br/>
Janet L. Kolodner<br/>
15. The Knowledge Integration Perspective on Learning and Instruction 243<br/>
Marcia C. Linn<br/>
16. A History of Conceptual Change Research: Threads and Fault Lines 265<br/>
Andrea A. diSessa<br/>
17. Spatial Representations and Imagery in Learning 283<br/>
Daniel L. Schwartz and Julie Heiser<br/>
18. Literacy and the Learning Sciences 299<br/>
Annemarie Sullivan Palincsar and Barbara G. Ladewski</p>

<p>part iv<br/>
MAKING KNOWLEDGE VISIBLE<br/>
19. Project-Based Learning 317<br/>
Joseph S. Krajcik and Phyllis C. Blumenfeld<br/>
20. Making Authentic Practices Accessible to Learners: Design Challenges and Strategies 335<br/>
Daniel C. Edelson and Brian J. Reiser<br/>
21. BioKIDS: An Animated Conversation on the Development of Curricular Activity Structures for Inquiry Science 355<br/>
Nancy Butler Songer<br/>
22. Cultivating Model-Based Reasoning in Science Education 371<br/>
Richard Lehrer and Leona Schauble<br/>
23. Exploring Mathematics Through Construction and Collaboration 389<br/>
Richard Noss and Celia Hoyles</p>

<p>part v<br/>
LEARNING TOGETHER<br/>
24. Computer-Supported Collaborative Learning 409<br/>
Gerry Stahl, Timothy Koschmann, and Daniel D. Suthers<br/>
25. WILD for Learning: Interacting Through New Computing Devices Anytime, Anywhere 427<br/>
Roy D. Pea and Heidy Maldonado<br/>
26. Arguing to Learn 443<br/>
Jerry Andriessen<br/>
27. Learning in Online Communities 461<br/>
Amy Bruckman<br/>
part vi<br/>
LEARNING ENVIRONMENTS<br/>
28. Motivation and Cognitive Engagement in Learning Environments 475<br/>
Phyllis C. Blumenfeld, Toni M. Kempler, and Joseph S. Krajcik<br/>
29. Learning as a Cultural Process: Achieving Equity Through Diversity 489<br/>
Na’ilah Suad Nasir, Ann S. Rosebery, Beth Warren, and Carol D. Lee<br/>
30. Prospects for Transforming Schools with Technology- Supported Assessment 505<br/>
Barbara Means<br/>
31. Internet Use in Schools: Promise and Problems 521<br/>
Janet Ward Schofield<br/>
32. Teacher Learning Research and the Learning Sciences 535<br/>
Barry J. Fishman and Elizabeth A. Davis<br/>
33. Scaling Up: Evolving Innovations Beyond Ideal Settings to Challenging Contexts of Practice 551<br/>
Chris Dede<br/>
34. Conclusion: The Schools of the Future 567<br/>
R. Keith Sawyer</p>

<p>Afterword: After How Comes What 581<br/>
Seymour Papert<br/>
Epilogue: The Fundamental Issue in the Learning Sciences 587<br/>
Roger C. Schank<br/>
Author Index 593<br/>
Subject Index</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
