<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-29T22:43:28+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Epistemological beliefs]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/11/25/epistemological-beliefs/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-25T23:34:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/11/25/epistemological-beliefs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Epistemological beliefs is about what knowledge and knowing is and is not.</p>

<p>Read the following paper to know more about EB.</p>

<p>Kampa, N., Neumann, I., Heitmann, P., &amp; Kremer, K. (2016). Epistemological beliefs in science—a person-centered approach to investigate high school students' profiles. Contemporary educational psychology, 46, 81-93.</p>

<pre><code>The four factors split into two factors in the area of nature of knowledge ([1] certainty and [2] development of scientific knowl- edge) and two factors in the area of nature of knowing ([3] source and [4] justification of scientific knowing).

1.certainty.   
Beliefs on the certainty of knowledge span from viewing scientific knowledge as either being right or wrong (naïve) to viewing scientific knowledge as a reflection from more than one perspective (sophisticated). 

2.development.  
Beliefs on the development of knowledge span from viewing scientific knowledge as a static and unchanging subject (naïve) to accepting that scientific ideas and theories change over time in light of new evidence (sophisticated). 

3.source.  
Beliefs on the source of knowing refer to viewing knowledge as residing in external authorities such as scientists or teachers (naïve) versus viewing knowledge as created within the student (sophisticated). 

4.justification.  
Beliefs on the justification of knowing refer to discovering phenomena through scientific investigations, e.g., experiment or observation (naïve) versus understanding that knowledge comes from reasoning, thinking, and multiple experimentations as well as observations (sophisticated; Conley et al., 2004).
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elegy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/08/26/elegy/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T22:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/08/26/elegy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Elegy翻译为挽歌，是一部2008年的电影。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/elegy.jpg" alt="Elegy" />
Human is a kind of social animal that can not live alone. If he does live alone, he fades. When he interacts with others, he thrives.</p>

<p>In this sense, human being is like a neuron and the society is the neutral network.</p>

<p>Once I believe that I can think, but after carefully thinking I draw a conclustion that I can hardly thinking independently. For example, if live me alone in dark room I can think less and less.</p>

<p>In fact, people do not think, they just reflect or interact with the environment. This truth is hard to believe, but it is important to know if you really want to direct your life.</p>

<p>A philosopher once said that there are two kind of people in the world, those who divide things into two kinds and those do not. I don't know what the philosopher want to say, but the philosopher must be the former. There are both advantage and disadvantage in dividing things into two kinds.</p>

<p>There is an old saying in China, when the flower bloom pick it, do not wait untill it shrivels. God is a time keeper, he just counts and when he stop your life come to the end. When the time come, you may regret the stupid time you spend but nothing you can change. It is really a tragedy. Tragedy teach you the lesson.</p>

<p>In front of the god time keeper, you have to be honest to seek what you really want because you have to face yourself and you have only one chance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 4 characteristics of 21st century learning - ABCD]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/07/28/the-4-characteristics-of-21st-centry-learning-abcd/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-28T20:56:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2018/07/28/the-4-characteristics-of-21st-centry-learning-abcd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The learing in 21st century becomes so different from the past, which need us to rethink our present schooling and relearn the conception of learning.</p>

<p>OECD, UNESCO, P21 all highlighted the importancs of 21st century skills, but there is no one sigle approach agreed to acceive this goal. They did agree on some characteristics of effective learning environment for preparing these skills. The list of characteristics of of 21st century learning environment may be long and hard to remember, so I want to highlight 4 most important characteristics which can be easily abbreviated as ABCD.</p>

<p>A. Autonomous<br/>
Students can actively engaged in learning as an autonomous learner. They can take the control of their learning by setting the learning goals, selecting appropriate learning content and  methods with the partner they like.They also take the responsibilities for their own learning.</p>

<p>B. Blended<br/>
The learning content should be connected across disciplines and subjects. The experience in and out of school should also be bridged. Blended learning take place where learners learn blended content in a blended way.</p>

<p>C. Collaborative<br/>
This characteristic reveals the importance of the social nature of learning. The school should not only promote student’s hard working as a individual, but also provide more chances for students to collaborated with each others. Because the 21st century talents will work in globally collaborative environment where cooperation and communication skills mater very much.</p>

<p>D. Differentiated<br/>
Technology rich learning environment give the advantage of supporting each student differently according to their needs and preferences. Learning should be differentiated to help students get most gain from their learning processes, rather than following the same route and pace in a teacher-centered classroom.</p>

<p>Of course, the list can keep growing, but these four characteristics should be recoginzed and put into practice frist by teachers, learners and learning environment engineers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[加拿大卓越教师项目总结]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/13/ubc-program-summary/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-13T12:48:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/13/ubc-program-summary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>21天的紧张学习，一次特别意义的春节，3次新奇而愉快校园之旅，在我们全员参与的一场快闪热舞之后落下帷幕。有<a href="https://v.qq.com/x/page/a0371cjogl2.html">视频</a>为证。</p>

<p><embed src="https://imgcache.qq.com/tencentvideo_v1/playerv3/TPout.swf?max_age=86400&v=20161117&vid=a0371cjogl2&auto=0" allowFullScreen="true" quality="high" width="480" height="400" align="middle" allowScriptAccess="always" type="application/x-shockwave-flash"></embed></p>

<p>这次培训项目是Tony老师为我们师范生精心准备和量身打造的、高质量的课程。当中 有很多教育理念、教学技巧、策略以及教学活动都值得未来教师教育项目参考和借鉴。</p>

<p>其中给我形象最为深刻的活动如下：<br/>
1、教育印象（image of schooling: An image about teaching or learning that has some meaning to you）<br/>
2、劈叉苦茶 Pechakucha Pairs(15seconds X20 pages) 开学第一天就明确最后作业<br/>
Planning Sheet for Pechakucha- peer review<br/>
3、在地性学习（place-based learning -- interviewing the campus）<br/>
4、读书进程 （Reading Schedule）<br/>
5、TPI survey<br/>
6、Multiple Intelligence survey<br/>
7、学习经历短剧（Skit that illustrates your experience as a student）<br/>
8、学校观察（New understanding and questions about teachers, students, subject matter, Milieux）<br/>
9、个体帮助（Meet with professor Marina Milner-Bolotin）<br/>
10、社会和情感学习能力（Self-awareness, Social awareness, Responsible decision-making, self-management, relationship skills）</p>

<h3>教育策略及其背后理念:</h3>

<p>可视化（教育是认知加工辅助）如画示意图<br/>
游戏化（教育是刺激反应连接）如开展比赛，教师团队和学生团队pk，4人讲同一主题，两两一组，同课异构，相互PK，一方做教师另外一方就做学生，另外4人担任裁判，做教学记录，并最终在支持的一方处签名。<br/>
民主化（教育是社会文化转型）如让学生决定准备时间，分权而不是控制<br/>
意义化（教育是意义主动构建）如参观学校主动构建对学校教育的理解</p>

<h3>具体的做法和技巧：</h3>

<p>Philosophy of teaching statement<br/>
short test<br/>
Fill the form sheet to draw your conclusion</p>

<h3>Group work</h3>

<p>1、Think-pair-share<br/>
2、Jigsaw<br/>
3、Three step interview(interview alternate and then share in group)<br/>
4、Group Investigation(找到共同兴趣点、计划研究内容、研究任务分工、分析、总结、报告)</p>

<p>divide into different groups by taking off a shoe</p>

<h3>Inquiry based activities</h3>

<p>1、Use factoid to provoke student questions(e.g.: Tornadoes are nearly invisible whirling winds until dust and debris are picked up or a cloud forms inside the funnel.)<br/>
2、Push student thinking by asking questions(What do you wonder about now? Does this suggest any new approaches, ideas to you worth investigating? what kinds of connections can you make? where do we go from here?)<br/>
3、Slow down<br/>
4、Be on the look out for student's questions and persistent interests<br/>
5、Use previous activities to move forward<br/>
6、Help students make sense of non-fiction text（by different symbols）</p>

<p>促进学生思考的策略：<br/>
分享教学目标、关键问题或面临的挑战<br/>
随机提问<br/>
Wait Time<br/>
澄清或转述学生的回答<br/>
追问（为什么？你同意吗？你能举个例子吗？）<br/>
让学生总结（你可以总结一下小丽的观点吗？）<br/>
克制价值判断性言论<br/>
让学生外化思维过程（你是怎么得出这个答案的？）<br/>
信息可视化（如图片组织者）</p>

<p>简单学习策略<br/>
时间伙伴（clock buddies）<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/clock_buddies.png" alt="clock buddiest" />
Think, Pair, Share(2分钟独立思考，2分钟同伴交流，最后班级分享)<br/>
图形组织者<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/graphic_organizer.png" alt="graphic organizert" /><br/>
PMI chart<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/PMI.png" alt="PMI chart" /></p>

<p>更复杂的学习策略<br/>
3 step interview（访谈者，被访谈者，报告员，3个主题的访谈，每一轮角色轮换一次）<br/>
角色扮演\skit（情景短剧）<br/>
拼图Jigsaw（每组派一名学生去专家组学习，然后返回学习小组进行分享）<br/>
Place Mat<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/PlaceMat.png" alt="Place Mat" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LeSoleil Fine Art Gallery]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/09/lesoleil-fine-art-gallery/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-09T12:20:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/02/09/lesoleil-fine-art-gallery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was wandering around in Vancouver BC last month, I found a art gallery along the Howe Street by chance. It is called LeSoleil Fine Art Gallery.</p>

<p>It was raining and I had some time, so I decided to have a look inside of the gallery. One artist's painting named "That Night the Magic Mirror" attracted my attention. The artist's name is Cecilia Aisin-Gioro (爱新觉罗.恒钦). She is the grandniece of the last Chinese Emperor Pu Yi Aisin-Gioro.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/that-night-the-magic-mirror.jpg" alt="That Night the Magic Mirror original" /></p>

<p>You can find more paintings of her <a href="http://lesoleilfineart.com/cecilia-aisin-gioro">here</a>.</p>

<p>At my first look of the picture, the woman is very beautiful and youthful, but herself in the mirror seems less energetic. When you look the picture carefully, you will found a mistake(or unnatural phenomenon) in the picture. Take your time to have a look.</p>

<p>The woman have two left arms, one you can see directly, one in the mirror, without right arm. What does Cecilia want to say? or it is just a mistake?</p>

<p>The other thing I don't like is the face in the mirror. It is flat and dull comparing with her real face.</p>

<p>So I changed it like this.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/that-night-the-magic-mirror11.jpg" alt="That Night the Magic Mirror changed" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
