<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-14T19:04:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swimming pool finally found in Remsey Center]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/swimming-pool-finally-found-remsey-center/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T18:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/12/swimming-pool-finally-found-remsey-center</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally find a swimming poor that I can have access in UGA. It is in the Remsey Center just take the next stop of Aderhold by East-West School Bus. I purchased a membership for three months($15 per month). Today I went there to work out and swim. It is really worth every cents.</p>

<p>I took several pictures:<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/work-out.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I often see people running on the road to do exercise. Sometimes man, sometimes old men stripped to the waist, sometimes women with young boy or girls. In fact, the road in Athens are not flat, so they have to run up and down. They really got the admirable sport spirits.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>
The following is a picture of the swimming pool taken from a window.  The water is blue and there many students swimming like fish in the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/swimming-pool.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Today the climbing wall is open for free. It will be one day for free per month. So if you want to try, don't miss the boat. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/climbing-wall.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I am too tired after swimming to try it. May be next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A list of science labs that rocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T00:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/10/a-list-of-science-labs-that-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will make a list of science labs activities which are so fun and interesting that you can't miss.</p>

<p>Real Labs<br/>
+   Secret tube(modeling)<br/>
+   Candle in the tube above water(causal model)<br/>
+   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3600?ref=search">Transpiration lab</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/careerstart-grade8/5540">Cell theory and plant respiration G8</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/editions/criticalthinking/6650">Water quality - Critical thinking in science</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://www.learnnc.org/lp/pages/3226?ref=search">Amazing amaryllis activitiesm G2-3 4Ws</a></p>

<p>Hands on activities<br/>
+   <a href="http://www.education.com/activity/article/Sourdough_bread/">Sourdough Science!</a><br/>
+   Making a safty harmer<br/>
+   Design a sprinkler head for watering lawn</p>

<p>Virual Labs/ Simulations<br/>
+   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
+   PhET: <a href="http://phet.colorado.edu/">Free online simulations</a><br/>
+   <a href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/interaction-simulation-based-inquiry-activities/">Interactive simulation based inquiry activities - Chunlei's Blog</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Firefox extension FireGesture Scripts]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/firefox-extension-firegesture-scripts/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T18:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/firefox-extension-firegesture-scripts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found the firefox extension Firegesture is very useful. You can self-define the function of your gestures.</p>

<p>The following are my scripts:<br/>
1.  Sina Weibo(DUDU)<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>var sel = 'http://v.t.sina.com.cn/share/share.php?title='+encodeURIComponent(document.title)+'&amp;url='+encodeURIComponent(window.content.location.href)+'&amp;source=bookmark';
gBrowser.loadOneTab(sel, {
    inBackground: true,
    relatedToCurrent: true
});
</code></pre>

<p></code>
2. iciba(RLR)<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>var word = getBrowserSelection();
if (!word)
    return;
var sel = 'http://www.iciba.com/'+encodeURIComponent(word);
gBrowser.loadOneTab(sel, {
    inBackground: true,
    relatedToCurrent: true
});
</code></pre>

<p></code>
3.  Copy the title and url</p>

<pre><code>
const AS_HTML = false;

function htmlEscape(s) {
  s = s.replace(/&/g, "&amp;");
  s = s.replace(/>/g, "&gt;");
  s = s.replace(/</g, "&lt;");
  s = s.replace(/"/g, "&quot;");
  return s;
}
var url = window.content.location.href;
var title = window.content.document.title;
var txt = AS_HTML ? 
  '<a href="' + htmlEscape(url) + '">' + htmlEscape(title) + '</a>' : 
  title + "\n" + url;
var clipboard = Cc["@mozilla.org/widget/clipboardhelper;1"]
                .getService(Ci.nsIClipboardHelper);
clipboard.copyString(txt);
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strong sense of crisis make a nation grow sturdy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/strong-sense-of-crisis-make-a-nation-grow-sturdy/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T15:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/strong-sense-of-crisis-make-a-nation-grow-sturdy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People who have strong sense of crisis tend to study and practice hard. Nation with strong sense of crisis is more likely to grow sturdy.</p>

<p>American people and Unite States are good examples.</p>

<p>Here are some pictures evidence.<br/>
The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /><br/>
&lt;--!more-->
The safety shower is just at the right of the door.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Safety_Shower.jpg" alt="Emergency Shower in Classroom" /></p>

<p>Im my apartment, there is a white notice like following.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/safetyalert.jpg" alt="Safety Alert in Apartment" /></p>

<p>It doesn't look nice on the door. But it is there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why we teach science in school and how]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T21:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Why</h3>

<p>It is important for students to survive in such an era full of science and technology products and information.<br/>
It is also important for a country to have enough science literate talents and labors in order to survive in the global economy.<br/>
Why science important? You can go on reading another blog post<a href="http://www.letstalkscience.ca/about-us/why-science">Why science?</a></p>

<h3>We</h3>

<p>Science teacher is a career but also a job. They are playing the most important role in developing the science literacy of the next generation. We choose it and we do it.</p>

<h3>Teach</h3>

<p>Good teaching is not an accident. It is a pursely planed activity fiting students' needs and level.</p>

<h3>Science</h3>

<p>Authentic science not just includ scientific knowledge(facts, concepts, theories), but also the process of science and the nature of science.</p>

<h3>In school</h3>

<p>While school education system is still the dominant formal learning place today. So it is an crutial battle feild of science education. But science learning can happen anywhere not just in school.</p>

<h3>Why has science teaching changed over time?</h3>

<p>Science is changing everyday. New discovery, New papers, New theories and models, in fact science update itself everyday.<br/>
Student is changing every year. Students today are not like before. They have iphone, ipad, facebook. Even kids at the same age in different class response significant differently to the same question.<br/>
Society is changing too. It need more talents who are good at 4Cs: Communication, Collaboration, Critical thinking and Creativity.<br/>
Should science teaching keep the same as before? Never.</p>

<h3>How should science be taught in science classrooms?</h3>

<p>Well, It is really a hard question.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
