<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: en | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-01T13:39:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[what robot can do]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/what-robot-can-do/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T20:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/what-robot-can-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am very interested in robot. I believed that someday it can play a very important role in our society and personal life.</p>

<p>There are many amazing things that robot can do. They become more clever and skilled in lots of feild: Some robots talk; Some walk; Some can carry; Some fly; Some can drive; Some teach; Some have expressions; Some have skins.</p>

<p>Today I watched a TED video in which robots help Henry -- a stroke patient -- regain his life.</p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/henry_evans_and_chad_jenkins_meet_the_robots_for_humanity.html" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>What robot can do? It depends on what they are used for. In the global market, if you want a awesome job, learn and do something that robots can't do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eco-life Design and Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/eco-life-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T18:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/eco-life-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In agriculture age,people don't have to worry about pollution. Because all the products are degradable. Nature itself is a great designer, everything can be reused and recycled. But as human entered the age of industry, the situation changed. Human want to create new stuff that never existed in natural world. Yes they made it but they are not born good designers; Many waste are produced but can not be recycled.</p>

<p>There is a simple logic. If human want live in earth forever, then everything should be recycled, otherwise there will be not enough resources or room for human beings.</p>

<p>China have made a miracle of economic growth, but the growth cost dear -- air and water pollution, increasing gap between rich and poor, village and city, east and west. This growth also can not be sustainable because the environment is getting worse and worse and the resources is getting fewer and fewer. In order to live a healthy life, China must reconsider its style of economic growth and design more environmentally friendly industry,agriculture and living system. But do China have enough designers to design the eco-life system? It is questionalble. STEM education may play a crucial role in preparing these future designers in China.</p>

<p>If you look into Chinese secondary and primary curriculum, you will find there is little content of enginering or designing in their class learning activities. How to assess the curriculum content to tell if it is updated and suitable for preparing future citizens? How teachers address this problem in their classroom teaching? Is there a lack of designing education in our curriculum system? If not, is the content and education good enough for preparing our future designers? These questions matters for the future development of China.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emotion control]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/emotion-control/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-25T00:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/25/emotion-control</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes people lost control of their emotion, which usually do harm to themselves and others. It is an very important thing to learn to control and even make use of one's emotion.</p>

<p>Emotion takes long time to form and change. It is like the parameters in hidden layer of NN, taking more instances to evolve and even more instances to adapt themselves to new changes. Emotion can help people to judge people and things(e.g.. good or bad, friends or enemy) and decide what to do(e.g.. quit or persist). It can also work as the energy source of people. People are most easily motivated by emotion than reason. Students tend to remember something deeply with a special emotion aroused. You would also feel very strange if you are talking with some people emotionless and feel hard to build trust on his.</p>

<p>Although, emotion play a very important role in our life, but we usually ignore emotion education in our formal or informal education. We should provide opportunity for people to know how emotion affect our cognition and social interactions. How to cope with ones' emotion and keep emotional health.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patent a special knowledge as private property]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/patent-a-special-knowledge-as-private-property/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-23T12:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/patent-a-special-knowledge-as-private-property</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why we introduces the idea of patent?<br/>
Patent is a commercial idea based on market. A patent is a limited property right the government gives inventors in exchange for their agreement to share details of their inventions with the public. Like any other property right, it may be sold, licensed, mortgaged, assigned or transferred, given away, or simply abandoned.[<a href="#1">1</a>] We can see the rationale of patent is to disclose the innovations to public domains for common good. What to do if patents are going to violate this original rationale? Should we still protect patents or abandon it?</p>

<p>What can be patented? What can't or shouldn't?<br/>
In order to apply for a patent the inventor should provide information about how to made and use this invention. Basically, this is a kind of knowledge about "how". So patent is both a special knowledge and a private property(intellectual property). Usually, a private property such as a chair is unique in the world and can not be given to others without losing it. But knowledge and information are different. We can transmit them without losing them. This is how education and media works. Patent means you can know it but you can't use it without license or permission. But people naturally can make use of their knowledge. It should be legal for people to make use of their knowledge to know and help themselves. So there is a question, should a special knowledge be patentable? <br/>
Case 1:<br/>
There is an interesting case about patent. Mr. Bowman bought gene-modified seed from Monsanto company to plant in his form. For that second crop, he bought seeds from a grain elevator filled with a mix of seeds in the reasonable hope that many of them contained Monsanto’s patented Roundup Ready gene.[<a href="#2">2</a>] Monsanto brought Mr. Bowman to the court for abuse of seeds with their patented Roundup Ready gene. Mr. Bowman argued that it is the natural right to make any use of the seeds that you bought. The patent should be in exhaustion when I bought the seeds from grain elevator.</p>

<p>But Mr. Bowman still lost the case. This is what Justice Kagan said:
“Under the patent exhaustion doctrine, Bowman could resell the patented soybeans he purchased from the grain elevator; so too he could consume the beans himself or feed them to his animals. But the exhaustion doctrine does not enable Bowman to make additional patented soybeans without Monsanto’s permission, that is precisely what Bowman did.” [<a href="#3">3</a>]</p>

<p>Case 2<br/>
There is another case, a farmer grow his corn in his form. But his neighborhood grew gene-modified corn, by accident the wind blow the pollen with modified gene to his farm. So his corn also had the modified gene. But the farmer planted corn for a Japan company that only want corn without modified gene. So he can couldn't sell his corn to the company and lost lot of money. Who should pay for his lost?</p>

<p>Case 3<br/>
A family invented a new kind of food(toy for cat). They keep the making process secret. But later it has been stolen and patented. Although they have made this new food for many years, now it become illegal to keep their business without paying for the patent. Is it fair? How about second time independent invention?</p>

<p>Although, in the first case, Mr. Bowman was intently to make use of the loophole of second buying. But it still annoy my nerves when thinking of gene-modified plant take the place of the other plants that farmers can grow and plant without any limitation, gene-modified food went into market without label, modified gene go to other plan species without control. A question emerged from this case is that Should gene be patentable?</p>

<p>How about human gene? Here is an interesting video "Who Owns You? 20% of the Genes in Your Body are Patented".[<a href="#4">4</a>]</p>

<iframe src="http://zhangchunlei.com//player.vimeo.com/video/11755917" width="500" height="281" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This let me reflect the following questions: Should human gene be patentable? Will these patents prohibit us to know more about ourselves and make use our knowledge to benefit ourselves? Will this go against individual human rights? Is patent, or commercialization a good idea in education and human society in future?</p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a id="1">[1]</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent">Patent - Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</a></p>

<p><a id="2">[2]</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/16/business/supreme-court-to-hear-monsanto-seed-patent-case.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=0">Supreme Court to Hear Monsanto Seed Patent Case - NYTimes.com</a></p>

<p><a id="3">[3]</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/14/business/monsanto-victorious-in-genetic-seed-case.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1385229872-QGNdTtZez+JvcDHciXNSIg">Monsanto Victorious in Seed-Patent Case - NYTimes.com</a></p>

<p><a id="4">[4]</a> <a href="http://singularityhub.com/2010/08/11/who-owns-you-20-of-the-genes-in-your-body-are-patented-video/">Who Owns You? 20% of the Genes in Your Body are Patented | Singularity Hub</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What do you ecpect in your life]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/chunlei-and-mathematics/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-23T10:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/chunlei-and-mathematics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following is a visulization designed by myself. It let me think what do I expect in my life.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/birth&amp;death.png" alt="meaning of life" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
