<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: homework | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/homework/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-13T10:11:17+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why we teach science in school and how]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T21:27:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Why</h3>

<p>It is important for students to survive in such an era full of science and technology products and information.<br/>
It is also important for a country to have enough science literate talents and labors in order to survive in the global economy.<br/>
Why science important? You can go on reading another blog post<a href="http://www.letstalkscience.ca/about-us/why-science">Why science?</a></p>

<h3>We</h3>

<p>Science teacher is a career but also a job. They are playing the most important role in developing the science literacy of the next generation. We choose it and we do it.</p>

<h3>Teach</h3>

<p>Good teaching is not an accident. It is a pursely planed activity fiting students' needs and level.</p>

<h3>Science</h3>

<p>Authentic science not just includ scientific knowledge(facts, concepts, theories), but also the process of science and the nature of science.</p>

<h3>In school</h3>

<p>While school education system is still the dominant formal learning place today. So it is an crutial battle feild of science education. But science learning can happen anywhere not just in school.</p>

<h3>Why has science teaching changed over time?</h3>

<p>Science is changing everyday. New discovery, New papers, New theories and models, in fact science update itself everyday.<br/>
Student is changing every year. Students today are not like before. They have iphone, ipad, facebook. Even kids at the same age in different class response significant differently to the same question.<br/>
Society is changing too. It need more talents who are good at 4Cs: Communication, Collaboration, Critical thinking and Creativity.<br/>
Should science teaching keep the same as before? Never.</p>

<h3>How should science be taught in science classrooms?</h3>

<p>Well, It is really a hard question.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
