<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: book | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/book/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-06T12:58:05+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[一人一本书]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/02/22/one-people-one-book/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T23:32:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/02/22/one-people-one-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>一不小心就已经三十岁，掐指算算不知道以前的日子怎么过的，还是觉得头脑空空。你不能埋怨这个社会什么，你只能从自己身上找原因，为什么没有独立的思想，为什么没有独立思想的走到了今天。</p>

<p>就好像一个刚从梦里醒来的人，肚饿难当，也不知道昏睡了多久。</p>

<p>但是不管怎样，醒来了就是醒来了，只能自己找吃的。不知道该吃什么，那就每样吃一点，先解决温饱再说。</p>

<p>一人一本书，就是一个很重要的人，你选择他的一本书来读。这个法子不一定妥当，但是也并不太大的不妥。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[District standards and position description]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/18/district-standards-and-position-description/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T13:34:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/18/district-standards-and-position-description</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following is from the book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a>  .</p>

<h3>District standards of competent performance</h3>

<p>A standard is composed of three parts: a statement which establishes a general behavior, a list of indicators which specify how that behavior will be identified, and a principal's judgment as to the level of competent performance. The statement and indicators are listed for each standard. The level of expected performance of these standards will be determined by the professional judgment of the pnncipal. The judgment is influenced by the teacher's assignment, class size, experience, and available resources. To determine if the requirements of the standard have been met, the statement of general teacher behavior, all of the indicators, and the performance level must be considered.</p>

<p>Section I—Instructional development<br/>
Area: Diagnosing
Standard 1 The competent teacher establishes procedures for gathering data by<br/>
a. completing the diagnosis for each student<br/>
b. using the diagnostic tools which are pertinent to the teacher's goals<br/>
c. using a variety of diagnostic instruments and techniques<br/>
d. requesting assistance from others, when needed, for more comprehensive diagnosis</p>

<!--more-->


<p>
Standard 2 The competent teacher interprets diagnostic data to identify the needs and concerns of both the individual and the group by<br/>
a. identifying the achievement level of each student<br/>
b. explaining the significance of the achievement level diagnosed</p>

<p>Area: Prescribing<br/>
Standard 3 The competent teacher utilizes diagnostic data to establish instructional objectives and relates these to individual needs by<br/>
a. writing instructional objectives<br/>
b. preparing objectives that show the data gathered in diagnosis are utilized<br/>
c. preparing objectives in terms of student performance<br/>
d. preparing objectives that are measurable<br/>
e. preparing both short- and long-term objectives for any assigned class</p>

<p>Standard 4 The competent teacher plans lessons to meet individual and group needs by<br/>
a. planning lessons that are consistent with the objectives<br/>
b. planning lessons that include appropriate activities which meet individual and group needs<br/>
c. planning to use appropriate resource materials related to instructional objectives<br/>
d. planning alternatives to meet the needs of individual students<br/>
e. accepting and using student feedback in planning instruction</p>

<p>Area: Facilitating<br/>
Standard 5 The competent teacher utilizes knowledge of subject matter by<br/>
a. using words and content appropriate to the subject area and students' abilities<br/>
b. using available media effectively and efficiently<br/>
c. requesting and using materials and facilities based on instructional objectives<br/>
d. knowing and utilizing community agencies, groups, and individuals to further the educational
program</p>

<p>Standard 6 The competent teacher uses effective classroom management techniques by<br/>
a. showing respect for students<br/>
b. providing an atmosphere in which students remain at task<br/>
c. exhibiting consistency when dealing with behavior problems<br/>
d. exhibiting positive verbal and nonverbal influence on students</p>

<p>Standard 7 The competent teacher applies learning theory by<br/>
a. utilizing and building upon students' interests and prior knowledge<br/>
b. providing feedback as students progress toward goals<br/>
c. allowing for a balance between intake of information and the expression of student ideas<br/>
d. providing the individual with activities to develop attitudes, appreciations, and values</p>

<p>Standard 8 The competent teacher uses a variety of instructional techniques appropriate to the students' needs by<br/>
a. giving directions in a clear, concise manner<br/>
b. phrasing questions so students may respond appropriately<br/>
C. using strategies which involve students in higher levels of thinking<br/>
d. pacing the activities within a lesson according to the needs of students</p>

<p>Area: Student Performance Evaluation<br/>
Standard 9 The competent teacher establishes procedures for assessing student performance by<br/>
a. selecting means of evaluation which are appropriate to the objectives<br/>
b. planning measurement procedures for specific purposes<br/>
C. utilizing procedures whereby students receive feedback on their individual performance<br/>
d. presenting information that indicates evaluation has taken place for each student</p>

<p>Standard 10 The competent teacher interprets the results of student performance assessment by<br/>
a.identifs ing the reasons why students have or have not met the performance objectives</p>

<p>Standard 11 The competent teacher utilizes the results of student performance assessment by<br/>
a. using objective data to arrive at a grade or indicator of student progress to be reported to parents and student<br/>
b. providing feedback that facilitates the student accomplishment of goals.<br/>
c. planning changes in teaching strategies based on the results of the evaluation.</p>

<p>Section II—Professional development<br/>
Area: Communication<br/>
Standard 12 The competent teacher communicates effectively with students by<br/>
a. listening to and considering student comments and suggestions<br/>
b. being open to suggestions about ways in which to present material<br/>
c. conveying an attitude that promotes participation in activities<br/>
Standard 13 The competent teacher communicates effectively with colleagues and staff by<br/>
a. participating in the group decision-making process<br/>
b. listening to and considering suggestions from the staff<br/>
c. sharing ideas and resources with others</p>

<p>Standard 14 The competent teacher communicates responsibly to the public the significance of the school program by<br/>
a. answering parents' inquiries promptly, honestly, and discretely<br/>
b. initiating when necessary communication with parents<br/>
c. having available or locating information to relate district philosophy to the community at large</p>

<p>Area: School Relationships<br/>
Standard 15 The competent teacher has a consistent and professional attitude toward accomplishment of own school goals by<br/>
a. contributing to the decision-making process and abiding by group decisions
b. accepting shared responsibilities in and out of the classroom during the school day
c. maintaining consistency in record keeping as defined by building or district administrative regulations and procedures<br/>
d. using adopted courses of study or adjusting teaching objectives to include such adoptions<br/>
e. carrying out reasonable requests given by proper authority</p>

<p>Standard 16 The competent teacher has a consistent and professional attitude toward the accom
plishment of district and state goals by<br/>
a adhering to and enforcing school law, state board regulations, school board policy, and established administrative procedures.<br/>
b. adhering to the Employee Conduct and Responsibility requirements as stated in the Board Policy Handbook.</p>

<p>Source: Adapted from Beaverton, Oregon Schools Personnel Handbook.</p>

<h3>Position description</h3>

<p>Position: Teacher
Reports to: Principal (or His/Her Designee)
Position Purpose:
Implements, supervises, and maintains a high quality learning environment Tor students within the specific curriculum and standards of the district.<br/>
Nature and Scope:
The teacher is a professional with the responsibility for implementing a curriculum. Inherent in this responsibility is the requirement of related academic knowledge, technical skills, and professional attitudes and judgments.<br/>
The teacher must have the ability to diagnose the needs of learners and to evaluate their performance. The teacher must also be able to prescribe learning activities appropriate to student needs and to constructively evaluate these activities. The teacher effects an optimum learning climate through appropriate and maximum use of all resources available, and through the use of effective instructional and classroom management techniques.<br/>
In addition to the requirement of technical competence, the teacher maintains an attitude and
conduct which is consistent with the district policy of professional conduct. The teacher follows building and district procedural guidelines and policy.<br/>
Primary Accountabilities:
1. Identifies the needs of students through diagnostic procedures and relates instructional objectives to these needs. Plans, prepares, and executes appropriate lessons, utilizing appropriate resource materials and activities.<br/>
2. Maintains student records as required by the school.<br/>
3. Communicates with parents, students, and other professional staff regarding student progress(behavioral and academic).<br/>
4. Follows a curriculum that is prescribed by state, district, or building.<br/>
5. Assures students of learning opportunities within a classroom environment that facilitates learning.<br/>
6. Meets the district's Standards of Competent Performance at all times.<br/>
7. Follows district and school policies, procedures, rules, regulations, and guidelines and the provisions of the contract.</p>

<p>Source: School District 48J, Beaverton, OR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effective teaching notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T11:25:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/09/17/effective-teaching-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was reading a book <a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Clinical_Supervision_and_Teacher_Develop.html?id=O3ycAAAAMAAJ">Clinical Supervision and Teacher Development</a></p>

<p>The following are summary notes of Chapter 3 Using clinical supervision to promote effective teaching.</p>

<p>Characteristics of Good Teaching in Students' Mind?<br/>
Niss(Nice)<br/>
 *   Nice(respect, patient and easy to get along with)<br/>
 *   Interesting(makes subject interesting and fun with students engaged)<br/>
 *   Sense of humor(tell jokes and smiles a lot)<br/>
 *   Sensitive to students' need( Listent to students' question and make changes to help students learn )</p>

<p>Teacher characteristics associated with gain in students' academic achievement?<br/>
Creati<br/>
 +   Clarity<br/>
 +   Raise Variety(of materials, methods, question types and levels)<br/>
 +   Enthusiasm<br/>
 +   avoid harsh criticism<br/>
 +   Task-oriented<br/>
 +   Indirect teaching style</p>

<p>Substantive interaction that increase students' at-task time:<br/>
Equal<br/>
  -   Explain(content to students)<br/>
  -   questioning<br/>
  -   using feedback<br/>
  -   assistance<br/>
  -   list the steps or tasks(chunlei added)</p>

<p>Effective Classroom Preconditions:<br/>
Amazing
- Attention and motivation<br/>
- Meaningful(students can find personal meaning in the information being presented)<br/>
- Applications(opportunities to practice using new information)<br/>
- Include both lower-coginitive and higher-cognitive tasks or questions<br/>
- Group work process in the classroom</p>

<p>Notes taken from another book chapter-Glickman -chapter 4.pdf<br/>
Research on effective instruction() indicates that effective instruction is based on adaption of curriculum and materials to local settings and particular learning goals. In other words, effective teachers think about what they are currently doing, assess the results of their practice, explore with each other new possibilities  for teaching students, and are able to consider students' perspectives.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/teacher-transform.png" alt="teacher transfrom" /></p>

<p>The following was added at 2014/10/30
Evidence based Teaching notes<br/>
<a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Evidence_Based_Teaching.html?id=DZRhPQAACAAJ">Evidence-Based Teaching: A Practical Approach by Geoff Petty</a></p>

<p>==Expert teachers set challenging goals: deep learning==</p>

<p>==Expert teachers had very deep understanding of their subject  and the teaching and learning of the subject==</p>

<p>Their subject knowledge was more integrated, interrelated and built around general principles.</p>

<p>This deep learning enabled them to "make lessons uniquely their own by changing, combining, and adding to them according to their students' needs and their own goals".<br/>
p310</p>

<p>The expert teacher knowledge of the learning process was similarly deeper than that of experienced teachers. This enabled them to predict and avoid difficulties that students might have , and to see what was happening in their classrooms in terms of a deeper set of principles relating how students learn.</p>

<p>This mean that expert teacher were better able to diagnose what was happening in their classrooms, and to adapt. They were more responsive to their students as a result. The teaching and learning principles they used were probably something like those outlined  in Chapter 14.</p>

<p>==Expert teachers monitor learning and provide feedback==</p>

<p>Aim for evolution rather than revolution. Trying new methods one at a time is usually best, or your students will get unsettled even if you don't.<br/>
Teachers touch students' lives for ever - so it's worth the effort to make powerful methods work.</p>

<p>Graham Gibbs(1992)<br/>
action research approach advice:<br/>
Involve others<br/>
Identify the problem clearly<br/>
Use research evidence to convince others and to find promising strategies<br/>
Start where you can<br/>
Start small<br/>
Don't reinvent the wheel<br/>
Involve the students<br/>
Changes as you go along</p>

<p>p318</p>

<p>Review<br/>
we review our teaching in particular lesson or sequence of lessons, and look for evidence for what worked and what didn't.<br/>
Difficulties: Being brave enough to collect evidence that might be uncomfortable, andhones enough to face up to problems without blaming ourselves or our students</p>

<p>Learn<br/>
we try to lean from this review, not just what worked or didn't, but why. This creates general principles that we can apply elsewhere.<br/>
Difficulties: Asking 'why' persistently enough to enable us to lean the root cause of success or failure. Being able to 'bridge' this learning to other context by asking 'where else in my teaching could I use what I have just learned?'</p>

<p>Apply<br/>
We plan an experiment, perhaps adapting what we did in an earlier 'Do' phase.<br/>
Difficulties: Finding the courage, time and inclination to do things differently.</p>

<p>Do<br/>
we carry out our experiment. The cycle repeats.</p>

<p>p164<br/>
Seven principles common to high-quality leaning and achievement</p>

<p>1 student must see the value of the learning<br/>
2 students must believe they can do it<br/>
3 challenging goals<br/>
the goal involves student activity on constructive methods<br/>
the goal involves reasoning not just reproduction<br/>
high participation rate<br/>
students have their audience, variety and fun</p>

<p>4 feedback and dialogue on progress towards goal<br/>
students need 'medals' that give information about the extent to which they have achieved the goals<br/>
students need 'missions' that describe how to improve and progress<br/>
students need to develop a growing understanding of the goals</p>

<p>5 establish the structure of information and so its meaning<br/>
from known to unknown<br/>
from concrete to abstract<br/>
the structure first, then add the detail</p>

<p>6 time and repetition<br/>
multiple context: examples and non-examples in many different contexts in order to 'get' them
multiple perspectives: student need to see what they are leaning through different 'spectacles'. SOLO<br/>
multiple representations: right- and left-brain</p>

<p>7 teach skills as well as content</p>

<p>The PAR model<br/>
Present Apply &amp; Review</p>

<p>end notes</p>

<p>有趣的是，脑科学和认知科学也提出了若干原则和规律：<br/>
基于神经生物学研究的证据，Zull在2002年提出了3条规律：<br/>
1. 认识到情感因素的关键性作用。<br/>
2. 帮助学生建立自己掌控学习的感觉。<br/>
3. 学习必须基于自己已有的神经网络（已有知识），即使这个网络是错误的。</p>

<p>脑科学的研究发现，情绪是智慧的高级组织者，情绪能够指导认知进程和影响推理。例如长期高水平的皮质醇最终将导致与学习和记忆有关的海马神经元的损伤 ，即使是短时间的高水平皮质醇也会对短期记忆产生影响 。情绪对学习的影响具有两重性，轻松、愉快的情绪有利于学生的学习和健康发展，而过于紧张、沮丧、愤怒的情绪则不利于学生的学习。<br/>
此外无论是教育研究还是认知科学研究都显示，元认知的发展对于学习非常关键<br/>
学习者已有的知识对于学习有直接和重大的影响。学生并非头脑空空的来到教室，他们通过生活经验以及人际交流已经形成了很多概念和认识，这些概念或者完全错误，或者不完全，或者相对合理，不一而同，但是都对相关概念的学习有着重要的影响，科学教育研究者称之为前科学概念。而其脑科学的基础就是学生在已有的神经网络的基础上建造新的神经网络进而执行新的认知功能。</p>

<p>Boettcher2007年根据脑科学研究成果，提出的核心学习原则：
1：每一个结构化的学习经验都有四个元素（学习者、教师、知识、环境），它们以学习者为中心。
2：每一个学习经验都包括能够与学习者的相互作用环境。
3：我们塑造工具，工具也塑造我们。
4：教师是学习经验的导演。
5：学习者具有与该学习经验有关的个体知识、技能和态度。
6：学习者都具自己特定的最近发展区作为建构有用知识的基础。
7：概念并不是语句而是有组织的错综复杂的知识簇。
8：学习者都不需要学习所有内容，但是需要学习核心概念。
9：学习目标不同，所需教学也不同。
10：在其他条件一线的情况下，更多学习任务时间等价于更多的学习。</p>

<p>References:<br/>
Boettcher, J. (2007). Ten core principles for designing effective learning environments: Insights from brain research and pedagogical theory. Innovate: Journal of Online Education, 3(3), n3.<br/>
Zull, J. E. (2002). The art of changing the brain: Enriching the practice of teaching by exploring the biology of learning. Sterling, VA: Stylus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[超越上海：中国科学教育真的领先吗]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/surpassing-shanghai/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T21:08:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/surpassing-shanghai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近在QQ论坛里，有同学提到这本书《超越上海：美国应该如何建设世界顶尖的教育系统》。这个标题容易给人一种误解，以为中国的教育已经在美国前头了，这绝对是错误的理解。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Surpassing-Shanghai.jpg" alt="Surpassing Shanghai" /><br/>
其实美国人的危机意识很强烈，从《A nation at risk》到《No child left behind》都显示了国家对教育的重视，特别是科学教育，其实大家去查一查各国的教育财政预算比例就清楚了。之所以很多美国学者喊狼来了，道理很简单，第一是危机意识，第二，为了获得更多关注、科研项目和财政支持。这种危机意识是这个国家保持全球第一的重要条件。</p>

<p>其实简单的说美国教育好或者中国教育好是没有意义的，另外上海的pisa成绩根本代表不了中国，大家闭着眼睛想一想自己家乡的教育状况就心中有数了。</p>

<p>另外再看看我们学生高考完的表现，焚书啊！你说教育取得了多少成绩，我说很惨，没有发自内心的热爱，一票否决。</p>

<p>最近看了Timss的几个课堂视频，强列推荐大家看看，特别是日本的中学科学课堂。大家可以自己比一比，想一想。<a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">Timssvideo-Japan-Physics</a></p>

<p>千万不要被上海的pisa成绩或者这本书的标题蒙骗了，要想想样本的代表性以及作者的立场。说到科学教育，中国科学教育者还有很长的一段路要走。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[大脑错觉（Brain bugs）]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/11/27/brain-bugs/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2011/11/27/brain-bugs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在笑来的博客上看到，这本书《Brain bugs》，笑说有趣的很。于是打开看了一下目录还有网站的Demos如下：<br />Brain Bugs | Demos<br />: http://www.brainbugs.org/demos.html<br /><br />上面的页面上列举了很多brain bugs。<br />比如McGurk Effect，上面有一个女人在发言，但是当你闭上眼睛的时候，你听到的是一个声音，当你睁开眼睛的时候你听到的是另外一个声音。（我猜测是收到了发音者口型的影响）<br /><br />再比如Baker-baker Paradox<br />我们经常会忘记某个人的名字，但是多半会记得他的职业。即使是一个叫Baker的baker，我们还是容易自己的他是一个面包师。原因在于，我们记忆一个人的职业的时候，会有很多相关的概念协同起来，而名字则很少协同记忆。（也许老师们也可以尝试为学生的名字富于内涵，从而便于记忆）<br />这也提示我们，在教学过程中，应该把新概念与学生的已有概念产生更多的来联系，使其协同起来，而不是像名字一样孤零零的，最后被遗忘。<br /><br />再如Flash Lag Effect<br />我在预测红球的时候，总是预测超前50左右，这就是为什么足球边裁判罚越位中有24%为误判的原因。其原因是我们的视觉系统在关注其他信号的同时，总是倾向于超前估计运动物体的位置。<br /><br />再如Leaning Tower Illusion<br />看起来右侧的塔会更加的倾斜，但是其实两个塔的照片是完全相同。<br /><br />这是采访本书作者的录音：http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/fa/2011/07/20110714_fa_01.mp3<br /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
