<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 设计 | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/categories/设计/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-19T14:56:25-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design for better future]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T14:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/01/08/design-for-better-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I saw this in our main library when the staff cleanup the restroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/door-with-leg.png" alt="Door with leg" /><br/>
What a cool leg the door has! The idea is simple, but the result is so good. Sometimes simple change can make a big difference.</p>

<p>There also some design confuses me. Here is a table with sharp edge on the top surface. I really cannot understand what this edge serves for beyound hurting my arms when typing on my laptop.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/table-with-sharp-edge.png" alt="Sharp edge table" /></p>

<p>Nowadays, the environment is becoming worse and worse. One basic reason is bad design. Our company design good batteries with low-cost but ignored how to recycle and reuse the waste batteries. Similarly, the white pollution, air and water pollution all failded to take environment pollution cost into concern. These industries are all good examples of bad design and are badly need to change.</p>

<p>Well, how to solve these problems and create better future? The answer is design zero pollution industry pipeline. Just like the nature design all kinds of lives, no waste at all. For example, how to make use of clean energy as power for travelling. When you taking whole process into concern, you will find the horse and cart is one example of good designs. Of course, we will not return to this old method of travelling, but we really should rethink this design.</p>

<p>It is not just product design or pipeline design. It is also a life design. On behavior researcher found a very simple and effective way to save energy-- sending a letter of electric usage report comparing with neighborhood. After being told use more than twice electric than neighborhood, people tend to pay much attention to save energy. This is just how behavior science used to affect personal life styles.</p>

<p>Nowadays, people have learnt to make use clean energy such as wind, water,sun. Researchers are also trying to invent new technologies of producing and storing and converting these energy. We are going to and have to achieve no waste design in order to live a better life for long run on earth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eco-life Design and Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/eco-life-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T18:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/26/eco-life-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In agriculture age,people don't have to worry about pollution. Because all the products are degradable. Nature itself is a great designer, everything can be reused and recycled. But as human entered the age of industry, the situation changed. Human want to create new stuff that never existed in natural world. Yes they made it but they are not born good designers; Many waste are produced but can not be recycled.</p>

<p>There is a simple logic. If human want live in earth forever, then everything should be recycled, otherwise there will be not enough resources or room for human beings.</p>

<p>China have made a miracle of economic growth, but the growth cost dear -- air and water pollution, increasing gap between rich and poor, village and city, east and west. This growth also can not be sustainable because the environment is getting worse and worse and the resources is getting fewer and fewer. In order to live a healthy life, China must reconsider its style of economic growth and design more environmentally friendly industry,agriculture and living system. But do China have enough designers to design the eco-life system? It is questionalble. STEM education may play a crucial role in preparing these future designers in China.</p>

<p>If you look into Chinese secondary and primary curriculum, you will find there is little content of enginering or designing in their class learning activities. How to assess the curriculum content to tell if it is updated and suitable for preparing future citizens? How teachers address this problem in their classroom teaching? Is there a lack of designing education in our curriculum system? If not, is the content and education good enough for preparing our future designers? These questions matters for the future development of China.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What do you ecpect in your life]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/chunlei-and-mathematics/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-23T10:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/chunlei-and-mathematics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following is a visulization designed by myself. It let me think what do I expect in my life.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/birth&amp;death.png" alt="meaning of life" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laptop stand designed by myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-29T22:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/29/laptop-stand-designed-by-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is uncomfortable to work on my laptop on a table. Becuase the screen is too low and you have to bend your head which cause pain in the neck.<br/>
So I made a laptop stand using a useless shoes box. Here is the picture.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/laptopstand.png" alt="laptop stand" /></p>

<p>You can alway make a change if you want to. And small change can make a big difference sometimes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[设计Chindogu锻炼创造力]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/05/15/Chindogu-designed-by-me/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T19:33:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/05/15/Chindogu-designed-by-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近参加了一门网络课程，是关于创造力的，课程活动要求参与者设计一些chindogu，这个词源于日本，是指一些没有实际用途但是有趣的设计产品。于是我设计了以下作品： <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/beauty-in-your-cup.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hourglass-bath.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/couple-zipper-umbrella.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/lovers-dancing-shoe.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hand-tap-1.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" />
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/music-tap-1.png" alt="beauty-in-your-cup" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
