<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: patent | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/patent/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-12-29T12:11:01+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patent a special knowledge as private property]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/patent-a-special-knowledge-as-private-property/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-23T12:04:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/23/patent-a-special-knowledge-as-private-property</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why we introduces the idea of patent?<br/>
Patent is a commercial idea based on market. A patent is a limited property right the government gives inventors in exchange for their agreement to share details of their inventions with the public. Like any other property right, it may be sold, licensed, mortgaged, assigned or transferred, given away, or simply abandoned.[<a href="#1">1</a>] We can see the rationale of patent is to disclose the innovations to public domains for common good. What to do if patents are going to violate this original rationale? Should we still protect patents or abandon it?</p>

<p>What can be patented? What can't or shouldn't?<br/>
In order to apply for a patent the inventor should provide information about how to made and use this invention. Basically, this is a kind of knowledge about "how". So patent is both a special knowledge and a private property(intellectual property). Usually, a private property such as a chair is unique in the world and can not be given to others without losing it. But knowledge and information are different. We can transmit them without losing them. This is how education and media works. Patent means you can know it but you can't use it without license or permission. But people naturally can make use of their knowledge. It should be legal for people to make use of their knowledge to know and help themselves. So there is a question, should a special knowledge be patentable? <br/>
Case 1:<br/>
There is an interesting case about patent. Mr. Bowman bought gene-modified seed from Monsanto company to plant in his form. For that second crop, he bought seeds from a grain elevator filled with a mix of seeds in the reasonable hope that many of them contained Monsanto’s patented Roundup Ready gene.[<a href="#2">2</a>] Monsanto brought Mr. Bowman to the court for abuse of seeds with their patented Roundup Ready gene. Mr. Bowman argued that it is the natural right to make any use of the seeds that you bought. The patent should be in exhaustion when I bought the seeds from grain elevator.</p>

<p>But Mr. Bowman still lost the case. This is what Justice Kagan said:
“Under the patent exhaustion doctrine, Bowman could resell the patented soybeans he purchased from the grain elevator; so too he could consume the beans himself or feed them to his animals. But the exhaustion doctrine does not enable Bowman to make additional patented soybeans without Monsanto’s permission, that is precisely what Bowman did.” [<a href="#3">3</a>]</p>

<p>Case 2<br/>
There is another case, a farmer grow his corn in his form. But his neighborhood grew gene-modified corn, by accident the wind blow the pollen with modified gene to his farm. So his corn also had the modified gene. But the farmer planted corn for a Japan company that only want corn without modified gene. So he can couldn't sell his corn to the company and lost lot of money. Who should pay for his lost?</p>

<p>Case 3<br/>
A family invented a new kind of food(toy for cat). They keep the making process secret. But later it has been stolen and patented. Although they have made this new food for many years, now it become illegal to keep their business without paying for the patent. Is it fair? How about second time independent invention?</p>

<p>Although, in the first case, Mr. Bowman was intently to make use of the loophole of second buying. But it still annoy my nerves when thinking of gene-modified plant take the place of the other plants that farmers can grow and plant without any limitation, gene-modified food went into market without label, modified gene go to other plan species without control. A question emerged from this case is that Should gene be patentable?</p>

<p>How about human gene? Here is an interesting video "Who Owns You? 20% of the Genes in Your Body are Patented".[<a href="#4">4</a>]</p>

<iframe src="http://zhangchunlei.com//player.vimeo.com/video/11755917" width="500" height="281" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This let me reflect the following questions: Should human gene be patentable? Will these patents prohibit us to know more about ourselves and make use our knowledge to benefit ourselves? Will this go against individual human rights? Is patent, or commercialization a good idea in education and human society in future?</p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a id="1">[1]</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent">Patent - Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</a></p>

<p><a id="2">[2]</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/16/business/supreme-court-to-hear-monsanto-seed-patent-case.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=0">Supreme Court to Hear Monsanto Seed Patent Case - NYTimes.com</a></p>

<p><a id="3">[3]</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/14/business/monsanto-victorious-in-genetic-seed-case.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1385229872-QGNdTtZez+JvcDHciXNSIg">Monsanto Victorious in Seed-Patent Case - NYTimes.com</a></p>

<p><a id="4">[4]</a> <a href="http://singularityhub.com/2010/08/11/who-owns-you-20-of-the-genes-in-your-body-are-patented-video/">Who Owns You? 20% of the Genes in Your Body are Patented | Singularity Hub</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conflicts between commercialization of science and education equity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/30/conflicts-between-commercialisation-of-science-and-education-equity/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T23:46:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/10/30/conflicts-between-commercialisation-of-science-and-education-equity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I attended Dr Jackson' class <a href="http://djackson.myweb.uga.edu/8990/Daily/Day12.html">ESCI 8990 Daily Page</a>.</p>

<p>We discussed questions:<br/>
1.  whether scientific knowledge is a private product?<br/>
2.  whether is it right to use grants to apply patent or develop products for profits?<br/>
3.  conflicts between patent protection and equal access to scientific knowledge.</p>

<p>I didn't say a word because I was the only Chinese around the table and intellectual property protection in China has a bad reputation although the situation is improving. I don't want to defend too much, but I guess everyone may only have one story about the IPP in China. But just as Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie said: <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/chimamanda_adichie_the_danger_of_a_single_story.html">There is a danger of a single story</a>. So it will always be good to know more than one story.</p>

<p>The idea of patent protection became popular in industry culture. In order to encourage people and companies to develop more new type of products for society goodness, we give them such protects and advantages in using the patent that they invented first.</p>

<p>But, in agricultural civilization, such as accent China, there is no such idea. Some people may keep their special way of making food or drinks as their secrets, but once the secrets were known by others, they can also make the same food and drinks, and it is legal. The government may also help to publish and transmit some technologies, such as paper making and the printing. If they apply for the patent of making paper and printing, how much money they can earn? But this may also slow down the development of human society. So every patent has limited period for protection. The patent finally becomes common property of human society.</p>

<p>In agricultural civilization, labor is the main value source of a product. Yes, patent tell how to make a product, but it is the labor make it realized. This is not true in industrial civilization, the people or company who possess the patent earn the most of the profit. You will never know how cheap labor become in China nowadays. Is it equal? Is it a new kind of colonization? Many developed country put their factories into developing countries, they use their labor, resources and make wastes and pollution. Is it fair? Is it sustainable? Will it leads to wars? You can read more about <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/drloveccsu/ecojustice-pedagogy">Ecojustice</a>.</p>

<p>Well, industrialization and consumerism are both come from western culture. Human rights is also declared in the western. But there is conflicts between commercialization of science and education equity. The following paragraph is from:<a href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/">The Universal Declaration of Human Rights</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Article 26.
   (1) Everyone has the right to education. Education shall be free, at least in the elementary and fundamental stages. Elementary education shall be compulsory. Technical and professional education shall be made generally available and higher education shall be equally accessible to all on the basis of merit.</p></blockquote>

<p>Poor people receive poor education and they remain poor, becomes a circle. This will only lead to hate and war. Patent protection can help develop new products and technologies and promote the progress of society. It can also benefit some people and groups and hurt the others. Especially, when the researchers use grants(money from citizens) to do research and apply for patents only benefit for a special organization or people. Then it is unfair.</p>

<p>It is also disputable whether something should be a patent. For example, the people invent the product later by his own, will lost all the value of his effort because it would be illegal to for him to use the same way to make product.</p>

<p>The company own the patent seems own a new kind of capital -- Intellectual Capitalism. Government tend to protect their patent rights in order to encourage more company to do research and development. But sometimes it will lead to monopolization and the price of their products becomes unreasonable(several times higher than its actual cost). Will government still protect?</p>

<p>With the global industrial production, with consumerism and commercialization, will this new kind of capitalism -- Intellectual Capitalism create a new colonial history. Do we want this happen? Or it already happened.</p>

<p>There should be a balance between patent protection and common benefit, between efficiency and fairness, between developed and developing countries, between industrial civilization and agricultural civilization, between human and nature, otherwise we are making troubles and potential dangers for ourselves!</p>

<pre><code>On the other hand, science education sits in an uncomfortable place in this landscape given particular aspects of patenting and property rights imply limited access and thus inequity in knowledge acquisition.
</code></pre>

<p>iphone</p>

<p>克隆文化
有性繁殖与无性繁殖</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
