<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: writing | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-23T15:05:29+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Questions need to address in a research paper]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/28/questions-need-to-address-in-a-research-paper/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-28T18:28:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/28/questions-need-to-address-in-a-research-paper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A sample division for 40 pages paper.<br/>
2 Introduction<br/>
5-6 Literature<br/>
2 Theory/conceptual frameworks<br/>
6-10 Methods<br/>
4-12 Findings<br/>
10 Discussion conclusion Implication</p>

<p>(1)Introduction</p>

<pre><code>* what is known  
* what is unknown  
* Your burning Hypothesis, question, aim(Approach, plan of attack, proposed solution(a little bit),your experimental approach,why your study fills the gap  
</code></pre>

<p>tips for introduction</p>

<pre><code>* Keep short  
* for general audience: clear, concise, non-technical  
* take the reader step by step form what is know to what is unknown. end with your specific question  
* Emphasize how your study fills in the gaps(the unknown)  
* Summarize at a high level! Leave detailed descriptions, speculations, and criticism of studies in discussion  
</code></pre>

<p>Keep in minds:</p>

<pre><code>* it is not a literature review  
* catch attention  
* making the case  
</code></pre>

<p>(2)Literature review</p>

<pre><code>* comprehension  
* synthesis  
* critical  
* write the most important citations that stand your study out  
* anything in discussion should be here, no new paper add in discussion  
* one paragraph summary your review  
</code></pre>

<p>notes: if there is no directly related literature, you can close area to draw on, or standards, government policy</p>

<p>(3)Theoretical/ Conceptual Frameworks</p>

<pre><code>* help to analysis the data and approach the questions  
* theory -position/approach  
* conceptual model  
* theory drawing the studies
</code></pre>

<p>(4)Methods</p>

<pre><code>* Participants  
* Context  
* Data collections  
* Data analysis  
* Methodological theory  
* Reliability and validity  
* enough information for other people to repeat  
</code></pre>

<p>(5)Results<br/>
Tables and figures<br/>
Summarize not read table for reader<br/>
Highlight the result, Not only positive results but also negative<br/>
complement the information that is already in tables and figures<br/>
give precise values in the figure or the percentage change<br/>
don't forget to talk about the negative and control results<br/>
Reserve the term "significant" for statistically significant<br/>
reserve information about what you did for the methods section<br/>
do not discuss the rationale for statistical analyses within the results section<br/>
Reserve comments on the meaning of your results for the discussion section<br/>
Just tell what the data show not what your data mean</p>

<p>Use the past tense for completed actions: we found , women were, men smoked ,was<br/>
Use the present tense for assertions that continue to be true<br/>
figure 1 show ,  finds confirm the data suggests</p>

<pre><code>* Synthesis the important not all  
* Show the results to match the questions  
* select the most powerful and significant  
* do not repeat the tables and figures  
</code></pre>

<p>(6)Discussion<br/>
Answer the question you asked<br/>
Support your conclusion(your data, others' data)<br/>
Defend your conclusion(anticipate criticisms)<br/>
Give the "big-picture" take-home message<br/>
Connect your theory framework and review<br/>
how your work add on</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing paper for publication]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-14T10:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/05/14/writing-paper-for-publication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing is an very important skill as speaking. It aims to send message, from people to people, from generation to generation, from country to country. One of the most efficient way to do this is publishing in good journals. Nowadays, publication has become a crucial part of resume or CV, and people write papers not just for sending messages but also seeking for promotions. So good universities ask faculties for good papers; good researchers look for good journals to publish. Good journals want good impactors or indexes. Good researchers tend to cite more good papers from good journals. But can this system help sending necessary message to those in-need audiences? It may not necessarily be the case. It is just a game of numbers dominated by the for-profit companies and ambitious universities who care little what the content really mean.</p>

<p>Complain is enough. We still have to write anyway. But I believe we are writing for our audiences not for universities or journal companies. We write because we have the impulse to share. As a beginning researcher, I'd like to co-write with partners at first. I can learn easier and faster by observing the writing process and talking to them about it. So I would also recommend you co-write with somebody at first.</p>

<p>Although you may not like the game, it is still good to know the rules and the tools. Here are some useful resources for writhing educational journals:</p>

<p>I found writhing is both hard and complicated. It is like a hedgehog rolls itself as a ball; you can hardly approach anyhow. First it is hard because it is hard. Especially if you don't write often, it takes time to develop your own writing skills. Second, it is complex and complicated. Writhing a paper may include many small jobs: reading, citing, linking, analyzing, reasoning, revising, formatting, managing. It will remain hard unless you cut the job into small pieces that you can play with; Cutting tasks is a crucial managing skill.</p>

<h3>Writing tips:</h3>

<pre><code>* Write down your thoughts while you read.  
* Write it down when it come up to you.  
* Write timely before the deadline.  
* Write summary periodically.  
* Write, and then shut down disturbs.  
* Write with your ear, your mouth, and anything that helps.  
* Write briefly and clear; Every word tell.  
* Write as yourself and to be yourself.  
* Write as you are talking to a friend about your new discovery(emotion)  
</code></pre>

<h3>Writing steps:</h3>

<pre><code>1  abstract, title, journal  
2  results, logic, 5pages  
3  enrich each paragraph and link together  
4  revise and formatting  
</code></pre>

<h3>What make a paragraph good</h3>

<p>Focus on one idea<br/>
Format paragraph<br/>
  -Topic sentence<br/>
  -explanation evidence logic<br/>
-not too long: 3 sentences<br/>
-Concluding/Beginning sentence<br/>
-Paragraph work together<br/>
-unity(pronoun, sense, tongue)</p>

<h3>What make good sentence</h3>

<p>-no cluster, brief, clear, concise every word tell<br/>
-use strong verb<br/>
-make it colorful</p>

<h3>The hard thing:</h3>

<p>When you are wrting,it is hard to make the right decisions:<br/>
when to quit (something you don't want to do now);<br/>
when to search for help (something necessary but you can't do yourself);<br/>
when to just do the job no matter you like it or not.</p>

<h3>Writing tools:</h3>

<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/">Google Drive</a> can help you co-write online.<br/>
<a href="http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</a> can help you manage your references.<br/>
<a href="http://interest.science.thomsonreuters.com/forms/HistCite/">HisCite</a> can make graph to let you know how paper cited each other.<br/>
<a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/analytics/spss/">SPSS</a> can help you analyze the data.<br/>
<a href="http://latex-project.org/intro.html">LaTeX</a> is a good document preparation system especially useful when you have lots of equations and graphs(generated with R).<br/>
There are lots of other text editors such as Miscro-soft Word, EditPlus for consider.</p>

<h3>Useful books:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Publication-Manual-American-Psychological-Association-ebook/dp/B00CPUBEBM">Publication Manual by APA</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.apastyle.org/">APA Style website</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Writing-Well-30th-Anniversary-Edition/dp/0060891548">On Writing Well</a> by Zinsser</p>

<h3>Journal Rankings Search:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.scimagojr.com/journalrank.php?area=0&amp;category=3304&amp;country=all&amp;year=2012&amp;order=sjr&amp;min=0&amp;min_type=cd">Journal Rankings on Education</a><br/>
<a href="http://admin-apps.webofknowledge.com/JCR/JCR?RQ=HOME">Web of Science JCR-WebSearch Engine</a></p>

<h3>Journals and their impactors(2012 JCR Social Science Edition):</h3>

<p>REVIEW OF EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH 4.2<br/>
LEARNING AND INSTRUCTION 3.3<br/>
Journal of the Learning Sciences 3.0<br/>
COMPUTERS &amp; EDUCATION 2.7</p>

<p>JOURNAL OF RESEARCH IN SCIENCE TEACHING 2.5<br/>
<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1002/%28ISSN%291098-237X">SCIENCE EDUCATION 2.4</a><br/>
<a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1002/%28ISSN%291098-237X/homepage/ForAuthors.html">for-authors</a><br/>
<a href="http://jte.sagepub.com/">Journal of Teacher Education 1.6</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.sagepub.com/journals/Journal200961/manuscriptSubmission">for-authors</a><br/>
JOURNAL OF COMPUTER ASSISTED LEARNING 1.6<br/>
<a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?show=aimsScope&amp;journalCode=tsed20#.U3QKWCggtes">INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.3</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/action/authorSubmission?journalCode=tsed20&amp;page=instructions#.U3QLWiggtes">for-authors</a></p>

<p>British Journal of Educational Technology 1.3<br/>
<a href="http://www.journals.elsevier.com/teaching-and-teacher-education/">TEACHING AND TEACHER EDUCATION 1.2</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.journals.elsevier.com/teaching-and-teacher-education/">For Authors</a><br/>
RESEARCH IN SCIENCE EDUCATION 1.1</p>

<h3>NARST Proposal Review Rubric</h3>

<p>(from <a href="http://www.narst.org/">NARST website</a>)</p>

<pre><code>
For each category, three criteria are required. Given the constraints of the 5-page limit  
for proposals, please assign a numerical rating using the following descriptors as a guide:
5 Highly evident: Proposal provides clear, substantive, and coherent evidence of all criteria
4 Evident: Proposal adequately describes all criteria in the category.
3 Mostly evident: Proposal adequately describes 2 out of 3 criteria in the category
2 Somewhat evident: Proposal adequately describes 1 out of 3 criteria in the category
1 Not evident Proposal does not adequately describe any of the criteria in the category
Subject/Problem
1. Is there a clear focus for the study?
2. Does the proposal include a clear rationale for the study?
3. Does the proposal describe the model, theoretical framework, or philosophy of the study?
Design or Procedure
Empirical Studies
1. Does the proposal clearly describe the methodology (theory of method)?
2. Does the proposal clearly describe the research methods, design, and study context?
3. Are the methodology, procedure, and design appropriate for the study?
Non-Empirical Studies (e.g., conceptual or position papers, reviews of literature)
1. Does the proposal clearly describe the approach used to develop the argument or conduct the review?
2. Are the ideological/philosophical positions of the author and sources made clear?
3. Does the proposal include an appropriate range of literature?
Analyses and Findings
Empirical Studies
1. Do the data analyses appear to be appropriate, coherent, and complete?
2. Are the arguments or interpretations supported by the data?
3. Does the proposal discuss alternative interpretations, bias, reliability, or validity as appropriate?
Non-Empirical Studies (e.g., conceptual or position papers, reviews of literature)
1. Do the syntheses of ideas appear to be appropriate, coherent, and complete?
2. Are the arguments or interpretations supported by evidence?
3. Does the proposal discuss alternative interpretations, counter-arguments, or bias, as appropriate?
Contribution
1. Do the conclusions add to, refine, or refute the oretical constructs?
2. Do conclusions contribute valuable insights into teaching/learning/researching science education?
3. Does the proposal clearly describe implications for teaching/learning/researching science education?
Cohesiveness*(Related Paper-Sets ONLY)
1. Are all of the papers in the set focused on a similar concept/theme?
2. Do all papers contribute new information to the set, making a meaningful strongly-related whole?
3. Are all papers of high enough quality to be accepted individually?
General Interest
1. Does the content of the presentation promise to be of general interest to NARST members?
2. Is the content presented in a way that will be meaningful to NARST members?
3. Does the paper promise to be of interest to the education community at large?
Overall Rating
(1-not recommended; 5 highly recommended)  
</code></pre>


<h3>Basic Paper Structure(ITDFD)</h3>

<pre><code>
Title
Author
Abstract
Keywords

Introduction
  Background
  Literature
Theoretical Framework 
  Theoretical foundation
  Research questions
Design/Procedure
  Participants
  Instrument & Procedure
  Reliability & Validity
Findings
  Tables & Figures
Discussion
  Findings review
  Conclusions
  Implications

Acknowledgements
References
Journal
Luft, J.A., & Zhang, C. (2014).The pedagogical content knowledge and beliefs of newly hired secondary science teachers: The first three years.Educacion Quimica, 25(3), 325-331.

Conference
Zhang, C., & Liu, E.(Marth 2014).Teachers' Perceptions of Working Conditions and Workplace Learning in the Context of China's Educational Reform. National Association for Research in Science Teaching,Pittsburgh, PA

Book & chapter
Shotton, M. A (1989). Computer addiction? A study of computer dependency. London, England: Taylor & Francis.

Editor, A A (Ed.). (1986). Title of work. Location: Publisher.

Author, A A, & Author, B. B. (1995). litle of chapter or entry. In A Editor, B.
Editor, & C. Editor (Eds.), Title of book (pp. xxx-xxx). Location: Publisher.

Author, A. A. (1978). Title of doctoral dissertation or masters thesis (Unpublished
doctoral dissertation or master's thesis). Name of Institution, Location.

Report:   
Kessy, S. S. A.. & Urio, F. M. (2006). The contribution of microfinance institutions
to poverty reduction in Tanzania (Research Report No. 06.3). Retrieved
from Research on Poverty Alleviation website: http://www.repoa.or.tz
/documents_storage/Publications/Reports/06.3_Kessy_and_Urio.pdf

</pre>


<p></code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
