<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: UGA | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/uga/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-23T17:44:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The surprising trees]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T16:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/23/the-surprising-trees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A tree can have its own home.<br/>
It can also step over the wall.<br/>
A tree can free your minds.<br/>
It can also make the spirit call.<br/>
A tree can become your home.<br/>
And you will never forget it anymore.</p>

<p>The tree that owns itself.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-owns-itself.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that steps over the wall.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/the-tree-step-over-wall.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/the-tree-step-over.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that frees your mind.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-free-your-mind.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-free-your-mind2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree that touchs your soul.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-touch-you.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The tree can be your home and you will not forget it anymore.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/home-tree.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[美鸟掠影]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/21/birds-in-usa/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T10:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/21/birds-in-usa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在Bell食品超市里大概有20排货架，摆满了面包、罐头、调料等食杂用品，在特定的货架上还可以买到药膏、洗发水等生活用品。有两排货架很特殊，摆满了各式各样的、各种品牌的狗食。在堆放各种新鲜水果、蔬菜的地方，货架下面还放满了鸟食，只不过以前我一直不知道它是鸟食。虽然我经常光顾这个商店，但是确是在半年之后偶然发现这些鸟食，或者说是再发现。开始的时候，我只是感到奇怪，为什么美国人也喜欢把各种谷物混杂在一起卖，难道美国人也喜欢喝粥？直到我起了喝粥的念头，仔细观察这些装着五颜六色各种谷物的袋子，才发现上面都印着鸟的图案，原来是给鸟准备的营养大餐。</p>

<p>中国以前经常批判资本主义社会“重狗轻人”，现在可能还会有人再加一条“重鸟轻人”。不过如果你仔细的想一想，如果在一个国度人们爱狗、爱鸟爱到这样的地步，它又有什么理由会比“吃狗打鸟”的国家更轻视人的尊严和权利呢。当然，你不能排除这些爱狗爱鸟的国家里也有种族歧视者，也不能排除吃狗打鸟的国家里也有环境保护者。但是假如你是一只喜欢自由天空和安全快乐的鸟，你会定居何处？是什么影响了你的选择？可惜鸟是不会思索的，也不会选择，所以有些鸟儿幸运，有些鸟儿凄惨。</p>

<p>在我的印象当中，美国的鸟是非常大胆的。它可以无视你的靠近，自在的在草丛中寻食。它可以落在你的舰艇上歇脚，俯视着船上的人类。它可以倒立着吃你在松塔里填埋的谷物，毫不担心陷阱。它可以把自己的巢搭在紧挨你橱窗的小树上，繁殖后代。</p>

<p>在Dr. Tippins的Ecojustice课上，一位同学（中学教师）教了我们如何给鸟制作Pinecone bird feeder,我叫它松塔糕。是在松塔上抹上粘稠的花生酱然后在各种谷物里打一个滚就成了。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pinecone-bird-feeder.png" alt="课上给鸟制作的松塔糕" /><br/>
之后，需要用一根细绳把这个松塔糕拴在树杈上，由于是靠一根细线悬垂的，所以松鼠和大鸟是很难够得着的。而小巧的雀儿却正合适，这可能是观鸟者想看到它们美丽的身影才这样设计的。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pinecone-bird-feeder-in-tree.png" alt="松塔糕拴在树上" /><br/>
我特意将这个松塔糕绑在窗前大树上，这样我从二楼的卧室里就可以看到鸟儿，一开始并没有鸟儿关顾，我还挺失望的，因为是春季，如果是在冬季食物短缺的时候会很快又鸟儿光顾的。但是我并没有白忙活，一天，一只很小的雀儿在松塔糕上忙活起来，它不断的变换着姿势。因为松塔糕是通过一根细线悬垂下来的，根本没有立足的地方，所以它不得不跟松塔糕一起荡秋千，像是马戏团耍杂技的一样不断的变换姿势和翻跟头。之后，不几天的功夫，沾满了各种谷物的松塔糕就被吃了个精光。制作松塔糕和观看鸟儿啄食的样子请移步这里<a href="http://www.mykidsadventures.com/pinecone-bird-feeder/">Pinecone Bird Feeder</a></p>

<p>我曾经到纽约观光，在自由女神观光船上无意中看到了一只白鸽落在舰艇的顶端歇息，于是我迅速拿出手机拍下照片。船上挤满了游客，这只鸟就居然这么大模大样的俯视着我们这些人类。它歇了一会，觉得无聊了，就飞走了。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dove-on-ship.png" alt="舰艇上的鸟" /></p>

<p>一天中午，在公寓厨房做饭的时候，我瞥见窗外树丛里落着一只腹白头红的鸟儿，触手可及，隔着窗纱也不害怕。其实以前也常看到这只鸟儿在这棵小树上穿梭，只是没有在意。由于我正在洗碗，熟练的很，所以不时抽眼向它望一望，我居然有一个新的发现，这个鸟儿总是从底下钻进树丛，然后向上一跳一跳的，像是上台阶，逗留一会就飞走了。不一会又飞回来了，仔细观察我才发现，它嘴巴里还叼着一个细树枝，这次我特别留心，我的目光紧随着它一次次向上攀移，最后停下来的小树叉上，居然凭空出现了一个窝，真是神奇。</p>

<p>清早起来，可能是昨晚忘了关窗户，各种鸟儿已经叽叽喳喳叫开了。我不知道还有多少人能在中国听到鸟儿清早的鸣唱？————无论你是在城市还是在农村。没了这动听的声音，孩子们的笔下是否会变得干涩？心头突然升起一个疑问：我们到底是从大自然里“获取了”还是“失去了”？</p>

<p>在这里儿，人类是鸟的朋友，但是鸟儿也有天敌。今天早上，我去准备自己的早餐，热一热昨天的剩饭。正在用微波炉的时候，我听见外面的鸟儿不停的、急切的、沙哑的叫着，透过窗子望去，一只松鼠正停在树杈上，四处张望，眼冒精光，这是我第一次近距离观察松鼠，它们一向在我走近前就会逃走、或者上树的，我平时还是比较喜欢这些可爱的松鼠的，但是今天这个面孔让我特别厌恶，我紧急的敲了几下窗沙，松鼠被我吓跑了，不一会哪只鸟又出现在窗前的小树上，头上红色的羽毛不住的颤动，还是那么一跳一跳的，上了四五个台阶，最后来到巢上巡视。我不知道我的干预是否及时，也不知道到巢中是否还有幸存的幼鸟，这只鸟俯下身去，小树和巢的双重遮掩让我什么也看不到。希望它们平安无事！</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coco Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/20/coco-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T11:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/20/coco-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today we did the coco experiment in Dr. Oliver's Class. Here are some pictures.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/five-coco.png" alt="five-coco" /></p>

<p>The materials our group used:<br/>
  1. 5 bottles of coco (4 diet coco, 1 coco)<br/>
  1. 25 memos(5 fruit memos and 20 memos)<br/>
  1. 5 ml salt<br/>
  1. 1 measurer ruler<br/>
  1. 1 funnel</p>

<p>The 5 cocos were used as 5 experiment as control, coco, fruit memos, flat, salt. We measured the height of the coco before and after experiment, so we could count how much coco get out of the bottle. Here is what we got.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/coco-data.png" alt="data and figure" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inquiry and demonstration]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T14:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/17/inquiry-and-demonstration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Dr. Oliver gave us an amazing class about demonstration and inquiry. He first asked what question to think about or ask ourselves when using demonstration. Then we played two demonstration games with everybody totally engaged.</p>

<p>The first is radiometer (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crookes_radiometer">Crookes radiometer - Wikipedia</a>).<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/radiometer.jpg" alt="Crookes Radiometer" /></p>

<p>He just put it on a table and lighted up another bulb, it began to rotate. It was my first time to see this, I was very curious of its work principle. After close observation, I found that it rotated always the same direction with white vane in front and black vane behind.</p>

<p>Then we began to wonder what factors caused the vanes to rotate. Lights? But how? Temperature? how? What else? How can we found out? Try it. I tried using different angles of the light.</p>

<p>We also tried to use hot water and cold water to pure on it. It rotate exactly the same direction as using light when using hot water but the opposite direction when using cold water.<br/>
Nobody came up with a good explantion at the end. First I thought it was because the momentum of the absorbed Photon just like Crookes did which was wrong in this situation.</p>

<p>Then we began to do another game --Buoyancy.<br/>
First Dr. Oliver sent out a pre-test with 3 yes no questions about buoyancy followed why you believe so. Then we talked about each question a little while. Students answers and opinions are totally different.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/pre-test.png" alt="Pre-test" /><br/>
Let us found out. So he did another demonstration droppiing a brass cube into water cup which had been balanced. He asked us what would happen if he immersed it into the water.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/drop-into-water.png" alt="Brass cube into water" /><br/>
We made our predictions and then we did the experiment. We also tried some other settings which were carefully designed but playfully demonstrated.How do you use these demonstration in large class size like 30 students?</p>

<p>At the end of the class, he use his front pocket quesitons to reflect this lesson:<br/>
Does it elict students' ideas for teaching?<br/>
Does it it help student make sense of the material activity?<br/>
Dose it press students for evidenced based reasoning and communicating?</p>

<p>Yes it does! Yeah, we succeed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modify my previous lesson ESCI7040-A1]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/16/modify-my-previous-lesson-esci7040-a1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an assignment of Dr. Oliver's class ESCI7040(teaching strategies). The goal of this activity is to reflect on my own teaching and modify the plans for future teaching.</p>

<p>I taught learning theories to undergraduates in order to let them make sense of how students learn and apply these principles in their future teaching.</p>

<p>The guiding question is what is knowledge and how people learn? The big ideas include:<br/>
1. Different type of knowledge play different roles and people learn them differently.<br/>
2. Learning Science is not just learning scientific knowledge but also science practice and the nature of science.<br/>
3. Teacher need various types of knowledge to help students learn science.<br/>
4. Different learning theories understand people's learning differently and give different suggestions for teaching and learning.<br/>
5. Preconceptions, learning styles, learning strategies play an important role in students' learning.</p>

<p>This lesson takes 90 minutes and during 60 minutes I was lecturing.</p>

<h3>Task1: Reflections of this lesson:</h3>

<ol>
<li>Wether the content of this lesson can effectively help them understand how students learn science and apply these principles in their teaching?<br/>
Some ideas are too general and loosely related. They should be deleted or modified.<br/>
You should focus more on students' learning not teachers' learning<br/>
Don't try to cover every learning theories, teach the most important one and the crucial strategies or tools.<br/>
You may also included some brain-based learning studies such as how learning occur and what factors may affect learning.<br/>
Conceptual change should be included in this lesson.</li>
<li><p>Are these goals/objectives appropriate for your students?<br/>
These goals are not challenging enough for undergraduates. More critical thinking and challenging tasks should be used in this lesson.<br/>
You can try to related your teaching methods with learning principles and invite students to think both in the role of learners and teacher(your role).</p></li>
<li><p>How were the goals/objectives appropriate for the course in which the unit was taught?<br/>
I found that I simply followed the sequence of the textbook. I may first teach this lesson 'learning theory' (Chapter 4) and then teach 'teaching strategies'(Chapter 3). Students should first know how leaning happen and then learn how to teach.</p></li>
<li><p>How the instructional strategies adequate for the learning you hoped would happen?<br/>
Lecture should be more interactive(share learning experience of yours or students, thinking aloud, student teaching), include more student-centered activities (sorting learning tasks, diagnosing students' learning difficulties, think-pair-share, one minute writing, interpret teaching clips).</p></li>
<li><p>How were the assessments--either formal or informal--adequate(and valid and reliable) for the task of assessing student learning?<br/>
There are two assessments: A1 explain Osmosis to high school students; A2 design a 5E lesson plan. A1 is an informal assessment on class. A2 seems not closely related with this lesson. A better assignment would be study students' preconceptions about one topic and design an activity to elicit students prior ideas.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Task 2 redesign:</h3>

<h4>The big ideas that student should understand:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Learners build their knowledge on their prior knowledge collaboratively in special social context or situations.</li>
<li>Learning occur when connections are made in Neural Networks or social networks.</li>
<li>Well designed physical and social learning environment help students learn by improving their brains' function.</li>
<li>Prior ideas, emotion, metacogniton play crucial roles in students' science learning.</li>
<li>Different learning strategies suit for different learning tasks; Some tasks are more difficult than others; Student percept learning tasks differently.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The skills that student should develop:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Elicit and engage students' prior ideas of a core concept.</li>
<li>Diagnosis students' difficulties in learning a concept.</li>
<li>Design or redesign classroom learning environment to optimize students' learning.</li>
<li>Select proper learning strategies for special learning tasks.</li>
<li>Summary learning research results and its implications for teaching.</li>
</ol>


<h4>The interactive lecture and student activities:</h4>

<p>Tell the story of two kids arguing about sun:</p>

<pre><code>孔子到东方游历，遇见两个小孩在路上争辩，便问原因。一个小孩说：“太阳刚升起时距离人近。”另一个小孩说：“太阳中午的时候才距离人近呢。” 一个小孩又说：“不对，太阳刚升起的时候大得像个车盖，到了正午就小得像一个盘子，这不是远处的看着小而近处的看着大的道理吗？” 另一个小孩说：“太阳刚升起的时候清凉，到了中午的时候像手伸进热水里一样热，这不是近的时候感觉热而远的时候感觉凉的道理吗？”  
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/two-kids-argue-sun.png" alt="tow kids argue sun" /><br/>
Which kid do you agree with?<br/>
How about the situation of winter and summer?<br/>
If you are going to teaching these two kids the model of sun and earth, what are you going to do with these ideas? <br/>
Pretest: What do you know about learning? Yes or No question and why?<br/>
Learning occur easily and fast. Yes No<br/>
Learning is mainly remembering and recalling. Yes NO<br/>
Learning is a process that seldom change. Yes No<br/>
Learning ability can be enhanced though learning effort. Yes No<br/>
How this lesson Connect, extend or challenge what you know and how you teach?</p>

<p>Can you share a impressive learning experience that happened to you before? Or your most powerful learning strategy?</p>

<h4>Different types of learning:</h4>

<p>Learning subject: Machine learning, human learning, animal learning<br/>
Learning method: Discovery learning, guided discovery, inquiry-based learning, Problem-based learning; learning from instruction, rote learning, learning from examples, learning by analogy, explanation-based learning<br/>
Learning object: Conceptural learning(facts, concepts, model, theory), skill learning(process, strategies), emotion, attitude and value learning, metacognitive learning<br/>
Learning result: Deep learning, surface learning, meaningful learning,rote learning,effective or ineffective learning<br/>
Learning effort or emotion: hard learning, lazy learning, happy learning,painful learning<br/>
Learning sensory and style: eye, ear, feel, action, think, taste, smell</p>

<p>What can you learn from the following objective verb table?<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/objective-verb-table.png" alt="objective verbs table" /></p>

<ol>
<li><p>Think-pair-share<br/>
Read a research paper of misconception, write down all possible ways to elicit students' prior ideas, share with peers how these prior ideas are going to affect students' learning.</p></li>
<li><p>Ask a student to thinking aloud about a Buoyancy problem; Ask another student to think aloud about a phototropism problem; Ask the third student to think aloud about a NO2 chemical equilibrium problem. Interview them a little bit.</p></li>
<li><p>Share personal learning strategy (Chemical equilibrium).<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/no2.png" alt="NO2 Chemical equilibrium" /></p></li>
<li><p>One minute writing<br/>
Why students approach the same problem differently? How can you encourage deep learning?</p></li>
<li><p>Sorting learning tasks and matching with learning strategies.<br/>
List as many different types of learning tasks as you can in your group?<br/>
Group them as many ways as you can?</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Sorting learning tasks:<br/>
Write down the definition of enzyme.<br/>
Judge whether x is Enzyme or not.<br/>
Compare Plant and animal cell structures.<br/>
Draw the process of Mitosis.<br/>
Design the law of using human embryonic cells as research materials.<br/>
Count the Probability of a special Phenotype in the next generation.<br/>
Explain why egg shells are not too thin or too thick.</p>

<p>Learning strategies:<br/>
compare and group, summarize, visualize, hands-on, simplize, break down</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Student teaching one concept to other students or one screen to the class.<br/>
They need to be the volunteer and download the material and learn it before class, they have 3 minutes to help group members to understand this concept. Students will share their learning experience and give feedback to the volunteer teacher.</p></li>
<li><p>Diagnosing students' learning difficulties in a teaching clip.<br/>
Teacher will show a clip of real teaching, the students are asked to make sense what is happening and what to do with the situation.</p></li>
<li><p>Write one minute about what you learn or change today about learning, what is your most favorite analogy of learning now, share with your partner.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Task 3 reflect on why you change:</h3>

<p>My previous purpose is follow and cover the most important content both on the textbook and in my vision. I spent a lot of time on how to represent these content to students but did not pay too much attention to how these content serve the goal of this course. At that time, I did not have many activities to choose from and had to create my own one by one. I also had limited knowledge of how students learn science before, now I know more. So I want to include the more important ideas that I know and get rid of un important or unrelated ideas.</p>

<p>Although I believed that I should use more student-centered activities, but I just didn't have them. It took time for me to gather, test, accumulate related activities or ideas. My enriched learning experiences and pedagogical thinking also help me to generate new activities that probably work for my students.</p>

<p>Recently, I read some papers and books about evidence-based teaching and brain-based learning, they also encourage me to select the core ideas and activities for my teaching plan.</p>

<p>Conclusion: If you want to improve your teaching practice, you need to know more about the content, more about your students, more about what you can possibly do and use in your class. Of course, you also have to know what student really learn and why they do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
