<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: UGA | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/uga/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-24T14:12:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modeling activities and reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T23:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I attended Dr Luft's class Methods of Science Teaching. I am becoming more and more interested in Modeling activities and I want to make a collection of these activities.</p>

<p>This is the list:<br/>
-   Candle in the water tube make it go out(Dr Luft's class)<br/>
-   Black box(<a href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=11102">How students learn: science in classroom</a> see Chp 12)<br/>
-   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
-   Secret Tube (Dr C's class)<br/>
-   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
If you have more good modeling activities, welcome recommandations.</p>

<p>These activities provide lots of practice options for science teachers. We usually only provide standards of what students should master but little practice activites for teachers. Well, the <a href="http://www.nextgenscience.org/next-generation-science-standards">Next Generation Standard</a> is going to change this.</p>

<p>Reflections on Modeling in science teaching<br/>
The charm of modeling:<br/>
-   Naturally need students to make careful observation,recording data,drawing conclusions<br/>
-   Naturally engage students' prior ideas for explaination or application<br/>
-   Naturally put students into the test, debate and revisement of their models or prior ideas<br/>
-   Naturally let students experience the full process of science inquiry and nature of science</p>

<p>What to focus in the modeling activites as a science teacher?</p>

<p>How to keep the balance between knowledge-centered and student-centered? Individual and Community? Cognition and metacognition?</p>

<p>Welcome to join the discussion of these open questions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Metaphors of good teacher and education reform]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T22:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/metaphors-of-good-teacher-and-education-reform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A good teacher just like a good cook. Of course, you can tell a good cook by the taste of his dishes. So students' perfect performance is a good predictor of competent teacher. But it takes a lot effort to make the dishes OR evaluate the students. In fact, we can also tell a good cook by his preparation and operation of his cooking.  Good cook can aways make many dishes in a limited time. Because he don't stop, when heating the water, he is washing the vegatables or cutting the meat. When the water is ready he is also ready to fry them together. The teacher do the same thing in class expecially in a short class. I found this metaphor visiting Dr C's class, she give instructions as well as preparing the tools for modeling, at the same time she was also doing demonstration of what the secret tube behaviors.</p>

<p>Sometimes science teacher educators complain that teachers' beliefs are stubborn and reluctant to change their practices. Well, It is true.</p>

<p>The science teacher is like a swimming player in a swimming poor. The science teacher educator stand beside and tell the player how to swim, which style is good which is bad. But the most important thing for a person in the swimming poor is to keep safty and the most reliable style is his primary style. How can we blame them not trying to change, if their safty is not guaranteed and skills not developed.</p>

<p>As a science teacher educator, you can not stand by but jump into the swimming poor and provide necessary skills and safety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Timms video and reflection of teaching science with modeling]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/timms-video-and-reflection-of-teaching-science-with-modeling/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/timms-video-and-reflection-of-teaching-science-with-modeling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is my first time to view a science classroom teaching in Japan. In fact, it supprise me a little. I know the science education in Japan is of high quality. They get much better score than the other counties and teacher are respectable profession. But I never thought the classroom are so interactive and effective. You can click <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">here</a> to view the video.</p>

<blockquote><p>This eighth-grade science lesson is about the formation of clouds. It is the third lesson in a sequence of 19 lessons on weather. The lesson is 53 minutes in duration. There are 25 students in the class.<br/>
<video width='720' height='480' preload='none' controls poster=' https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/timssvideo.png'><source src='http://timssvid1.s3.amazonaws.com/JP5%20Air%20compression%20and%20expansion.mp4' type='video/mp4; codecs="avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2"'/></video></p></blockquote>

<p>Here is my record of the time usage of the class:</p>

<blockquote><p>00-03 review what learnt<br/>
03-07 demistration<br/>
07-17 demistration of key skills for today's experiment<br/>
18-36 Student activites(4 experiments and group take turn)<br/>
36-50 sumary of experiment result and draw conclusion<br/>
50-52 self-evalation</p></blockquote>

<p>I watched the video twice, first I just got a glance of it very quickly. The second time, I watch it very carefully and make notes of what teacher and students were doing.</p>

<p>First, I found a very interesting thing that the Japenese teacher used about 17 minutes to engage students and make demonstration at the begining. He also used about 17 minutes to sumary the results and conclusions at the end of the class. Acording to psychology studies, people are most likely to remember what happened at begining and at the end. People usually can only concentrate for 15 minutes. So most TED videos will not last more than 17 minutes. I don't know if the teacher did it popurely. But he did it really well.</p>

<p>Second, the class is very interesting and vigorous. Students really had fun with the activities and record and try to explain.</p>

<p>Third, it keep a good balance of knowledge-centered and student-centered. The most important ideas and inquiry skills were embodied in student activities.</p>

<p>At last, I want to say although the teacher said nothing about modeling. But he raised a question for students to study.  Students want to explain but had little idea and experieces. So they did the activities that teacher prepared for them. Before experiments, they make their explannation and predictions, they recorded the result on the handouts, they have to revise their explanation and building a more powerful causal model to explain all the phenomenons. So we do can found the shape of modeling in this class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Study life begin in UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/28/study-life-begin-in-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T23:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/07/28/study-life-begin-in-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>我将在佐治亚访学一年，这一年的时间里我想用日志记录。记录我的所看、所感。</p>

<p>7月25号上午9点从上海飞往东京，转机飞亚特兰大。在东京停留了2个小时左右，我趁机买了一些日本的特产，包括绿茶和点心，这些小礼物是给接我的博士生R买的。一路上都很顺利，去亚特兰大的飞机上，坐在我左边的是一个中国人，右边的似乎是一个墨西哥人，很胖很壮，不过也很友善。我填写的海关表时，还向他借了笔，此外也问了他一些关于I94 departure record的问题，他回答的很耐心。</p>

<p>一路上我要莫看录像，要莫睡觉，为倒时差做准备。当然聊的比较多的还是与左边的中国留学生，他在英国留学，这次去美国看妈妈，我问他Groome shutle怎么坐，他说他也要做shutle，后来我给他看手机上的信息，结果其实他也是要做这个shutle的但是不是同一个线路而已。 于是我们商量好一起走。</p>

<p>从飞机下来要走很远，才能到海关检查的地点。然后排队等候，一个旅客无意识掏出了手机，结果给工作人员看见了，要求他拿着手机给检查官看，检查官是个黑人，盘问的半天检查了手机才让他继续排队。原因是这个地方是禁止拍照的。</p>

<p>盘查我的也是那个黑人警官，他问了2个问题，你来美国看什么，你研究什么，还让我出示了邀请信，之后才改了章放我过去。过了海关就去认领行李，一开始我以为应该有工作人员扫描条形码然后给我们行李，结果到了哪啥都没有，就是一个电子牌指示哪个航班的行李在哪个转盘上，我们等了半天，最后我的行李先出来了，由于我的班车是5点多的，我看了时间只有20分钟左右，我就自己先走了。 机场的地图虽然下载过，但是没什么用，有用的还是问路，问了一个警官，他告诉我做3路机场公车就可以，我赶紧去坐车，还好顺利赶到了。</p>

<p>我赶到的时候，只有2位乘客没有上车了，司机是个白人，长头发，很帅气，我告诉他我定了位置，他帮我放好行李，然后查看了记录手册，并让我付钱，结果我拿出一百美元，他说没有零钱。我问是否可以用信用卡，他说可以打电话，于是他帮我打通了电话，我说明了情况，报告了信用卡信息，结果就成功支付了。下车的时候，我看到有乘客给小费，但是很不巧我只有一百美元的，所以我说了谢谢，并解释了一下，他说没关系的。下车有机会再给吧。</p>

<p>我下了shutle，但是发现根本没有人等我，不过刚刚过了3分钟R先生就开车到了。我请他吃了快餐，本来还要买sim卡的，但是兜了很久也没找到，于是他送我去HSC入住。在工作人员的提示下，我填写了几张表格，就拿到了钥匙入住了。悬着的心终于放下来了，美国我来了。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
