<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: UGA | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/uga/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-30T21:06:31-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[科学教法课上的种子萌发实验]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/seed-activity-in-method-of-biology-and-earth-science-teaching/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T19:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/30/seed-activity-in-method-of-biology-and-earth-science-teaching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>我有幸参与了Dr C的三次教法课，每次课一个小时。之所以第一次参与这个课堂，一个很直接的原因是我被一盆开的很漂亮的花吸引了，我想知道老师想用这盆花干什么。<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-19-12.11.21.jpg" alt="漂亮的花朵" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>后面之所以继续参与课堂，则是因为我被课堂的活动吸引了，其中之一就是种子萌发这个活动。<br/>
其实种子萌发这个活动我们也中学也做，不过我中学没做过，因为当时考试不考。这次看外国本科生做这个活动，觉得很新鲜。老师到底想干嘛？<br/>
老师先让学生仔细关注天气预报中的信息，日期，温度，湿度，风力，天气等，那么这些变量可能与植物生长有什么关系呢？植物的生长受哪些因素的影响？如何影响呢？<br/>
带着这些问题，开始进行活动，每个人发一个透明的封口袋还有一些扁豆种子，然后在封口袋中放一张吸水纸，在底端1/3处用订书机打上一排钉子。然后将种子放进去，并且往里面添加一些水。写上姓名和日期。<br/>
这是第一次课8/19的照片：<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-19-12.08.01.jpg" alt="8-19" /><br/>
这是第二次课8/26的照片：<br/>
![8-26a]https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/(2013-08-26-11.07.53.jpg)
![8-26b]https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/(2013-08-26-11.09.46.jpg)
这是第三次课8/30的照片：<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-30-10.56.08.jpg" alt="8-30a" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/2013-08-30-10.56.33.jpg" alt="8-30b" />
第二次课上还没开始前，老师的幻灯片上就要求每个同学对种子萌发的情况进行观察、测量、记录、绘图等。有的学生的种子疯长，有的则还是老样子。他们很兴奋的讨论着这些结果和可能的原因，有的说是温度，有的说是水，有的说是光，五花八门。  <br/>
第三次课上，老师在下课前布置了一个任务，每个学生要用一个大可乐瓶制作一个植物培养瓶，老师提供了样板，学生则需要设计一个实验检验自己的某个假设，可以组成小组合作设计和控制变量。</p>

<p>这些是大四的本科生，他们毕业后可能会当科学教师。这些活动不仅仅是关注在科学研究上，同时教师也在尝试传递Model-based Learning（基于模型的学习）的理念和实践。这不是说教式的探究，而是真刀真枪的用自己的教学方式践行理念。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strong sense of crisis make a nation grow sturdy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/strong-sense-of-crisis-make-a-nation-grow-sturdy/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T15:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/26/strong-sense-of-crisis-make-a-nation-grow-sturdy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People who have strong sense of crisis tend to study and practice hard. Nation with strong sense of crisis is more likely to grow sturdy.</p>

<p>American people and Unite States are good examples.</p>

<p>Here are some pictures evidence.<br/>
The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /><br/>
The safety shower is just at the right of the door.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Safety_Shower.jpg" alt="Emergency Shower in Classroom" /></p>

<p>Im my apartment, there is a white notice like following.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/safetyalert.jpg" alt="Safety Alert in Apartment" /></p>

<p>It doesn't look nice on the door. But it is there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why we teach science in school and how]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T21:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/25/why-we-teach-science-in-school-and-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Why</h3>

<p>It is important for students to survive in such an era full of science and technology products and information.<br/>
It is also important for a country to have enough science literate talents and labors in order to survive in the global economy.<br/>
Why science important? You can go on reading another blog post<a href="http://www.letstalkscience.ca/about-us/why-science">Why science?</a></p>

<h3>We</h3>

<p>Science teacher is a career but also a job. They are playing the most important role in developing the science literacy of the next generation. We choose it and we do it.</p>

<h3>Teach</h3>

<p>Good teaching is not an accident. It is a pursely planed activity fiting students' needs and level.</p>

<h3>Science</h3>

<p>Authentic science not just includ scientific knowledge(facts, concepts, theories), but also the process of science and the nature of science.</p>

<h3>In school</h3>

<p>While school education system is still the dominant formal learning place today. So it is an crutial battle feild of science education. But science learning can happen anywhere not just in school.</p>

<h3>Why has science teaching changed over time?</h3>

<p>Science is changing everyday. New discovery, New papers, New theories and models, in fact science update itself everyday.<br/>
Student is changing every year. Students today are not like before. They have iphone, ipad, facebook. Even kids at the same age in different class response significant differently to the same question.<br/>
Society is changing too. It need more talents who are good at 4Cs: Communication, Collaboration, Critical thinking and Creativity.<br/>
Should science teaching keep the same as before? Never.</p>

<h3>How should science be taught in science classrooms?</h3>

<p>Well, It is really a hard question.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some pictures of UGA]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/24/some-pictures-of-uga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I went to the Main library of UGA. I had a task to search a journal from 1980 to 1990. It was my first time to be there. To my suprise, nobody stopped me to check my UGA card. So I just went around and check out the journels. It means everybody can come in and take a seat to read. It is great! The frist floor is very big and open. The book and magzines are located in the center, surrounded by many groups of tables, seats and computers. Although many students studying there, it was very quiet. I ask a library staff how to find the journal, he helped me to check it out in his computer and told me it is located at the second floor and it is also available online. So I just came out. It was at the noon, I took a picture of the main library, it is beautiful. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/library.jpg" alt="Main Library of UGA" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>
I also found some interesting things at Aderhold where College of Education located. The first thing was the emergency chair at the corner of stairwell. You can break the window and use the chair to take somebody hurt going downstairs. What a considerate safety concern! You can find an emergency shower at every classroom, which hardly seen in Chinese classroom.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/dangerchair.jpg" alt="Emergency Chair in Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I entered the building in the morning, I found there were lots of names on the bricks. I guess there are the names of professors who had worked there. <br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/stopread.jpg" alt="Stop reading go to study" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/namebricks.jpg" alt="Name bricks in front of Aderhold" /></p>

<p>When I kept looking, I saw a brick which said: "stop read the bricks, go to study". I smiled and entered the building.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modeling activities and reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T23:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/08/19/modeling-activities-and-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I attended Dr Luft's class Methods of Science Teaching. I am becoming more and more interested in Modeling activities and I want to make a collection of these activities.</p>

<p>This is the list:<br/>
-   Candle in the water tube make it go out(Dr Luft's class)<br/>
-   Black box(<a href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=11102">How students learn: science in classroom</a> see Chp 12)<br/>
-   Timms video <a href="http://timssvideo.com/72">JP5 AIR COMPRESSION AND EXPANSION</a><br/>
-   Secret Tube (Dr C's class)<br/>
-   Next Generation Science Standards <a href="http://concord.org/ngss/">simulation activities in Concord</a><br/>
If you have more good modeling activities, welcome recommandations.</p>

<p>These activities provide lots of practice options for science teachers. We usually only provide standards of what students should master but little practice activites for teachers. Well, the <a href="http://www.nextgenscience.org/next-generation-science-standards">Next Generation Standard</a> is going to change this.</p>

<p>Reflections on Modeling in science teaching<br/>
The charm of modeling:<br/>
-   Naturally need students to make careful observation,recording data,drawing conclusions<br/>
-   Naturally engage students' prior ideas for explaination or application<br/>
-   Naturally put students into the test, debate and revisement of their models or prior ideas<br/>
-   Naturally let students experience the full process of science inquiry and nature of science</p>

<p>What to focus in the modeling activites as a science teacher?</p>

<p>How to keep the balance between knowledge-centered and student-centered? Individual and Community? Cognition and metacognition?</p>

<p>Welcome to join the discussion of these open questions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
