<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: UGA | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/uga/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-24T12:34:27-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ecojustice work]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/15/ecojustice-work/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-15T20:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/15/ecojustice-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>share a film clip that portrays an environemntal meassage<br/>
美丽的大脚</p>

<p>photo essay</p>

<p>sustainability share-a-thon</p>

<p>book study</p>

<p>nature principle presentation</p>

<p>memory banking<br/>
pick a community practice and interview some people who participate in this practice to grow your knowledge about this practice. I selected foot ball as both comercial and community practice. I wrote a post about foot ball.</p>

<p>Citizen Science<br/>
Citizen science (also known as crowd science, crowd-sourced science, civic science, or networked science) is scientific research conducted, in whole or in part, by amateur or nonprofessional scientists, often by crowdsourcing and crowdfunding. Formally, citizen science has been defined as "the systematic collection and analysis of data; development of technology; testing of natural phenomena; and the dissemination of these activities by researchers on a primarily avocational basis".[1] Citizen science is sometimes called "public participation in scientific research."[2]<br/>
[1] "Finalizing a Definition of "Citizen Science" and "Citizen Scientists"". OpenScientist. 2011-09-03. Retrieved 2012-10-11.<br/>
[2] Hand, E. (2010). "Citizen science: People power". Nature 466 (7307): 685–687. doi:10.1038/466685a. PMID 20686547<br/>
from: wikipedia</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why football is so influential in US]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/11/why-football-is-so-influential-in-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-11T11:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/11/why-football-is-so-influential-in-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Football is very influential in United States.</p>

<p>If you walk in the streets in Athens, you will see bulldogs everywhere, not the real bulldog but the statues, pictures, logos of bulldogs. Why? Because bulldog is the nickname of their UGA football team and it is also the mascot of their team.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bulldog.png" alt="bulldog Uga" /></p>

<p>When you take buses, you can see slogans such as "Go Dawgs!" "Beat Kentucky!" on the screen of the UGA buses. The University even made a special holiday for students to watch football game. A professor told me this story. When there was a game in Florida vs Georgia Bulldog, many students dropped the class to go to Florida to watch the game. So the university decided to make this Friday a holiday for students.</p>

<p>The football game is a full day events on Saturday. When there is a home base game in Sanford stadium, many people come to enjoy the game, the road becomes very crowed and it is so inconvenient and expensive to park that many people nearby decide to walk nearly an hour to get the stadium. People usually wear some red, such as red T-shirt or hat. A home base ticket cost 50~200$ according to the position of the seats. So it is not cheap, and most people would go game for five or six times in a year, which means they will spend about 500$ for game. Why they would like to spent so much money and time on football? Well, the answer is it is not only a game.</p>

<p>Before entering the stadium, people often bring there lunch and eat together siting somewhere. This is called "Tailgating". Some people even use their car to make tent and bring their TV set and have a barbecue in their auto tent. In the tailgating, every people prepare some dishes, and share with each other, it is not only a time to eat but also to chat with leacher other and get known to each other.</p>

<p>Every time I went to the football game, there are some events. Sometimes they are honor events. University professors, athletes or players, all the outstanding people in many field come to the ground to show up in front of audience, it is a great honor to be on the green ground. Sometimes they are surprising events. The first time I went football, I saw a solider appear in the ground and gave his family a big surprise after honored on the ground. The mother ran to his son and hug him, it is so touching, tears welled from many audience's faces.</p>

<p>In the second game I visited, the senior students were going to leave the game ground, so they come and give a performance of instrumental ensemble, the audience flag "Once Dawg always Dawg", the cheer team print "Georgia Senior" and "Senior" on their T shirt or bodies. The flags were small; One or two people can held them; People might made them by themselves.</p>

<p>The game is interactive and full of passion. The stadium is full of red people raising their flag or hands and sing the same song at the start of the game. During the game, the players would encourage the audience to make noise to cheer for their offence or defense. There is also some game for audience to guess which cup contain the food on the big screen. Many photographers stand around the stadium not only record what happen on ground but also in audience seats. They would project audience on the big screen, such as little boy, girl, beauties, man, old women. People become very exited when their image is on the big screen. There are lots ways for audiences to cheer for their team including both lingual and body lauguage.</p>

<p>In fact, Saturday football has become a part of American life, just like Sunday church. On Monday class, students usually greeting each other by asking "Did you go to the game?" And then they start talk about the game.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observe US science classroom: AP chemistry class]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/20/observe-us-science-education/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-20T21:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/20/observe-us-science-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I visited a AP chemistry class in a high school. I found this class is apparently test driven. The teacher first let the students took a test for 15 minutes. And then coped with students' individual questions and worksheet related issues. Then he began teach students the rules and tips to get right answers to the questions. Once a time, a student asked when they would do laboratory. The answer was "maybe next week".</p>

<p>The whole class last 90 minutes, which is twice long of class in China. There was a 5-10 minutes break during the class. There about 30 students in the classroom. The topic of this class included Ionic bond,Covalent bond, Polar and non-polar Molecular, Melting point, Atomic properties. The main objective is to learn how to judge which Molecular have higher melting point or stronger bond for the quiz questions. This class was a teacher-dominated class. Teacher used most of the time to lecture the "powerful" tips to solve these type of questions. About 20 students seemed listen carefully and 10 students enraged in the conversations by asking questions. Teacher usually addressed students questions immediately sometimes said he would addressed that question later. There were several times students want to ask questions, but the teacher went along with the important tips and principles.</p>

<p>To my surprise, there was a student had nothing to do and lay on the ground listen Mp3. The student said something to the teacher before class, the teacher just let him go. This will never be allowed in Chinese classroom. There are some student hard to like too in China, but mostly they will not put their feet on their desk or sleep on the ground. The teacher will never allow this happen too.</p>

<p>While the teacher also tried to help student understand what factors affect the strength of a bond. He wrote down the Electric force formula on white board. He also used an analogy of 10 toy between boys and girls to explain Polar and non-polar. I am very interested in this representation, it tell me something about the teacher's stratiges to convey the concept to students, researchers name this knowledge as Pedagogical Content Knowledge. This representation do help to understand polar and non-polar, the teacher said that think about a group of boys have 5 toy and the girl group also have 5 toy, then it is equal, so in this case the bond is non-polar band. As to polar bond, the teacher let students thought about boys had 7 toy while girls only have 3 toy, this is polar bond. As to ionic bond, the boy just got all the toys while girls have no toys. I agreed this analogy could convey some important features of the concept to students. But if you think carefully, this representation also has fatal limitations and even wrong. First, Electron pair does not "belong to" each side but "shared". Second, it is dynamic not static. Third, it is not how many electrons each side have, but how frequently it appears around. Well, teacher can use analogies as middle models to help students learn, but it is also necessary to know the limitations of every middle models and move along to the more scientific models.</p>

<p>On my road home, I watched a TED show <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rrkrvAUbU9Y">Dan Pink: The puzzle of motivation</a>. The speaker talked about higher motivation(big award) can impede or even kill creativity(e.g. developing new software). I want to say it may also be true in education, while teacher highly motivated to prepare students to get better score, they will decrease the variety of teaching methods until only lecture left. It had happened in China, US would not like to fall into the same old trap again.</p>

<p>2014-04-23<br/>
When we are developing an instrument to measure teachers CK, Ben gave us a good analogy of chemical reaction. It is much better than the above chemistry teacher.</p>

<pre><code>The force holding bonds in place is due to the net electrostatic attraction between protons and electrons of bonding species. This is akin to the force holding two magnets together. The attraction between two magnets is stronger when they are close together (a strong “bond”) and weaker when they are farther apart (a weak “bond”). It takes energy to move magnets apart—going from a strong bond to a weak bond. When magnets are allowed to come together—moving from a relatively weak to a relatively strong attraction—kinetic energy is given off, and work can be done. Thus, magnets at a distance have more potential energy than magnets in close proximity. Weak bonds have more potential chemical energy than strong bonds.
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let us do 'lecture']]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/15/let-us-do-lecture/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T12:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/15/let-us-do-lecture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I participated the method class by Dr. Luft and responsed to her question "How students learn best? by rehearing something, learning the vocabulary, or by doing science".</p>

<p>My response was: the answer was obvious doing science will let student learn most, but if we take out of the word "best", all approaches can help student learn in special situations.</p>

<p>I know it is a little misleading and I am afraid that some students in the classroom might misunderstood me. Well, by saying that, I don't mean we should really repeat our explanations to students again and again or let students master only vocabularies or terms. But I do want say we should not put 'lecture' on the opposite side of 'inquiry'. I also want to point out that we should be very careful to use these two words to label teaching practices, especially those of student teachers.</p>

<p>Well, lecture, You can lecture; Some teacher is only able to lecture. But if you decide to use lecture, try to do it good. Because lecture can be totally different styles and outcomings.</p>

<p>It is interesting -- we did not teach student teachers how to lecture, although this conception exist in their mind, and they are very likely to use this approach in the beginning of their carriers -- isn't it.</p>

<p>Ok, let's do lecture.(really?)<br/>
There are different levels of lectures.<br/>
1.  Some teacher just stands there and say something, whether related or not. Student are very easily lost interests and get boring and then sleeping. Sometime they appear awake, but their mind are sleep.<br/>
2.  Some teacher stand there say something interesting, student are engaged and listen carefully, some can even retell the interesting stories to others. It is better, right.<br/>
3.  Some stand there say something putting students on uncomfortable positions, let students think critically about the dilemma or issues and discuss with each other, which may have a profound impact on what students believe and act in the future.</p>

<p>Some lecturer also do some performance or something tricky or funny; Some lecture even let audience participate, here is a example of <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZGY0wPAnus">TED lecture: the art of misdirection</a>. Whether lecture or inquiry, they are just labels. Label itself can not guarantee your teaching quality and students' learning outcomes. We should keep this in mind.</p>

<p>In fact, what teachers can do and only do is create learning opportunity by engaging student in learning activities. Student learn new knowledge through their learning experience. But, different learning experience have different consequences. The following is the learning pyriod.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/learningpyramid.png" alt="learning pyramid" /></p>

<p>You can see from the picture above, student can sit and listen, learn by listening and reading. This process just get information into their short term memory not long term memory. So they may just listen and forget, rarely transfer the new knowledge into new situations.</p>

<p>They can also study by doing science,trying to figure out questions such as what can I do with this stuff ? How to relate all these stuff? What data to collect? How to collect? What is happening? What is going to happen? Why it happen? Why it doesn't happen? and so on. This approach not only work on the working memory, but also interact with the long term memory -- their prior ideas and conceptual frameworks. They have to recall what they had learned and experienced in order to solve all these problems.</p>

<p>In the learning pyramid, the most effective way is learning by teaching,just as what the student teacher are doing now. Usually we suppose student teachers already have enough content knowledge for teaching the topic, but it is not true. Many studies showed that beginning teachers' content knowledge are usually Fragmented and less connected, it was also structured for doing test not teaching.<a href="#1">1</a> Maybe it is enough for exam but not enough for teaching.</p>

<p>Inquiry research showed that good inquiry are significantly better than lecture, but it has a precondition -- the teacher have good knowledge ground.<a href="#2">2</a> Carlsen (1991) reported that when teaching self-identified high knowledge topics, teacher were more likely to ask more high level questions than teaching low knowledge topics.<a href="#3">3</a> But student teachers usually lack of this ground, they are struggling with integrating inquiry into their lessons. It is not an easy thing achieved overnight, but a step by step continuing process.</p>

<p>Recently, I read a book review <a href="http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108010/chapters/Learning,-or-Not-Learning,-in-School.aspx">Learning,or not Learning,in school</a>. The author of the book argued teacher can not give a model or demonstration, and then let student follow the model to do on their own(the mistake I also made in my teaching). There should be some middle stages, such as discussing or doing together or let students do it collaborative, before let them do it by their own. The big idea is Gradually ownership shifting, or gradual release of responsibility. It is not a new idea, but I like it.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/learningshift.png" alt="learning shift" /><br/>
This picture is from: <a href="http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108010/chapters/Learning,-or-Not-Learning,-in-School.aspx">Learning,or not Learning,in school</a></p>

<p>As you can see in the picture, the middles stages Guided Instruction(we do it) and Collaborative(you do it together) sometimes is missing our teaching. This may explain why students can't do it well as teacher expected, because the learning process is too sharp.</p>

<p>Why I want to highlight the point that DO NOT put lecture in the opposite position of Inquiry, I have other concerns. Try to think:<br/>
What happen if student teacher believe in inquiry but can not do it well?<br/>
==>They drop out. Because they tend to believe themselves not suitable for teaching.</p>

<p>Another extreme concern is:<br/>
What happen if teacher only believe lecture and only one direction approach?<br/>
==>They refuse to change and can't do a good job,finally they may drop out.</p>

<p>Usually, student teacher know they should do inquiry or make their class more interactive, but they are just not able to do it or feel too hard to do it. Why this happen? What to do with this? If this doesn't change, they will form a belief that inquiry doesn't suit them or their teaching. It is a hot potato. Well one possible approach to this problem is "we do it together".</p>

<p>We were taught to not label students, right? We also should avoid to label teachers. Abused labels can cause problems even disasters, for example, students who labeled themselves as visual learner would say, I can't learn very well because the teacher used very little pictures, simulations. Really? In fact, the label just limit students' learning approaches instead of expand their ways of learning. Good learner should use every possible way to learn and develop skills respectively.</p>

<p>Who should take the responsibility for learning? Teacher? Students? Or both? Or the responsibility gradually shift from teacher to students?</p>

<p>What strategies or methods are suitable for this shifting?</p>

<p>These are the questions that are worth to think over.</p>

<p>References:<br/>
<a id="1">[1]</a> Hauslein, P. L., Good, R. G., &amp; Cummins, C. L. (1992). Biology content cognitive structure: From science student to science teacher. Journal of Research in Science Teaching, 29(9), 939-964.<br/>
<a id="2">[2]</a> Blanchard, M. R., Southerland, S. A., Osborne, J. W., Sampson, V. D., Annetta, L. A., &amp; Granger, E. M. (2010). Is inquiry possible in light of accountability?: A quantitative comparison of the relative effectiveness of guided inquiry and verification laboratory instruction. Science Education, 94(4), 577-616.<br/>
<a id="3">[3]</a> Carlsen, W. S. (1991). Effects of new biology teachers' subject‐matter knowledge on curricular planning. Science Education, 75(6), 631-647.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HungerU]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T14:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/12/hungeru</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I went to MLC to attend a lecture by Dr Michelle Smith. In front of MLC, I saw a strange thing. You can see the picture below.
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/hungeru.png" alt="hungeru" /></p>

<p>The fact and statistics is printed on it. Food still occupy a large percentage(39.8%) in their total household spend. In Congo, 70% goes to food, it means people there are more likely in hunger.</p>

<p>I asked where is the data from? They told me they gathered these data last Saturday, and the survey is still going on.</p>

<p>How can I participate? I asked. Just let people know this fact and then we can change this fact and statistic. Isn't it a good idea? College students may not give money directly, but they can collect data and spread the fact all over the world.</p>

<p>Although the program is funded by Farm Journal Foundation, I guess volunteer college students played a role in the Survey and HungerU Tour in different countries. This is the responsibility that our college students are able to and should shoulder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
