<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: UGA | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/uga/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-14T15:02:04-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The trees that owns itself]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/14/the-trees-that-owns-itself/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-14T14:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/14/the-trees-that-owns-itself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a happy time of lunch, Julie drived us to see a tree that owns itself. It took us only several minutes to get there from the Grit.</p>

<p>Here is the picture of the tree.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/tree-owns-itself.png" alt="Tree owns itself" /></p>

<p>The owner of the nearby house loved this tree too much, he wanted to protect the tree as long as possible. So he claimde that he conveyed the right of this tree and nearyby land to this tree itself.</p>

<p>The view of values of Americans are well presented in this tree. They love and respect nature and the natural organism. They also respect and trust laws. There are more williing to share and respect other peoples love and willings.</p>

<p>This cultural values may answer at leat partly the questions: why the sky is still blue and the water is still clean; why birds sing in the morning and squrales run around; why people like to go nature for holiday and spend more money to buy green electricity.</p>

<p>This may be the big thing that China lacks and we want to rebuild, in both Chinese culture and education system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why it is so hard to bridge the theory-practice gap]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/why-it-is-so-hard-to-bridge-the-theory-practice-gap/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T10:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/06/11/why-it-is-so-hard-to-bridge-the-theory-practice-gap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Oliver let us read this following paper and write one or two paragraph of summary.<br/>
Nuthall, G. (2004). Relating Classroom Teaching to Student Learning: A Critical Analysis of Why Research Has Failed to Bridge the Theory-Practice Gap. Harvard Educational Review, 74(3), 273–307.</p>

<p>It is good paper to read, although it is a little long for non-native English speaker.</p>

<p>Here is what I got:</p>

<p>It matters how teacher look at and use educational research.<br/>
Is this why western culture emphase qualitative studies than quantitative studies?<br/>
The precondition of this approach is that teacher education help teachers do so. So it should be one topic in teacher education program.<br/>
why research necessary for teacher development<br/>
what research questions are more hard to know by only practicing<br/>
What relationship existes between teaching and learning</p>

<p>Why educational research is necessary:<br/>
1 teacher hard to see learning evidence (only some students)<br/>
2 reseach can help identify teachers' tacit beliefs and limitations<br/>
3 learning in students' mind are not easy to see by teachers where research should help.</p>

<p>learning is an inner process that can not easily seen<br/>
Research should help teacher see this process</p>

<p>Teachers need an explanatory theory of the teaching-learning relationship that meets these
requirements in order to plan, carry out, and evaluate their daily activi- ties effectively and efficiently(Floden, 2001; Levin &amp; ODonnell, 1999).</p>

<p>Teachers usually take teaching-learning consequence for granted and when it don't it is student to blame.</p>

<p>Classroom 3 layers:<br/>
visible activities and behaviors<br/>
semi-visible stu-stu<br/>
semivisible individual stu</p>

<p>what role student-private-talk play in student learning(online learning sometimes is the case when learners do not interact with peers.)</p>

<p>understanding how teaching is related to learning requires an understanding of:<br/>
1. teacher influence<br/>
2. sociocultural influence<br/>
3. student make sense of their classroom experience</p>

<p>a theory of effective teaching is still needed in order to know when to look and what to look for when you observe the teachers classroom activities.</p>

<p>Best of these studies had two enormous advantages over previous research:<br/>
First, they were based on systematic observation or audio- and video-recording of teacher and student behavior. Second, independent measures of student learning that were directly related to the student experi- ences being observed were used in almost all of the best studies.</p>

<p>Teachers themselves are not always good at rating student achievement, as their ratings tend to be strongly affected by student behavior and motivation, crediting the most attentive and interested with higher achievement (Gold- enberg, Gallimore, Reese, &amp; Garnier, 2001)</p>

<p>The problem of process-product studies or careless quantitative studies is neglecting the context and other students out of</p>

<p>The study, however, is of little use in advancing our knowledge about the teaching-learning relationship</p>

<p>I have already made the point that teachers cannot be aware of critical elements in the
teaching-learning process in their own classrooms unless they already have a clear understanding of what to look for and have additional ways of observing or recording the experiences of individual students.</p>

<p>If you simply looked at the post-test totals, you would incorrectly assume that the more able learned more than the less able.</p>

<p>But it cannot produce generalizable knowledge (or an evi- dence based explanatory theory) of the relationships between the alternative versions of the visible structure and the basis model (to use Oser and Baeriswyls model) that can be transferred from classroom to classroom.</p>

<p>It has been claimed that how students learn and how their learning is shaped by the actions of the teacher is always unique and context dependent (Barab &amp; Kirschner, 2001; Bolster, 1983). This claim is both true and not true.</p>

<p>Part of the professional knowledge of teachers must be the distinction between what is unique to a specific context and what is generalizable across all students and/or contexts. While the latter is the proper focus of research on the teaching-learning relationship, an adequate explanatory theory should help us to distinguish between the two.</p>

<p>individual case studies of teaching, provided they include data about student experience and learning that can be directly connected to observations of specific classroom activities, can provide invaluable insights into the processes that lie behind the teaching-learning relationship.(baby project)</p>

<p>I believe that the professional knowledge base that is most needed to improve the quality of teaching and teacher education is knowledge about the ways in which classroom activities, including teaching, affect the changes taking place in the minds of students: what students know and believe and what they can do with their knowledge (what I have called above practical explanatory theory). At the heart of the problem that teachers face in the classroom is knowing what is going on in the minds of the students (Steffe, Thompson, &amp; von Glasersfeld, 2000).</p>

<p>Suggestions for future studies:<br/>
1. Independent in-depth assessment of what students learn.<br/>
2. Complete, continuous data on individual student experience.<br/>
3. Complete, continuous data on classroom activities.<br/>
4. Analysis based on the continuous connections among classroom activities, student experiences, and learning processes.<br/>
5. Avoid the aggregation of data.<br/>
6. Explanatory theory must be directly and transparently connected to relevant evidence.</p>

<p>Reference:<br/>
Nuthall, G. (2004). Relating Classroom Teaching to Student Learning: A Critical Analysis of Why Research Has Failed to Bridge the Theory-Practice Gap. Harvard Educational Review, 74(3), 273–307.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ecojustice work]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/15/ecojustice-work/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-15T20:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2014/04/15/ecojustice-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>share a film clip that portrays an environemntal meassage<br/>
美丽的大脚</p>

<p>photo essay</p>

<p>sustainability share-a-thon</p>

<p>book study</p>

<p>nature principle presentation</p>

<p>memory banking<br/>
pick a community practice and interview some people who participate in this practice to grow your knowledge about this practice. I selected foot ball as both comercial and community practice. I wrote a post about foot ball.</p>

<p>Citizen Science<br/>
Citizen science (also known as crowd science, crowd-sourced science, civic science, or networked science) is scientific research conducted, in whole or in part, by amateur or nonprofessional scientists, often by crowdsourcing and crowdfunding. Formally, citizen science has been defined as "the systematic collection and analysis of data; development of technology; testing of natural phenomena; and the dissemination of these activities by researchers on a primarily avocational basis".[1] Citizen science is sometimes called "public participation in scientific research."[2]<br/>
[1] "Finalizing a Definition of "Citizen Science" and "Citizen Scientists"". OpenScientist. 2011-09-03. Retrieved 2012-10-11.<br/>
[2] Hand, E. (2010). "Citizen science: People power". Nature 466 (7307): 685–687. doi:10.1038/466685a. PMID 20686547<br/>
from: wikipedia</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why football is so influential in US]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/11/why-football-is-so-influential-in-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-11T11:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/12/11/why-football-is-so-influential-in-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Football is very influential in United States.</p>

<p>If you walk in the streets in Athens, you will see bulldogs everywhere, not the real bulldog but the statues, pictures, logos of bulldogs. Why? Because bulldog is the nickname of their UGA football team and it is also the mascot of their team.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/bulldog.png" alt="bulldog Uga" /></p>

<p>When you take buses, you can see slogans such as "Go Dawgs!" "Beat Kentucky!" on the screen of the UGA buses. The University even made a special holiday for students to watch football game. A professor told me this story. When there was a game in Florida vs Georgia Bulldog, many students dropped the class to go to Florida to watch the game. So the university decided to make this Friday a holiday for students.</p>

<p>The football game is a full day events on Saturday. When there is a home base game in Sanford stadium, many people come to enjoy the game, the road becomes very crowed and it is so inconvenient and expensive to park that many people nearby decide to walk nearly an hour to get the stadium. People usually wear some red, such as red T-shirt or hat. A home base ticket cost 50~200$ according to the position of the seats. So it is not cheap, and most people would go game for five or six times in a year, which means they will spend about 500$ for game. Why they would like to spent so much money and time on football? Well, the answer is it is not only a game.</p>

<p>Before entering the stadium, people often bring there lunch and eat together siting somewhere. This is called "Tailgating". Some people even use their car to make tent and bring their TV set and have a barbecue in their auto tent. In the tailgating, every people prepare some dishes, and share with each other, it is not only a time to eat but also to chat with leacher other and get known to each other.</p>

<p>Every time I went to the football game, there are some events. Sometimes they are honor events. University professors, athletes or players, all the outstanding people in many field come to the ground to show up in front of audience, it is a great honor to be on the green ground. Sometimes they are surprising events. The first time I went football, I saw a solider appear in the ground and gave his family a big surprise after honored on the ground. The mother ran to his son and hug him, it is so touching, tears welled from many audience's faces.</p>

<p>In the second game I visited, the senior students were going to leave the game ground, so they come and give a performance of instrumental ensemble, the audience flag "Once Dawg always Dawg", the cheer team print "Georgia Senior" and "Senior" on their T shirt or bodies. The flags were small; One or two people can held them; People might made them by themselves.</p>

<p>The game is interactive and full of passion. The stadium is full of red people raising their flag or hands and sing the same song at the start of the game. During the game, the players would encourage the audience to make noise to cheer for their offence or defense. There is also some game for audience to guess which cup contain the food on the big screen. Many photographers stand around the stadium not only record what happen on ground but also in audience seats. They would project audience on the big screen, such as little boy, girl, beauties, man, old women. People become very exited when their image is on the big screen. There are lots ways for audiences to cheer for their team including both lingual and body lauguage.</p>

<p>In fact, Saturday football has become a part of American life, just like Sunday church. On Monday class, students usually greeting each other by asking "Did you go to the game?" And then they start talk about the game.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observe US science classroom: AP chemistry class]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/20/observe-us-science-education/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-20T21:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2013/11/20/observe-us-science-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I visited a AP chemistry class in a high school. I found this class is apparently test driven. The teacher first let the students took a test for 15 minutes. And then coped with students' individual questions and worksheet related issues. Then he began teach students the rules and tips to get right answers to the questions. Once a time, a student asked when they would do laboratory. The answer was "maybe next week".</p>

<p>The whole class last 90 minutes, which is twice long of class in China. There was a 5-10 minutes break during the class. There about 30 students in the classroom. The topic of this class included Ionic bond,Covalent bond, Polar and non-polar Molecular, Melting point, Atomic properties. The main objective is to learn how to judge which Molecular have higher melting point or stronger bond for the quiz questions. This class was a teacher-dominated class. Teacher used most of the time to lecture the "powerful" tips to solve these type of questions. About 20 students seemed listen carefully and 10 students enraged in the conversations by asking questions. Teacher usually addressed students questions immediately sometimes said he would addressed that question later. There were several times students want to ask questions, but the teacher went along with the important tips and principles.</p>

<p>To my surprise, there was a student had nothing to do and lay on the ground listen Mp3. The student said something to the teacher before class, the teacher just let him go. This will never be allowed in Chinese classroom. There are some student hard to like too in China, but mostly they will not put their feet on their desk or sleep on the ground. The teacher will never allow this happen too.</p>

<p>While the teacher also tried to help student understand what factors affect the strength of a bond. He wrote down the Electric force formula on white board. He also used an analogy of 10 toy between boys and girls to explain Polar and non-polar. I am very interested in this representation, it tell me something about the teacher's stratiges to convey the concept to students, researchers name this knowledge as Pedagogical Content Knowledge. This representation do help to understand polar and non-polar, the teacher said that think about a group of boys have 5 toy and the girl group also have 5 toy, then it is equal, so in this case the bond is non-polar band. As to polar bond, the teacher let students thought about boys had 7 toy while girls only have 3 toy, this is polar bond. As to ionic bond, the boy just got all the toys while girls have no toys. I agreed this analogy could convey some important features of the concept to students. But if you think carefully, this representation also has fatal limitations and even wrong. First, Electron pair does not "belong to" each side but "shared". Second, it is dynamic not static. Third, it is not how many electrons each side have, but how frequently it appears around. Well, teacher can use analogies as middle models to help students learn, but it is also necessary to know the limitations of every middle models and move along to the more scientific models.</p>

<p>On my road home, I watched a TED show <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rrkrvAUbU9Y">Dan Pink: The puzzle of motivation</a>. The speaker talked about higher motivation(big award) can impede or even kill creativity(e.g. developing new software). I want to say it may also be true in education, while teacher highly motivated to prepare students to get better score, they will decrease the variety of teaching methods until only lecture left. It had happened in China, US would not like to fall into the same old trap again.</p>

<p>2014-04-23<br/>
When we are developing an instrument to measure teachers CK, Ben gave us a good analogy of chemical reaction. It is much better than the above chemistry teacher.</p>

<pre><code>The force holding bonds in place is due to the net electrostatic attraction between protons and electrons of bonding species. This is akin to the force holding two magnets together. The attraction between two magnets is stronger when they are close together (a strong “bond”) and weaker when they are farther apart (a weak “bond”). It takes energy to move magnets apart—going from a strong bond to a weak bond. When magnets are allowed to come together—moving from a relatively weak to a relatively strong attraction—kinetic energy is given off, and work can be done. Thus, magnets at a distance have more potential energy than magnets in close proximity. Weak bonds have more potential chemical energy than strong bonds.
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
