<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tags: UBC | Chunlei's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/tag/ubc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-20T21:19:32-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[chunlei]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticism is not critical thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-19T19:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/19/criticize-is-not-critical-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today Tony asked our students to make up a skit to show their image of schooling. This activity provide opportunities for students to speak English and express their ideas or images of schooling which may be the first step to realize and change their own teaching perspective.</p>

<p>During the activities, an interesting phenomenon showed up. Most of them criticized the education they had in China. While,it was true that the Chinese education had many problems. But, the thinking and reasoning of the problematic educational phenomenon is shallow, or not deep enough, in other word, critical thinking is not criticism.</p>

<p>In order to get more from this activity, students should not jump up to conclusion too quickly. They should not ignore the context that these things took place, the social context, the historical context, the economic context, the physical context, and so on. They should also rethink the theories and rationals behind their judgement and carefully examine the proof and logic. In short, critical thinking should take the place of criticism.</p>

<p>Why harsh criticism of people's own education is not good even harmful? First, it easily leads to extreme and skin deep thinking which block more intellectual endeavor. Second, it hurt their self-image and self-confidence. Third, it can easily separate their connection with the previous themselves and places. Extreme criticisms call abandon or escape but not improvement and responsibility. Try to think of place-based learning, it heals the disconnection between people and places while harsh criticism do the opposite.</p>

<p>According to Daniel T. Willingham, critical thinking have three key features: effectiveness, novelty, and self-direction. Critical thinking is effective in that it avoids common pitfalls, such as seeing only one side of an issue, discounting new evidence that disconfirms your ideas, reasoning from passion rather than logic, failing to support statemnts with evidence, and so on.
Critical thinkiing is novel in that you don't simply remember a solution or a situation that is similar enough to guide you. Using a complex algorithm to solve a math problem is not critical thinking. But devising a new algorithm is. Critical thinking is self-directed in that the thinker must be calling the shot: awards or punishment will disrupt instead of promote critical thinking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Norma Rose Point School]]></title>
    <link href="http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T22:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zhangchunlei.com/blog/2017/01/18/papep-norma-rose-point-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have been in BC for 3days. Everything is new for our ECNU students, the beautiful campus of UBC, the long NO 44 bus, the comfortable Landmark hotel, the nice professors and staffs, the exciting learning activities.</p>

<p>Today is even special. We went to visit a middle school called <a href="http://go.vsb.bc.ca/schools/normarosepoint/Pages/default.aspx">Norma Rose Point School</a>. The school is not far from UBC, in fact it is the neighborhood of UBC. It took us about 20 or 30 minutes to walk there from Scarfe building where our classroom located. There are about six hundreds of students in the school, from kindergarten to grade 8, including both elementary and secondary stages. This school is very unique because of its educational rationals and teaching building design.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/ROSE_Point_school.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>They believe learning should be intergrated and take place in communities instead of separated and in classrooms of each discipline. They want to give student a whole picture of the world and want them to experience this by themselves in their learning communities. In this way, students get better understanding of who they are, where they come form, how they will change the world around them. They will also take more responsibility of their learning and be proactive to inquiry the world around them rather listen to the teacher and memorize for tests.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/global_issues.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/Community_learning_outcome.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The learning schedule and activities are designed and carried out by a faculty team but not a single teacher as traditionally school usually do. The teacher love this kind of collaborative teaching, it also give teacher many opportunities to learn from each others. It is much easier for new teacher to join the team to teach together. As you can see, they value collaboration very much. Student collaborate with student, teachers and even parents. Teacher collaborate with colleges, parents, and university professors. Student who are good at something can teach others. Teacher can do the same thing. They are all super heroes at that time. Super hero is a learning activity designed by the 4th grade teacher team which engage students and let them rethink what a hero means.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/grade4_learning_schedual.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Many features of the school building reflect educational wisdom. They make a window to let student who play basketball to look downstairs and notice what is happening in the football playground. All the classrooms are open without a door but only three or two walls. It means guests are always welcome to join or observe the class. There are also lots of art crafts made by student to show their understanding of their school spirits.<br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/art_crafts.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<img src="https://raw.github.com/lukezhg/Freyja/master/open_classroom.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>It is hard to believe such an ideal school existed and survived. ARE there any disadvantages and challenges for this kind of school? Of course there are, but who can deny their bold spirit and unique learning place design. It is beautiful! That is enough for now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
